<article class="specification" id="chimera">
	<title>Chimera-class</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup role="Maintainer">
			<author>
				<firstname>Bradley</firstname>
				<surname>Joy</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Primary Designers">
			<author>
				<firstname>Bradley</firstname>
				<surname>Joy</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Original Designers">
			<author>
				<firstname>Bradley</firstname>
				<surname>Joy</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword role="service">PC</keyword>
			<keyword role="category">Researcher</keyword>
			<keyword role="variant">Light</keyword>
			<keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>4 April 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Engineering Director Bret Godfrey</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>History and Mission Overview</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>The Tau</attribution>
			<para>"The one constant in the universe is change. The wise adapt"</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>The late 24th century was a time of change for the Federation. War with the Cardassian Union, internal strife within the Klingon Empire, and the war with the Dominion resulted in the Federation taking an active role in galactic politics. This had resulted in a knock-on effect for Star Fleet, who were forced to cater for an increasingly hostile galaxy. Many within Star Fleet felt that the increased emphasis on combat, although necessary, was detracting from Star Fleet's traditional roles of exploration and research.</para>
		<para>In the aftermath of the Dominion War, a meeting was held at Avalon Ship Yards, in an attempt to predict the future requirements of Star Fleet. Given that, in the past two years, the war had demanded combat ships, it was decided that Star Fleet would need new ships that weren't combat-orientated.</para>
		<para>A new Dreadnought, listed as NX/D10, was being developed and constructed at Avalon at the time of this meeting. This ship was given to Avalon's top designers and developers, with the simple brief: transform NX/D10 into a Science Vessel. With many of the major systems in place, and much of the testing completed, the task took far less time than usual.</para>
		<para>The majority of the weaponry was removed and replaced, creating a ship with heavily reduced combat ability, but extensive scientific capabilities. Any systems that could be retained without affecting the ship's ability to fulfil its new role were kept.</para>
		<para>Testament to the skills of the team at Avalon, the new ship was finished in 2377, only 1 year after the intended deadline for the original Dreadnought. The ship, classified as a Light Researcher, was deemed space-worthy and commissioned as the USS Chimera NCC-97131.</para>
		<para>Chimera-class vessels are intended to help expand the frontiers of knowledge by scientific investigation. It is designed to investigate phenomena that other ships are ill suited to study, and with its abundance of scientific equipment and facilities can serve as a mobile research station.</para>
		<para>Intended missions are as follows:</para>
		<simplelist>
			<member>Expansion of the frontiers of science</member>
			<member>Investigation of anomalies</member>
			<member>Research center</member>
			<member>Planetary Survey</member>
			<member>Short Range Exploration</member>
			<member>Medical relief to non-combat situations</member>
		</simplelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Structure and Construction</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Optimus Primal</attribution>
			<para>"Die-cast construction.  It's a lost art."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>Like most modern Federation starships, the Chimera is split into two sections, the Saucer and the Engineering Hull.  As has become common practice with recent designs, the two sections are connected directly.  From above, the Saucer is a broad kite shape, with heavily rounded points.  The Bridge sits on top of the expanded deck 02, which extends along the dorsal surface of the Engineering hull, forming a backbone ridge.  The Saucer's dorsal surface is domed, while the ventral surface is almost flat, with the noticeable exception of the Captain's Yacht's Hanger doors.</para>
		<para>The Engineering hull has a thin, elliptical shape, and emerges from the aft and ventral Saucer surfaces.  Part of the dorsal aft section is removed to make space for the shuttle bay doors, and part of the ventral bow section is absent to accommodate the deflector array.  Unusually, there is no concave surface in the ventral aft section.</para>
		<para>The Warp Nacelles are attached by pylons to the port/starboard dorsal surfaces of the Engineering hull.  However, unlike the majority of starship designs, the pylons are curved downward, so that the nacelles are level with the ship's keel in a manner not dissimilar from the Nebula-class.  The nacelles are cuboids, wider than they are tall, and extend past the aft edge of the Engineering hull. </para>
		<para>As part of Star Fleet's rebuilding program, intended to replace the ships lost in the war, the Chimera-class is constructed using <link linkend="tech/transporterwelding">Transporter Welding</link> to cut construction time. It is built from tritanium and duranium, as is the case with most Federation starships. The Chimera-class does not support mission modules.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Scattershot</attribution>
			<para>"I make out about a hundred blips heading right towards us."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<section>
			<title>Sensor Systems</title>
			<para>The sensor systems of the Chimera-class, as would be expected, are given higher priority than on non-scientific vessels. Power from the warp core, no longer needed for weaponry, and advances in technology during the war, gives the Chimera-class noticeably high sensor ranges. High Resolution sensors have a range of 5 light-years, while Low Resolution sensors have a range of 18 light-years. The longer-than-standard ranges allow for more efficient mapping and scans, as well as providing greater warning on incoming threats, which in turn provides more time to escape.</para>
			<para>The sensor system comes with an automated adjustment feature. A non-standard scan can be selected from a menu, and sensors will automatically be adjusted perform that scan. Coupled with the ship's supply of probes, this allows the ship to perform all standard biological, astrophysical and planetological sweeps, and leaves the ship well equipped to study previously unknown phenomena.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Computer Systems</title>
			<para>The ship has three isolinear chip-based computer cores, used primarily for data storage.  Two of these are Avalon "Librarium" model cores, measuring 16m tall.  These are intended to serve as the primary computer system, and so contain the majority of the processing power.  The third is a "Codicer" model core, 8m tall, which serves as a back up. The Chimera-class can operate on this core alone if needed, although as a precaution non-essential systems such as holodecks will be taken off-line.  These new computer cores were used because it was believed the original computer system lacked the processing power required for a Science vessel.</para>
			<para>Primary data processing is performed by localised data processing units, which make extensive use of bio-neural circuitry and gel-packs. These are found on the Bridge, Main Engineering, Holodecks, DH offices and Science Labs.  This de-centralized processing system, present in everything from Science Lab computer terminals to the Holodecks, is what allows the Chimera-class to operate on one core.</para>
			<para>Sickbay has its own dedicated computer core. This is intended to store information on medical disorders and procedures, as well as provide computer power for Sickbay should all three main cores fail. This core lacks the capacity to handle the workload of the Main Computer Cores, and so cannot be used to operate the ship.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Scientific Probes</title>
			<para>50 scientific probes, and a further 50 empty torpedo casings, are carried on Chimera-class vessels. The intention is that empty casings can be assembled as either probes or torpedoes when needed, so they are kept unassembled.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Holographic Support Systems</title>
			<para>The ship has one EMH system, which is the EMH mk4. Emitters are located in important sections of the ship, giving the EMH access to the Bridge, Main Engineering, Science Labs, shuttle bays, cargo bays (for use as triage centres), holodecks, holosuites and, of course, Sickbay.  Outside of these areas the EMH cannot function.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Warp Propulsion Systems</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Jazz</attribution>
			<para>"Where'd that thing come from?"</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>Developed at Avalon Ship Yards, the Chimera-class incorporates an Avalon Tempest warp core, rated at 1500 Cochranes, as standard. Cruising speed is set at Warp 5.0, with a maximum sustainable velocity of Warp 7.0. The Maximum Warp Speed of the Chimera-class is Warp 9.6 for 12 hours. Enough matter and antimatter is stored to allow for missions of up to nine years in duration.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Cliffjumper</attribution>
			<para>"I'm more concerned with where it's going."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>The Chimera-class has three impulse drive units. Two of these are on the saucer; the third is located in the aft engineering hull. These propel the ship at 0.24c. Although the Chimera-class is neither especially fast nor manoeuvrable the ship's movement was frequently compared to the grace of the Manta Ray native to Earth.  Acceleration is a rate of 50 seconds from Full Stop to Full Impulse, and 90 seconds when slowing from Full Impulse to Full Stop.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Tactical Systems</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Malcolm Reed</attribution>
			<para>"They're called 'phase pistols'.  They have two settings, stun and kill.  It would be best not to confuse them."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>The Chimera-class, as a science vessel, is not expected to engage in combat, and has less than half the weaponry of its original design. Its primary defence when attacked is to run away, as it lacks the armament for sustained combat.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Defensive Shields</title>
			<para>With reduced power requirements due to the reduction of the weaponry, defensive shields were given much higher priority. The shields have a Maximum Gravitational Load of 2006 Mw and a Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate of 5.4x10^5 kW.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Metaphasic Shields</title>
			<para>The Chimera-class is also equipped with a metaphasic shield generator. This creates a low-level subspace field, which protects the ship from radiation emissions and the like, a hazard when investigating stellar phenomena. The metaphasic shield offers no additional protection in combat.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Phaser Systems</title>
			<para>Intended for defensive use only, there are 6 phaser strips. Three are mounted on the Saucer hull (two dorsal surface, one ventral surface). Each of these has 100 type-VIII emitters. Two strips, each consisting of 60 type-VIII emitters, are found on the ventral surface of the warp nacelles (one strip per nacelle).  The final strip, consisting of 60 emitters is found on the dorsal engineering hull surface.  Each emitter has a maximum output of 2.6 Mw, with a range of 140,000km.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Torpedo Systems</title>
			<para>Like the phasers, the Torpedo launchers of the Chimera-class were also dramatically cut down. There are 2 torpedo tubes, which are primarily intended for the launch of scientific probes. One is located in the forward Engineering hull, the other in the aft Engineering hull. The Chimera-class carries 50 photon torpedoes, plus the 50 scientific probes and 50 casings described above. Each torpedo tube can load and fire 4 torpedoes before reloading. Torpedoes and probes are stored adjacent to the launchers in order to reduce the effort needed to load them.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Self-Destruct Systems</title>
			<para>The self-destruct system of the Chimera-class consists of the release of safety interlocks on antimatter storage units, the collapse of the containment field around the warp core and the detonation of any remaining torpedoes on board the ship. This can only be activated by the command codes of two Senior Officers serving on that ship.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Command and Support Systems</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>William The Bloody</attribution>
			<para>"This is...neat!"</para>
		</epigraph>
		<section>
			<title>Bridge</title>
			<para>The Bridge is found on Deck 1, along with the Captain's Ready Room and staff briefing room. The viewscreen is at the front of the Bridge, with two consoles just behind it. These are the Ops and Conn consoles, and resemble the curved-edge design of the Conn/Ops console of the Defiant-class. The Viewscreen is raised so that these do not appear on the other screen during a conversation.</para>
			<para>The Captain sits in a chair slightly off-centre of the Bridge, to port. The chair is large, black and extremely comfortable, and has a small display attachment that can be swapped between the two arms. The XO's chair, which is towards starboard, is equally black and comfortable, but is slightly smaller than the CO's Chair.</para>
			<para>Tactical command is on the wall to starboard, and incorporates Security and Communications control. This is a seated station. To port is the Engineering console, with chair and enough displays to monitor all major systems as well as co-ordinate engineering effort across the ship. Both of these stations are forward facing and enclosed, making for a safer bridge.</para>
			<para>Finally, there are three Science stations.  These have enough displays for virtually any type of scan imaginable, and each station accommodates one science officer at a time, sitting.  These are found on the wall of the Bridge behind the Captain. All chairs are swivel chairs. The walls are a dark grey colour, and the lighting has a slight hint of purple that creates a slightly gothic feel.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Ready Room</title>
			<para>To the rear of Deck 01 is the Captain's Ready Room.  The Captain's Ready Room features a large desk with a large, looming swivel chair for the Captain to sit in, incorporating a computer access terminal.  It also features a small "lounge" area, for when the Captain feels it necessary to relax while on duty.  This area includes a replicator for the Captain's use only.  Access to this room is via the Bridge, with a door adjacent to the Science console.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Briefing Room</title>
			<para>To the front of Deck 1 is a briefing room.  The Briefing room is pretty standard, looking much like every other briefing room an officer has been in. A large, rectangular table occupies the majority of the room, with a display screen built into one of the narrow walls so that everyone in the room can see it. A single door provides access. Chairs for the CO, XO, Department Heads and up to four others are found alongside the table, each with its own mini-display screen, so those attending the briefing can view the presentation at their own speed.  Access is via the Bridge, with a door to the Captain's left (adjacent to the viewscreen).</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Engineering</title>
			<para>Main Engineering is found on decks 18 and 19.  The Matter/Anti-matter Reaction Array is mounted vertically, as this is believed to be the most efficient method. The Matter/Anti-matter Reaction Chamber is found on these decks. The majority of the wall space on both levels is covered in consoles and readouts, allowing Engineers to adjust all systems on ship.</para>
			<para>Access between the two levels is via either ladder or turbolift.  There are two small turbolifts incorporated into alcoves in Main Engineering's walls.</para>
			<para>The Chief Engineer's Office is found on Deck 18, accessed through Main Engineering.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Security</title>
			<para>There is a single brig, found on deck 12. This has 10 cells. Access to the cells is via a single entry point. Security measures include restricted access, transport inhibitors, security fields and doors that can be physically sealed, after it was noted that prisoners tend to escape when power for the force fields is cut. Individual cell doors can be sealed, if needed.</para>
			<para>A small armoury is found on deck 07. This has side arms for the entire crew, plus type III-b phaser rifles for the Security officers. Under normal circumstances access to the armoury is restricted to CO, XO and COS, although access is granted to Department Heads during Yellow or Red Alert situations.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Sciences</title>
			<para>As would be expected on a science vessel, the Chimera-class has extensive science facilities. There are a total of 19 laboratories on the ship, varying in size and function, split into five groups.</para>
			<para>The first group consists of general use labs.  Labs 1 and 2 are general-purpose laboratories, extensive equipped but lacking in specialisation.  Labs 3, 4 and 5 are biology, chemistry and physics labs respectively.</para>
			<para>The second group specialises in the study of space.  Lab 6 is the Astrophysics lab, intended for the study of spatial and stellar phenomena.  Lab 7 is Stellar Cartography, and so is equipped for the mapping of space.  Both of these can function during the normal operation of the starship without interfering with other studies.</para>
			<para>The third group, consisting of four labs, is dedicated to specific fields of research and investigation, which tend to require a specific subject to study: that is, they are used for studying "on-site" Lab 8 is a Geology lab, 9 deals in Ecology, 10 handles Archaeology while 11 is equipped for meteorological studies.  When not being actively used on a mission, they can be used as research labs independent of the ships mission.</para>
			<para>The next group of labs fulfil help fulfil the role of research and development.  However, they are also equipped to study any examples found in space (for example, lab 16 can be used to study newly discovered plants).</para>
			<para>Lab 12 is a Cybernetics lab, helping to study and develop robotics and prosthetics.  Lab 13 is a Computer Studies lab.  This helps in the development of new computer systems, including both components and programmes.  Lab 14 is a Propulsion Systems development lab, looking into improved and alternative means of getting from A to B.  Lab 15 is a Materials Research lab, looking at new, more useful and efficient materials for use at large.  Lab 16 is a Botany lab, dedicated to the study of plant life.</para>
			<para>The final grouping of labs is the Medical Research Laboratories, or Med-Labs.  These are joint ventures between the Science and Medical departments.  There are 3 labs in this group.  Med-Lab 1 is a general-purpose medical research laboratory, Med-Lab 2 is a genetics lab and Med-Lab 3 is an exobiology laboratory.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Offices</title>
			<para>Each Department Head has an office reserved for their use. These are usually found adjacent to the main facility for that Department (for example, the Chief Engineer's Office is adjacent to Main Engineering). The exceptions to this are Command (Decks 01 and 02), the CSO (Deck 06) and the CNS (Deck 11). Offices consist of a desk, computer access terminal, chair (for the office's owner) and standing room for about 5 people, except for the CNS's office, which has two chairs and a spookily comfortable couch, for the needs of those requiring counselling.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Utility Systems</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Agent K</attribution>
			<para>"We're not even supposed to have this."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<section>
			<title>Cargo Bays</title>
			<para>Cargo bays are found on Decks 11 (Engineering hull), 13 (port and starboard, adjacent airlocks), 23 (port and starboard, adjacent airlocks), 25 and 26. Cargo bays on Decks 11, 25 and 26 have Cargo transporters due to impracticality of transporting Cargo across the ship.  In extreme medical emergencies, the Cargo bays can be used as triage centers.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Tractor Beam Systems</title>
			<para>Tractor beam emitters are found in the Engineering hull of the Chimera-class. The tractor beam as a maximum range of 18,000km although, as with all tractor beams, this is dependent on the mass and velocity of the object.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Transporter Systems</title>
			<para>There are 8 transporter rooms, coupled into 4 pairs, are located throughout the ship. Each has 8 pads and a range of 40,000 km. Another 8 emergency transporters, each also with 8 pads, are also found on the Chimera-class.  This provides a total of 16 transporters during an evacuation.  Emergency transporters have a range of 15,000 km.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Crew Support Systems</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Morpheus</attribution>
			<para>"This is the Construct."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<section>
			<title>Medical Facilities</title>
			<para>Sickbay is found on deck 8. This has 4 wards plus a medical storage bay and a specialised computer, which is used to store medical records, information on medical procedures and medical textbooks. The Chief Medical Officer's office is accessed through Sickbay.</para>
			<para>The medical computer core is notably smaller than the main Computer cores, and lacks the power to handle the workload of the primary computer system.</para>
			<para>Ward 1 is intended to deal with accidents and emergencies, and so is equipped to deal with both minor and major injuries. There are 8 beds. Ward 1 does not have a dedicated surgical area - any patients requiring major surgery will be taken to another ward. In the course of a day, it is Ward 1 that will see the most activity.</para>
			<para>Ward 2 is the Surgical Ward, where patients are prepared for and receive surgery. There are 8 beds, plus two surgical areas.</para>
			<para>Ward 3 is intended for post-op recovery and recuperation, and has 8 beds.</para>
			<para>Ward 4 is set-up to accommodate races that require environments other than M-class. Each of the 6 beds possesses an isolated environment. H, K, and L-class environments can be created in this ward if and when needed.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Replicators</title>
			<para>Replicators are found in all crew quarters, although these are low-volume replicators. High volume replicators can be found in the bar/lounge suite.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Recreational Facilities</title>
			<para>Deck 10 contains most of the ship's Recreational facilities. There is a large combination Bar/Lounge/Restaurant, which can also be used to host diplomatic meetings on account of the absence of dedicated diplomatic facilities.  Two Holodecks can be accessed from the deck, although these also incorporate parts of Deck 9. There are four holosuites on Deck 9, and another two on Deck 10.</para>
			<para>A small Galley is attached to the Bar, intended for use during diplomatic functions.  In rare circumstances it is used for crewmembers with special dietary requirements that cannot be met by the replicator system.  The majority of the crew use replicators for their meals.</para>
			<para>A Gym is found on Deck 09, occupying the space above the bar/lounge suite. This includes various exercise equipment as well as "open" areas for activities such as aerobics or martial arts.</para>
			<para>There is an Auditorium on Deck 14.  This can serve as a performance hall for theatrical and musical performances, as well as a Lecture and Seminar room.  In the latter of these options, it is intended for the presentation of research to the scientific community.</para>
			<para>A Botanical Garden is present on Deck 15.  As well as providing a pleasant alternative to the holodecks, it can be used to house samples of plants being studied.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Quarters</title>
			<para>Accommodation is divided into three categories: Officer, Crew and Guest. Crew quarters are the most basic, split into a lounge area (with replicator), living area (including bed, bath and sonic shower) and storage area (walls covered in storage units).</para>
			<para>Officer's quarters are larger than Crew Quarters, as they include a "Study" area required by the increased workload levelled upon Officers.</para>
			<para>Guest Quarters are as large as Officer Quarters, but have more room to relax due to the absence of the Study area.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Environmental systems</title>
			<para>Due to the use of a de-centralised environmental system, all crew quarters and cargo bays can be adjusted into class M, H, K or L environments. Should this system fail Main Life Support takes over. However, this is only a back-up system, and so is limited to M class environments.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Auxiliary Spacecraft Systems</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Ultra Magnus</attribution>
			<para>"To the shuttles!"</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>There are two shuttle bays on the Chimera-class. As standard, Shuttle Bay One contains 5 Armadillo-class Shuttlecraft. Shuttle Bay Two contains 3 Armadillo-class shuttlecraft. CO's may request to exchange the 5 shuttlecraft of Shuttle Bay One for 2 Runabouts.  In both cases, a partitioned area of the Shuttle Bay functions as maintenance and repair bays for the shuttles.</para>
		<para>The Captain's Yacht is found in a hanger on decks 14 and 15, which opens in the bottom of the saucer enabling the Yacht to drop out of the saucer.</para>
		<para>Someone was on a retro trip when designing the yacht, as it bears a strong resemblance to the pioneering NX-01 starship.  The front of the craft is a saucer, with the deflector array built into the front of the yacht.  Unlike the NX-01, an engineering hull, of a kind, emerges from the aft saucer, with the nacelles connected via pylon to the sides of this section.  Like the NX-01, the nacelles are above the main hull.  The yacht has a single deck.</para>
		<para>Three landing gears are built into the saucer (bow, port, starboard), with two more in the ventral aft surface of the engineering hull.  This allows for surface landings, assuming the surface is solid.</para>
		<para>The yacht is 26.56m long, 15.91m wide and 4.19m tall.  The yacht's sensors have a high-resolution range of 0.4 light-years, with a low-resolution range of 1.0 light-year.  It is warp capable, with a cruising speed of Warp 2, a maximum sustainable speed of Warp 3 and a maximum speed of Warp 4 for 12 hours. The sub-light speed is 0.26c.</para>
		<para>Four Type-IV phaser emitters are included for defensive purposes, with a range of 75,000km and a maximum output of 1 Mw.  Shields are rated as having a maximum gravitational load of 41Mw and an Energy Dissipation Rate of 1.9^4kW. </para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Technical Specifications</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Morpheus</attribution>
			<para>"How do you define 'real'?"</para>
		</epigraph>
		<section>
		<variablelist>
			<title>Dimensions and Structure</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Length</term>
				<listitem><para>619.04 meters (643.56 meters with nacelles</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Beam (Width)</term>
				<listitem><para>373.73 meters</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Height</term>
				<listitem><para>118.24 meters</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Decks</term>
				<listitem><para>27</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>						
		</variablelist>		
		<variablelist>
			<title>Crew Complement</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Officers and Crew</term>
				<listitem><para>750</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Command</term>
				<listitem><para>5%</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Engineering</term>
				<listitem><para>25%</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Medical</term>
				<listitem><para>20%</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Science</term>
				<listitem><para>40%</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Security</term>
				<listitem><para>10%</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Visiting Personnel</term>
				<listitem><para>200</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Maximum Evacuation Limit</term>
				<listitem><para>1,800</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>												
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<title>Computer Systems</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Core</term>
				<listitem><para>Isolinear data core x3</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Operating System</term>
				<listitem><para>Starfleet Library Computer Access and Retrieval System (LCARS)</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>User Interface</term>
				<listitem><para>MAJEL</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>			
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<title>Warp Systems</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Power Plant</term>
				<listitem><para>One 1500+ cochrane M/ARA cores feeding two nacelles</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Cruising Velocity</term>
				<listitem><para>Warp 5</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Maximum Sustainable Velocity</term>
				<listitem><para>Warp 7</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Maximum Velocity</term>
				<listitem><para>Warp 9.6 (12 hours)</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>						
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<title>Impulse Systems</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Full Impulse</term>
				<listitem><para>0.24c</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Accellerate</term>
				<listitem><para>50 seconds</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Decellerate</term>
				<listitem><para>90 seconds</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>			
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<title>Defensive Systems</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)</term>
				<listitem><para>2006 MegaWatts</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate</term>
				<listitem><para>5.4x10^5 kilowatts</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<title>Offensive Systems</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Torpedoes</term>
				<listitem>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Torpedo Tubes</term>
							<listitem><para>2</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Standard Payload (total)</term>
							<listitem><para>50 photo torpedoes, 50 probes</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Phasers</term>
				<listitem><para>5 Type-VIII Phaser Strips</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Deck Layout</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Swoop</attribution>
			<para>"Me Swoop no find nothing."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 1</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Bridge</member>
				<member>Captain's Ready Room</member>
				<member>Staff Briefing Room</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 2</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>XO's Office</member>
				<member>Science Labs 1-2</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 3</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Science Labs 3-5</member>
				<member>Computer Core 01 level A</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 4</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Science Labs 6-7</member>
				<member>Computer Core 01 level B</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 5</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Science Labs 8-11</member>
				<member>Shuttle Bay 1 Open Space</member>
				<member>Computer Core 1 level C</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 6</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Science Labs 12-14</member>
				<member>CSO's Office</member>
				<member>Shuttle Bay 01 Observation Deck</member>
				<member>Computer Core 01 level D</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 7</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Science Labs 15-16</member>
				<member>Shuttle Bay 01 Landing Deck</member>
				<member>Armoury</member>
				<member>Structural Integrity Field Generators</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 8</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>CMO's Office</member>
				<member>Main Sickbay</member>
				<member>Medical Computer Core</member>
				<member>Med-Labs 1-3</member>
				<member>Medical Supplies Storage Bay</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 9</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Officer's Quarters</member>
				<member>Guest Quarters</member>
				<member>Holodecks 1-4 upper level</member>
				<member>Holosuites 1-2</member>
				<member>Gym</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 10</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Bar/Lounge</member>
				<member>Galley</member>
				<member>Holodecks 1-4 lower level and access</member>
				<member>Holosuites 3-4</member>
				<member>Mess Hall</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Computer Core 2 Level A</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 11</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>CNS's Office</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Cargo Bays</member>
				<member>Computer Core 2 Level B</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 12</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>COS's Office</member>
				<member>Brig</member>
				<member>Shuttle Bay 2 Observation Deck</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Computer Core 2 Level C</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 13</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Shuttle Bay 2 Landing Deck</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Deuterium Storage Tanks</member>
				<member>Cargo Bays</member>
				<member>Computer Core 2 Level D</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 14</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Auditorium</member>
				<member>Captain's Yacht Hanger Upper Level</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 15</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Botanical Garden</member>
				<member>Captain's Yacht Hanger Lower Level</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 16</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Inertial Dampening Field Generators</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 17</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Structural Integrity Field Generators</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 18</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>CE's Office</member>
				<member>Main Engineering Upper Level</member>
				<member>Matter Injector Array</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 19</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Main Engineering Lower Level</member>
				<member>Antimatter Injector Array</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 20</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Computer Core 3 level A</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 21</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Computer Core 3 level B</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 22</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Replicator Raw Matter storage</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 23</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Cargo Bays</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 24</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Deflector Control</member>
				<member>Hydroponics Bay</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 25</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Antimatter Storage Tanks</member>
				<member>Cargo Bays</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 26</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Cargo Bays</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 27</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Warp Core Ejection System</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Ships of the Class</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Morpheus</attribution>
			<para>"Do you know who this is?"</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>The prototype, when commissioned, was named the USS Chimera, after the mythological creature. Other ships of the Chimera-class are named after creatures of myth and legend.</para>
		<simplelist role="ShipList">
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Chimera</productname>
				<productnumber>97131</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Unicorn</productname>
				<productnumber>97132</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Ogopogo</productname>
				<productnumber>97133</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Mawgawr</productname>
				<productnumber>97134</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Faerie</productname>
				<productnumber>97135</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Griffin</productname>
				<productnumber>97136</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Sphinx</productname>
				<productnumber>97137</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>White Buffalo</productname>
				<productnumber>97138</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Thunderbird</productname>
				<productnumber>97139</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Mokele-Mbembe</productname>
				<productnumber>97140</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Yeti</productname>
				<productnumber>97141</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Leprechaun</productname>
				<productnumber>97142</productnumber>
			</member>
		</simplelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Conclusion</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Pinhead</attribution>
			<para>"What did you see?  The same as I?  Appetite sated, desire indulged."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>The Chimera-class light Researcher is designed to help in the progress of science, and to bring the benefits of increased knowledge to the Federation and has extensive scientific facilities to accomplish this goal. It is ill suited to combat situations due to its light armament. The Chimera-class, like most Star Fleet vessels, has a long operational lifetime, and it is expected that the design will continue to serve for some time.</para>
	</section>
</article>