<article class="specification" id="darwin">
  <title>Darwin-class</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup role="Maintainer">
      <author>
        <firstname>EDept</firstname>
        <surname>Staff</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Primary Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Mike</firstname>
        <surname>Bourdaa</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Original Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Mike</firstname>
        <surname>Bourdaa</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword role="service">PC</keyword>
      <keyword role="category">Frigate</keyword>
      <keyword role="variant">Medium</keyword>
      <keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>2</revnumber>
        <date>6 July 2001</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Engineering Director Bret Godfrey</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>APPROVALDATE</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Engineering NAME</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>History and Mission Overview</title>
    <para>On Stardate 96010.1, Starfleet Command authorized what may be the first "mass-produced" capital ship design.  Based on a need to develop a new generation of light, fast vessels for exploration and patrol purposes, a design team was enlisted to create a design to balance the need for rapid deployment with the necessity of a quality vessel.</para>
    <para>The critical breakthrough was the modular units, which could be easily constructed, or even replicated as needed.  The only portions of the vessel which are not fully modular are the engine core, and the spaceframe.</para>
    <para>The first prototype of this design, the USS Darwin, was constructed at the Larimda Me Prototype Yards, of the Starbase 117 complex, in the Beta Priori Starsystem.  It was be immediately placed into active service for testing, while the construction of the next four vessels awaited.  After construction began on this first "batch", the semi-completed vessels were pressed into service as part of a task force to apprehend the thief of a transwarp-capable runabout, USS Pursuit.  After the conclusion of this action, the remaining 37 vessels in the contract were produced over the course of two and a half years.   While its battle skills are fairly questionable, it still is more than a match for most problems that would be encountered, and its mere existance will allow the more powerful designs to be freed from the more mundane exploration and survey missions.</para>
    <para>Beginning on Stardate 01020.5, the Mark II upgrade project was initiated.  This upgrade included a readjustment to the phaser arrays to compensate for observed phaser "shadows," a removal of the demonstratedly useless pulse-phaser mount above the nacelles, an increase in effective vessel range of 4%, and a significant upgrade of the Holographic and Computer systems.  These upgrades are expected to be rapidly completed, and make the Darwin a more well-rounded vessel for general mission.</para>
    <para>Standard Mission Profiles for the Darwin include:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>General Exploration Craft</term>
        <listitem><para>The Darwin makes an ideal scout, because of its high speed, powerful general purpose scanners, and small size.  While more in-depth research ought to be carried out by an Andromeda, Columbus, or Athens, the Darwin, with its sheer numbers, and relative expendability, will often be the first UFP vessel assigned to any research or exploration area.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>First Response Vessel</term>
        <listitem><para>The Darwin's speed and distibution make it likely to be one of the first ships to respond to disasters within and outside of the UFP.  For this reason, the design includes slightly more medical and engineering personnel than would normally be assigned to a ship of this size, and several holographic systems as well that allow the ship to 'donate' more of its personnel to external duties than otherwise possible.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Military Scout</term>
        <listitem><para>In times of warfare, the Darwin makes up for its relative lack of armament with its speed.  It makes an fairly good reconnaissance vessel, able to handle quick flybys, and report on enemy status and strength with a high degree of accuracy.  It can also be used as a troop transport, and a field hospital ship, because of its high speed.  There are, of course, other ships that can handle certain aspects better than a Darwin, however.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Urgent Cargo Carrier</term>
        <listitem><para>In ancient times, the most urgent of cargo was sent by the fastest available transport, whether that was by runner, horse, sailboat, or jet.  Field Commanders have long known that the most important part of warfare is maintaining secure supply lines.  While the Darwin is not very effective in slaying ones enemies, and makes a fairly poor convoy escort, it would be very effective when used as a cargoship on its own.  The old adage 'you can't kill what you can't catch' applies strongly in this context.  When it absolutely, positively, has to be there yesterday (and it's not too large), the Darwin will probably quickly become the ship of choice, at least until Transwarp-capable vessels of sufficient size are able to be constructed.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Scientific Research</term>
        <listitem><para>Although the Mark II upgrade of the Darwin was completed with a slight decrease to the overall scientific mission, to make a more well-rounded vessel, the Darwin remains a highly capable vessel for the general mission of Starfleet, exploration and discovery.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Structure and Construction</title>
    <para>Externally, owing to the requirements of the modular design, the vessel is anything but sleek.  The primary hull resembles more closely a trapezoid than a saucer, with the front section arcing only very gradually, then a sharp angular slice running down the port and starboard sides, until the aft 'arc' is intersected again.  The secondary hull, containing the deflector dish, warp core, and other vital systems, is mounted above, rather then below (using the orientation for planetary landing), and is offset 50 meters behind the stern of the primary hull, and extends 75 meters beyond the aft terminus of the primary hull.</para>
    <para>The warp nacelles are a swing-wing configuration, mounted "below" the primary hull.  In normal cruise configuration, the angle of the nacelles ranges from 61 to 72 degrees.  At impulse configuration, in order to minimize gravitational strain, the nacelles are set to ninety degrees, and retracted five meters into the hull.  For landing configuration, the nacelles are extended an extra three meters, and are set to an angle of negative five degrees, fitting inside slots at the bottom of the primary hull, in order to prevent damage to the nacelles on landing.</para>
    <para>The Darwin is, internally, a collection of approximately 300 separate units, all of which are easily constructed and replaced.  Some of these modules, like the Bridge Module, are used only once per ship.  Others, like the Officer/VIP Quarters, Interior and Exterior Crew Quarters, and the holodecks, are used many times over, and can be placed together in an assembly-line fashion, allowing these ships to be produced at an amazing 21% improvement over the Intrepid design, at each construction yard.  Additionally, because of the small size, two ships can be simultaneously built inside one large vessel mooring.  Because of this design, the internal layout of the Darwin Class can be somewhat customized at construction time as well.  Conversion of the Darwin class vessels to purely Medical, Research, or Cargo vessels, once the weaponry and warp drive are obsolete, should require only minor changes.  The expected useful lifetime of this incarnation of the Darwin Class is estimated a!
t 30 years, with an additional 40 years afterwards performing as more of a support (Medical, Research, etc.) ship.  Refits are projected to be at relatively low cost, compared to previous, non-modular designs, which could signifigantly extend the useful lifetime of the Darwin class.</para>
    <para>The Darwin Class vessel has one front-mounted Trafalgar-style mission module docking port, which can be exchanged at any Federation Starbase or Outpost equipped with spare modules.  The complete list of available modules is identical to that of Trafalgar.  Alternatively, the area can also be used to store a single Valhalla or Denver Class Runabout.  The other option for this space is it's official, default status, as a cargobay.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
    <para>.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Sensor Systems</title>
      <para>The sensor system on the Darwin is optimized for research purposes, but does have capacity for tactical operation as well.  High resolution range is 4.5 light years, with a low resolution range of up to 15 light years under optimum conditions.
The Darwin carries a load of twenty-five standard probes, which are launched via the torpedo tubes.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Computer Systems</title>
      <para>While early Darwin vessels were a hybrid of mostly isolinear and relatively sparse bioneural systems for their primary computer interface, bioneural circuitry has become more abundant recently, and the newer Darwin class vessels being constructed are 27% bioneural on their main and primary backup systems.  All critical systems have a secondary backup on an older, isolinear design, in case of catastrophic failure.  A storage locker in Main Engineering contains 55 spare bioneural gelpacks, for replacement and rotation.</para>
      <para>The main computer core, Mark X, is located in the center of the primary hull, and has a storage capacity of 2.1 teraquads.  The secondary core, a standard ODN 17Q system, is located in the primary hull, aft, and has a storage capacity of 700 gigaquads.</para>
      <para>The Darwin Class vessel uses the standard LCARS OS and Interface by default.  The original USS Darwin prototype, however, used a customized derivitive called the Darwin Operating System, or DarOS.  Despite the improved computer efficiency over the LCARS system, officers and crew found it difficult (if not impossible) to utilize the Darwin OS due to its highly user-unfriendly interface.  An overlay program was attempted to make the Darwin OS easier to use, but the overlay constantly crashed the computer core, and despite efforts to remedy this, the situation got worse and worse over time, despite numerous attempts to upgrade the overlay to correct this instability.  Fortunately, DarOS was never installed on any of the other vessels, and these problems have not been duplicated elsewhere as a result.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Holographic Crew</title>
      <para>The Darwin is equipped with Emergency Medical Hologram (EMH Mark IV).  Holographic officers are restricted to operation where holoemitters are present;  specifically sickbay, the holodecks, the bridge, and the brig.  Additionally, because two instances can be run simultaneously (one from the primary computer core, and one from the secondary core), but because of the limits of holoemitters, only one can be run in any given location at the same time.   Finally, use of any of the program continuously for more than five hours is strongly discouraged, due to the tendency for program corruption after extended operation.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Warp Propulsion Systems</title>
    <para>The Darwin contains two nacelles, located below the primary hull, in a swing-wing configuration with three preset angle settings; -5 degrees (planetary landing configuration), the range between 61 and 72 degrees (warp flight configuration) and 90 degrees (normal impulse flight operation.)  Zero degrees is defined as the nacelles being perfectly parallel with the saucer section's vertical plane of symmetry.  The Warp Core is located in the Secondary Hull.</para>
    <para>The Darwin has a standard cruising velocity of Warp 6, the velocity at which maximum fuel efficiency is attained.  It is capable of sustaining a velocity of Warp 9.3, and has a twelve hour emergency speed of Warp 9.903.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
    <para>The Impulse drive is located at the aft portion of the secondary hull.  It can propel the vessel to a maximum safe impulse velocity of 0.287c.  (This limit is largely due to relativistic concerns rather than technological issues.)  The impuse engines achieve maximum fuel efficiency at a cruising velocity of 0.23c and 0.0007c.  As such, 0.23c is designated "Standard Impulse," and 0.287c "Full Impulse."</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Tactical Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Defensive Shields</title>
      <para>The shields of the Darwin Class are of the standard deflector shielding variety, with a maximum graviton load of 1077 MW and a maximum dissipation rate of 3.2 x 10^4 kW.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Phaser Systems</title>
      <para>Five Type-IX phaser arrays are located on the vessel - two arcs located on the front side of the primary hull (top and bottom), one arc at the rear to cover escape, and two arcs located on opposite sides of the secondary hull to cover side approaches.  There is a "359" degree coverage with this arrangement;  two small phaser "blind spots" occur in the shadows of the warp nacelle.</para>
      <para>The strips contain the following emitter breakdown:  Top primary and bottom primary arc contain 80 emitters each.  Rear arc contains 50 emitters.  The secondary hull arcs contain 70 emitters each.  The total emitter count is 350.</para>
      <para>The maximum effective range of the Phaser systems is 250,000 km.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Torpedo Systems</title>
      <para>The torpedo launchers are located at the front and rear of the secondary hull, able again to cover "359" degrees of coverage using standard fire-and-forget targetting.  The launchers are physically seperate, but share a common torpedo storage area, where 85 torpedoes are stored (standard payload is 75 photon torpedoes, ten quantum torpedoes.)  The maximum burst-fire rate is four torpedoes per tube.  The torpedo blindspots are located at the underside of the primary hull, and directly above the primary hull at an approach perpendicular to the central axis.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Command and Support Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Bridge</title>
      <para>The bridge of the Darwin-class vessel is one of the smaller designs.  Similar in some ways to the older Constitution-class design, there are two central seats located in the rear for the Captain and First Officer.  The Tactical officer, Helmsman and Operations officer (clockwise) are located at the front, facing front, and four work stations along the perimeter face away from the center.  Two of these are dedicated for Engineering, Mission Operations.  (the more forward on either side;  Engineering is to the Port side, Mission Ops Starboard.), and the other two are configurable for whatever other purpose is deemed necessary for the specific mission.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Main Science Complex</title>
      <para>Deck 9 houses the Main Science Complex, which includes laboratory space for the various disciplines.  The basic lab facilities include a computer interface, and a configurable setup based on a basic template.  Individual labs can be configured for any of the sciences, from medical to astrophysics, with only minor adjustments.  28 labs make up the complex, in four wings (two 8-lab wings, and two 6-lab wings).</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Utility Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Cargo Bays</title>
      <para>Cargobays are located as follows:  Two on Deck 4, 1 on Deck 5, 3 on Deck 11, and 2 on Deck 12.  All cargobays are equiped with standard cargo transporters. Cargobay #4 (located at Deck 11 Forward) is unique in that it is located on the exterior of the vessel, and can be converted to accomodate either a Valhalla-class or Denver-Class Runabout, or a Trafalgar-class mission module.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tractor Beam Systems</title>
      <para>The tractor beam emitter is located on Deck 12.  It has an effective range of 425,000 km.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Transporter Systems</title>
      <para>The main transporters have a range of 42,500 km, and are located as follows:  two rooms on Deck 4, two rooms on Deck 9.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Crew Support Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Sickbay</title>
      <para>Sickbay is located on Deck 9.  It is divided into two normal six-bed rooms, and two quarentine two-bed rooms, for a total patient capacity of 16 beds.  It is located in close proximity to the main science complex, and the medical labs are considered part of that complex.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Recreational Facilities</title>
      <para>Most of the recreational facilities are located on Deck 8:  These include - two holodecks, a gymnasium, the Eight Forward Rec lounge, and the Eight Aft obvervation lounge.  VIP quarters are also located on Deck 8, conveniently close to these activity areas.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Alternate Environmental Support</title>
      <para>Two of the VIP quarters, a small obvervation lounge, and the quarters adjoining these three rooms, all located on the starboard side of Deck 8, are capable of sustained reproduction of most of the various alternate atmosphere conditions.  These are designed mostly for the use of visiting scientists or diplomats, although they may also be used to accomodate others as deemed necessary.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Auxiliary Spacecraft Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Shuttlecraft</title>
      <para>The shuttlebay, located Deck 5 aft, is capable of holding up to the standard compliment of four Type-12 Personnel shuttles.  Cargobay 8 adjoins the shuttlebay, and can contain one additional shuttle, for repairs, refit or storage.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Runabouts</title>
      <para>A Valhalla-class or Denver-class Runabout may be accomodated in Cargobay 4 (Deck 11) if that area is not being used for other purposes.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Captain's Yacht</title>
      <para>The Captain's Yacht is Type Upsilon (crossreference Upsilon-Type Yacht), and is mounted inside a grooved notch on Deck 12, which corresponds to Deck 1 of the Yacht.  A split dome hatch houses the yacht internally, which moves away to allow the Yacht to dock or depart.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Technical Specifications</title>
      <variablelist>
        <title>Dimensions and Structure</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Length</term>
          <listitem><para>198.62 meters</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Beam (Width)</term>
          <listitem><para>102.27 meters</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Height</term>
          <listitem><para>52.06 meters</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Decks</term>
          <listitem><para>12</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <variablelist>
        <title>Crew Complement</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Officers and Crew</term>
          <listitem><para>120</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Command</term>
          <listitem><para>9</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Engineering</term>
          <listitem><para>28</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Medical</term>
          <listitem><para>16</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Science</term>
          <listitem><para>38</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Security</term>
          <listitem><para>29</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Visiting Personnel</term>
          <listitem><para>90</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Maximum Evacuation Limit</term>
          <listitem><para>850</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <variablelist>
        <title>Computer Systems</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Primary Core</term>
          <listitem><para>Isolinear-Bioneural Hybrid  x 1</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Secondary Core</term>
          <listitem><para>Isolinear ODN 17Q  x 1</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Operating System</term>
          <listitem><para>Starfleet Library Computer Access and Retreval System (LCARS)</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>User Interface</term>
          <listitem><para>MAJEL</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <variablelist>
        <title>Warp Systems</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Power Plant</term>
          <listitem><para>One 1500+ cochrane M/ARA core feeding two nacelles</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Crusing Velocity</term>
          <listitem><para>Warp 6</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Maximum Sustainable Velocity</term>
          <listitem><para>Warp 9.3</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Maximum Velocity</term>
          <listitem><para>Warp 9.903 (12 hours)</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <variablelist>
        <title>Impulse Systems</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Full Impulse</term>
          <listitem><para>0.287c</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Accellerate</term>
          <listitem><para>6.35 seconds</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Decellerate</term>
          <listitem><para>6.98 seconds</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <variablelist>
        <title>Defensive Systems</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)</term>
          <listitem><para>1077 MegaWatts</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate</term>
          <listitem><para>3.2x10^4 kilowatts</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <variablelist>
        <title>Offensive Systems</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Torpedoes</term>
          <listitem>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Torpedo Tubes</term>
                <listitem><para>2</para></listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Standard Payload (total)</term>
                <listitem><para>75 photon torpedoes, 10 quantum torpedoes</para></listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Phasers</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>5 Type-IX Phaser Strips</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>  
  <section>
    <title>Deck Layout</title>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 1</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Auxillary Control</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 2</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Main Sensor Array</member>
        <member>Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Brig</member>
        <member>Main Deflector</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 3</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxillary Engineering</member>
        <member>Impulse Drive</member>
        <member>Main Computer Core #1</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 4</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Communication Array</member>
        <member>Cargobays</member>
        <member>Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Transporter Rooms</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 5</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Cargobays</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 6</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Bridge</member>
        <member>Ready Room</member>
        <member>Conference Room</member>
        <member>Sensor mountings</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 7</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Command Officer Quarters</member>
        <member>Officer's Mess</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 8</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Recreation Facilities</member>
        <member>VIP Quarters</member>
        <member>Main Computer Core #2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 9</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Sick Bay</member>
        <member>Main Science Complex</member>
        <member>Family Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Transporter Rooms</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 10</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Main Engineering, M/ARC</member>
        <member>Auxillary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Torpedo launchers and storage</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 11</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Starbase Umbilical Connection</member>
        <member>Cargobays</member>
        <member>Science Complexes</member>
        <member>Mount for Runabout or Trafalgar-class Mission Module</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 12</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Captain's Yacht Bay</member>
        <member>Cargobays</member>
        <member>Landing Struts</member>
        <member>Brig</member>
        <member>Tractor beam emitter</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Ships of the Class</title>
    <simplelist role="ShipList">
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Heisenburg</productname>
        <productnumber>74300</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Einstein</productname>
        <productnumber>74302</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Asimov</productname>
        <productnumber>74304</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Darwin</productname>
        <productnumber>74305</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Sagan</productname>
        <productnumber>74308</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Crick</productname>
        <productnumber>74310</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Dalton</productname>
        <productnumber>74315</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Volta</productname>
        <productnumber>74316</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Hawkings</productname>
        <productnumber>74320</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Verne</productname>
        <productnumber>74322</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Fleming</productname>
        <productnumber>74326</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Curie</productname>
        <productnumber>74329</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Golgi</productname>
        <productnumber>74341</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Adams</productname>
        <productnumber>74342</productnumber>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <epigraph>
      <para>"Check, please!"</para>
    </epigraph>
  </section>
</article>
