<article class="specification" id="fulcrum">
  <title>Fulcrum-class</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup role="Maintainer">
      <author>
        <firstname>Levon</firstname>
        <surname>Johnson</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Primary Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Levon</firstname>
        <surname>Johnson</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword role="service">PC/NPC</keyword>
      <keyword role="category">Runabout</keyword>
      <keyword role="variant">Scientific</keyword>
      <keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>07/27/14</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Engineering Director Robert Archer</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>History and Mission Overview</title>
    <para>In 2380, after a major fleet review, several members of numerous scientific bodies in the Federation felt that almost all of the auxiliary craft currently in use in Starfleet were majorly inadequate to scientific field work. To counter this, many lobbied for a new research and development project later that year, which ultimately gave way to the Fulcrum Class Scientific Runabout being commissioned in 2388. The prototypes and soon newly commissioned class of runabouts soon proved popular with many scientific and exploration away teams allowing more extensive studies while in the field.</para>
    <para/>
	<section>
    <title>Mission Profiles</title>
	  <para>The mission profile for the Fulcrum-class is as follows:</para>
    <simplelist>
      <member>To explore anomalies closer than a starship generally would with manned missions.</member>
	  <member>To perform reconnaissance missions ahead of a starship at low to mid-warp speeds.</member>
      <member>To detect anomalies faster than would be possible otherwise, through the use of a smaller auxiliary craft.</member>
      <member>To allow ships with minimal scientific abilities the ability to catalogue stellar phenomenon etc.</member>
	</simplelist>
  </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Structure and Construction</title>
    <para>The Fulcrum class is shaped near the bow as an angular smooth nose cone shaped hull. This then angles back to a sloping upwards rectangular box shaped aft hull structure. Three angular pylons extend in a triangular shape with two below the hull and one above. These add streamlined dynamics for more efficient atmospheric and sublight speed travel. It also provides more surface area for the mounting of required exterior technology and better use of interior space.</para>
	<para>The upper pylon contains the main sensor array in a triangular shaped sensor pod, while the lower two pylons contain the impulse engines and built in warp nacelles. The Fulcrum is built out of a two-decked, single-layer hull frame made from standard duranium alloys. It was then transporter welded to increase its strength and reduce construction time.</para>
    <para/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
	<section>
	<title>Sensor Systems</title>
	<para>The triangular sensor pod atop of the upper pylon houses a Class 5 sensor system, which is linked to the primary computer core directly to allow for maximum transfer speed and analysis. This allows the Fulcrum to pick up and relay anomalies, and other sensor data faster than other craft or ships with a Class-5 system. This sensor system and tandem relay network allows for a high resolution scan of 2.14 light years, and a low resolution scan 7.0 light years. Finally, the main deflector array is enclosed in a circular housing in the bow of the ship below the front of the cone shaped cockpit on deck 2.</para>
	<section>
	  <title>Computer Systems</title>
	  <para>The Fulcrum’s computer systems were one of the main focus points of the research and development project with the intention of building a superior and more redundant system structure than on other small auxiliary craft. As a result, the ship contains not one, but two individual and separated isolinear computer cores.</para>
	  <para>The first core, which is larger, is dedicated to the analysing and archiving of input from the sensor pod and other sensory systems. It also handles the retrieval and distribution of this information through the LCARS operating system and MAJEL user interface. The core is located along the ‘spine’ of the ship on deck 1, allowing it to take up as little interior area as possible. The second core is smaller than the first, and is used primarily for control of all primary systems other than information gathering and distribution. As such it handles weapons, navigation, transporters, and other associated systems. This core is located at the far aft end of the ship, in an alcove beneath deck 2.</para>
	  <para>The Fulcrum utilises both standard isolinear and bio-neural systems. These work in tandem to produce a more efficient overall system response. The isolinear chips used on the Fulcrum class’ first core are ‘double coated’ with the isolinear crystal formula. This allowed for extra storage space at the cost of transfer speed. The secondary core uses standard isolinear chips. The whole ship is wired with isolinear relays, with key junctions housing a bio-neural gel pack. This allows for a more efficient transfer with lack of latency, and less packet loss between junctions.</para>
      </section>
  </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Warp Propulsion Systems</title>
    <para>The Fulcrum class was provided with a standard Class 3 warp core, with a Cochrane rating of 392. The core is mounted on the aft end of decks 1 and 2 with ejection systems propelling the core out the bottom of the ship in an emergency. This warp core provides the runabout with a Cruising Velocity of Warp 3.0, a Maximum Sustainable Velocity of Warp 5.0, a Maximum Velocity of Warp 6.0 for 12 hours and an Emergency Speed of Warp 6.7 for 1 hour. This core feeds the ship’s two warp nacelles through their pylon mountings.</para>
    <para/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
    <para>The Fulcrum class was provided with two standard micro-impulse reactors and engines, one in each lower pylon extending from the ventral of the ship. These combined provide a maximum speed of .25c. The engines provide an acceleration to maximum velocity in approximately 31 seconds, and to a full stop in approximately the same time.</para>
    <para/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Tactical Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Defensive Shields</title>
	  <para>The Fulcrum class was provided with a Type-4 shield system, which provides a maximum graviton load of 537 megawatts, and a maximum dissipation rate of 1.46 x 10 ^ 5 kilowatts. Emitters for the system are placed in pairs of two in a rectangular shape along the body of the hull, primarily along the pylons and the angular hull lines.</para>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Phaser Systems</title>
	  <para>The Fulcrum class was provided with five Type-5 phaser arrays, each providing a maximum of 0.3 megawatts of output at an effective range of 18,750 kilometres. These arrays are positioned as follows:</para>
	  <simplelist>
			<member>Two arrays to port and starboard, each with 10 emitters per array.</member>
			<member>One array ventral and dorsal, each with 7 emitters per array.</member>
			<member>One array at the fore of the ship, each with 5 emitters per array.</member>
	  </simplelist>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Torpedo Systems</title>
	  <para>The Fulcrum class was provided with a type-1 micro-torpedo launcher, which allows up to one torpedo to be fired every eight seconds. This ship has the capacity to hold up to 15 standard micro-casings of torpedoes, and up to 15 micro-probes of different classes. In addition to standard micro-casings, the Fulcrum class utilises two expendable external casings, which are mounted on the pylons. These allow the ship to either mount two full sized standard torpedoes, or two full sized probes for special operations/missions.</para>
      <para/>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Command and Support Systems</title>
    <section>
	<title>Cockpit</title>
	<para>The cockpit includes three bridge consoles organised into the stations of science, helm/navigation, and tactical/operations. The cockpit is organised in a rounded triangular design, with the helmsman console at the far front, science console to the right of the helm, and tactical/operations to the left. This positioning allows for maximum space to be used without waste.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Engine Room</title>
	<para>The engine room houses the main impulse reactors and the warp core for the runabout inside a long rectangular room on deck 2. The warp core runs vertically along decks 1 and 2, with the impulse reactor running side by side on deck 2. Beside the warp core on the port side, there is the primary computer core inside an alcove, which connects directly to the impulse reactors for continuous uninterrupted supply of power. There are two consoles along the length of the warp core and impulse generators, one for the regulation and maintenance of each system. Inside the alcove, there is a ring of consoles around the data core for management and administration of the core.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Mission-Specific Holographic Laboratory</title>
	<para>The Fulcrum class’ main mission profile left Starfleet Corp of Engineers with a new task - developing a large enough area to contain a full-blown science, engineering, medical laboratories, and a sufficient sickbay. To fulfil this within space constraints, they turned to holotechnology to provide the answer.</para>
	<para>This room, located at the centre of deck one, is circular in shape, with a total projection size limit of 15 meters in diameter, and 4.3 meters high. Specialized holoprojection walls and emitters contain the room’s outline and major furniture within this area. This room has the capability to be changed into one of four types of rooms set and programmed before mission launch:</para>
	<simplelist>
		<member>Science Laboratory - Contains a basic field science laboratory able to handle basic scientific research.</member>
		<member>Engineering Laboratory - Contains a basic field engineering laboratory and repair shop to handle basic engineering repairs and research.</member>
		<member>Medical Laboratory - Contains a basic field medical laboratory to handle basic medical research and examinations.</member>
		<member>Sickbay - Contains a field sickbay able to hold a 3 patient biobed room and morgue unit.</member>
	</simplelist>
	<para>The holoprojection is limited, however, in what it can produce. The room is constrained to built-in components - anything that needs to be handheld, scanners, or portable must be brought along in storage. In addition, the storage lockers inside the Fulcrum are only large enough to carry materials for one of the holodeck profiles for any one mission. This requires restock at a starship or starbase to enable a different profile to be loaded with the required equipment.</para>
	</section>
   </section>
  <section>
    <title>Utility Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Storage Bay</title>
	  <para>The storage bay on the Fulcrum class is located behind the Holographic Laboratory, towards the port side. The room is approximately two meters square, and any materials and handheld equipment required for use within the Holographic Laboratory are stored here.</para>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tractor Beam Systems</title>
	  <para>The Fulcrum class was designed with one standard tractor beam emitter at the dorsal aft section of deck one. This emitter has the capability to move 907 metric tons out to a range of 50 kilometers.</para>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Transporter Systems</title>
	  <para>The Fulcrum class was designed with a single-person transporter pad, located behind the Holographic Laboratory, to the starboard side. The room is approximately two metres square, and the transporter has a maximum range of 40,000 kilometres.</para>
    </section>
	<section>
	<title>Access Lift</title>
	<para>The access lift used on the Fulcrum class is located behind the Holographic Laboratory, towards the far aft, and is between the transporter pad and storage bay. The lift is approximately two metres in diameter, and provides access to both decks as needed.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Crew Support Systems</title>
	<section>
	<title>Crew Mess Room</title>
	<para>The Fulcrum class was designed with a single mess room, located just fore of the engine room on deck two. The room is square in shape, at ten metres by ten metres. This room is equipped with a single replicator unit, and a four person table with chairs.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Crew Bunk Room</title>
	<para>The Fulcrum class was designed with the crew capacity to provide living spaces for up to eight people at any time. The room is square in shape, at ten metres by ten metres. The crew bunk room is located at the centre of deck two, just foward of the mess room, and contains eight beds arranged into paired bunks with personal storage lockers.</para>
	</section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Technical Specifications</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Dimensions and Structure</title>    
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Length</term>
        <listitem><para>30 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Beam (Width)</term>
        <listitem><para>20 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Height</term>
        <listitem><para>9 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Decks</term>
        <listitem><para>2</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Crew Complement</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pilots:</term>
        <listitem><para>1</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Crew</term>
        <listitem><para>8</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Evacuation Limit</term>
        <listitem><para>35</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>      
    <variablelist>
      <title>Computer Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Core</term>
        <listitem><para>Isolinear data core x3</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Operating System</term>
        <listitem><para>LCARS 7.0 with MAJEL interface</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>        
    <variablelist>
      <title>Warp Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Power Plant</term>
        <listitem><para>1x 392+ cochrane MARA core, feeding two nacelles</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Cruising Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>Warp 3.0</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Sustainable Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>Warp 5.0</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>Warp 6.0 (12 hours)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Emergency Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>Warp 6.7 (1 hour)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Impulse Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Full Impulse</term>
        <listitem><para>0.25c</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Acceleration</term>
        <listitem><para>31 seconds</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Deceleration</term>
        <listitem><para>31 seconds</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Defensive Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)</term>
        <listitem><para>537 MegaWatts</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate</term>
        <listitem><para>1.46x10^5 kilowatts</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Offensive Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Torpedoes</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Torpedo Tubes</term>
              <listitem><para>1x Type 1 Micro-Torpedo Tube</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Standard Payload (total)</term>
              <listitem><para>15x micro photon torpedoes</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>15x micro scientific probes</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mission Specific: 2x standard photon torpedoes / standard scientific probes (externally mounted)</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Phasers</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>5x Type-V Phaser Arrays</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Deck Layout</title>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 1</title>
      <simplelist>
		<member>Cockpit</member>
		<member>Main Deflector</member>
		<member>Sensor Arrays</member>
		<member>Phaser Arrays</member>
		<member>Holo-Projection Laboratories</member>
		<member>Storage Bay</member>
		<member>Transporter Pad</member>
		<member>Access Lift</member>
		<member>Tractor Emitter</member>
		<member>Upper Warp Core</member>
		<member>Upper Deuterium Storage</member>
		<member>Deuterium Storage Fill Port</member>
	  </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section>
	  <title>Deck 2</title>
      <simplelist>
		<member>Torpedo/Probe Launcher</member>
		<member>Torpedo/Probe Storage</member>
		<member>Crew Bunk Room</member>
		<member>Crew Mess Room</member>
		<member>Engine Room</member>
		<member>Computer Core 1 &amp; 2</member>
		<member>Lower Deuterium Storage</member>
		<member>Lower Warp Core</member>
		<member>Warp Core &amp; Deuterium Storage Ejection Systems</member>
		<member>Impulse Engine</member>
	  </simplelist>
    </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Ships of the Class</title>
	<para>The ships of the Fulcrum class are named with an engineering or scientific theme. Currently commissioned are the below:</para>
    <simplelist role="ShipList">
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Fulcrum</productname>
        <productnumber>11000</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Cohesion</productname>
        <productnumber>11001</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Inertia</productname>
        <productnumber>11002</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Sublimation</productname>
        <productnumber>11003</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Horsepower</productname>
        <productnumber>11004</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Integral</productname>
        <productnumber>11005</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Fluid</productname>
        <productnumber>11006</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Concave</productname>
        <productnumber>11007</productnumber>
      </member>
	  <member role="PC">
        <productname>Convex</productname>
        <productnumber>11008</productnumber>
      </member>
	  <member role="PC">
        <productname>Centroid</productname>
        <productnumber>11009</productnumber>
      </member>
	  <member role="PC">
        <productname>Amplifier</productname>
        <productnumber>11010</productnumber>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
	<para>The development and production of the Fulcrum class allows Starfleet to explore more scientific anomalies than generally would be possible with standard starship operations. The class’ versatility with its holoprojection laboratory allows a variety of field tasks to be undertaken by away teams more efficiently than was possibly previously. Further, it allows its parent craft/base to extend their range in scientific endeavors and scouting missions.</para>
    <para/>
  </section>
</article>
