<article class="specification" id="kearsarge">
	<title>Kearsarge-class</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup role="Maintainer">
			<author>
				<firstname>EDept</firstname>
				<surname>Staff</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Primary Designers">
			<author>
				<firstname>Bret</firstname>
				<surname>Godfrey</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Original Designers">
			<author>
				<firstname>Bret</firstname>
				<surname>Godfrey</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword role="service">PC</keyword>
			<keyword role="category">Cruiser</keyword>
			<keyword role="variant">Medium</keyword>
			<keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>2 April 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Assistant Engineering Director Bradley Joy and Dockmaster Larry Garfield</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>History and Mission Overview</title>
		<para>As the Federation entered a new, yet tentative age of peace with the Klingons in the years that followed the Khitomer Accord, Star Fleet began to reassess the condition, inventory, and mission profile of its fleet.  Before that time, older designs such had been relegated to boarder patrol and training duties while newer, more capable designs slowly took over the role of deep space exploration.  As promised in the Khitomer Accord, Star Fleet began demilitarizing and dismantling the outpost network along the Klingon Neutral Zone, while at the same time reducing the size of its combat fleet.  Thus many ships of the old guard literally found themselves decommissioned over night.  Ironically, this practice created an even greater need for new ship construction.</para>
		<para>In 2295, Star Fleet Command initiated a directive for the construction of a new medium exploration cruiser design.  Several contractors were invited to participate in a bidding contest for the new class designation. A combination of speed, space frame durability, tactical effectiveness, and space exploration sciences were to be incorporated into the over all design. In the end it was the Salazaar Shipyards of Andoria that won the contract with their prototype, the USS Mariner.  After successful completion of the Mariner's shake down cruise, Star Fleet placed an order for a further 50 ships of the same class.  Over the decades, the Mariner Class has more then proven its worth with a highly decorated service record.  Of special note are the astounding numbers of successful first contact missions that the ships of this class have carried out.  Though it was specifically designed as an exploration vessel, its mix of maneuverability, firepower, and Rodinium armor platting proved that the ship was a valuable tactical asset during the Tomed incident of 2311.</para>
		<para>Though having a long and enduring design life, by 2365, the Mariner hulls were beginning to show their age.  Star Fleet enacted a retirement plan where the older ships would be replaced as ships from newer designs were commissioned.  Over half the surviving Mariner Class ships were deactivated by the time of the Wolf-359 debacle. In an effort to quickly fill in the gaps caused by the Borg incursion, a retrofitting of retired space hulls was enacted. The generous use of Titanium in the Mariner's superstructure and hull plating was found to be a great asset in that titanium was cheaper and in more readily accessible quantities then Duranium or Tritanium alloys. This decreased the time index during refit, while at the same time aloud Star Fleet to use the newer alloys on new ship construction.   After completion of the first modernized hull, the USS Keararge ( NCC-2367), Star Fleet came to the conclusion that the over all enhancements were so divergent from the original design, that they deserved a designation all their own.  Thus the Kearsarge Class medium cruiser was born from the ashes of the soon to be scrapped Mariner.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Structure and Construction</title>
		<para>In appearance, the Kearsarge is of a standard configuration.  The saucer section is attached to the secondary hull via a front dorsal neck mounting, while the twin warp nacelles are fitted to the aft section of the secondary hull via upward turned pylons.</para>
		<para>The majority of the Kearsarge's space frame is made up of pure titanium with three separate framed hull layers. Once the pluming and electrical systems were in place and covered by hull plating, titanium fiber enriched duroplast foam was pressure injected into the spaces between the hull layers for insulation and radiation shielding. The outer most hull has an additional 4.5 cm layer of homogeneously rolled rodinium armor plating. Rodinium, the hardest known substance in Federation Science, was until that time primarily used for shielding on static structures such as an orbital Outpost or Starbase.  Though its heavy mass prevents it from use in Starship structural components, it works well as a hull layer armoring against physical penetration or focused energy attacks. Upon completion, a nonreflecting thermo coat of battleship-grey was electro-magnetically bonded to the rodinium hull, giving the ship a dull finish.  On average, the over all hull thickness of a completed space frame is 30.0cm.</para>
		<para>As was the practice of the time, during an extreme emergency, the saucer section was designed to be jettisoned from the secondary hull and act as a large life boat for the crew.  In such an occurrence, the impulse motor on the aft of the saucer section would act as the main propulsion drive and power generating plant.  Explosive bolts placed strategically along stress points with in the neck mount physically sever the saucer section from the secondary hull.  Once separated, the saucer can not be reattached to the secondary hull with out the services of a dry dock repair facility.  Although this was a common design feature, there are only two instances of ships from any class performing such a feat.  Maximum impulse speed of the Saucer section with the secondary hull jettisoned is 0.15 c.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
		<para>Along the hull of the ship are located a total of 200 sensors used for navigational, remote sensing, scientific, and tactical acquisition data collection. The sensory suite is designed for both active and passive data collection. In normal space flight operations, both methods are automatically employed simultaneously, though they can be reconfigured as active or passive only. Active sensory grids are echo collection devices that transmit a pulse signal, usually radio, optical, infrared, or subspace, and then interpret the rebounded signal in forms of cohesive data.  Passive sensory grids "listen" for physical and subspace signals that are given off by either a natural or artificial object. </para>
		<para>The original sensory equipment installed on the Mariner Class had a Standard high resolution range of approximately 2.5 light years in high resolution, and 8.5 light years in low resolution.  However, the current sensory package on the Kearsarge has a high resolution of 4.4 light years, and a low resolution range of 14.9 light years. Both figures are highly dependant on the current spatial conditions that the ship is experiencing. If the situation arises, the sensor grid can be used as an ECM device, effectively jamming most types of radio and subspace communications and navigational frequencies with decreasing effectiveness to a distance of 700,000km, depending on local relativistic conditions, though this will also render the ship's own subspace communications inoperable.</para>
		<para>In addition, the Kearsarge has on hand a usual complement of 25 prededicated scientific probes, and another 25 empty torpedo casings ready for scientific or tactical augmentation. </para>
		<section>
			<title>Computer Systems</title>
			<para>The Mariner was designed and built with one large and one smaller multitronic computer cores. The primary core was located in the center of decks 3, 4, and 5 of the saucer section, with the smaller back up core in the center aft of the secondary hull in deck-12. The smaller core housed compressed archive data as a means of back up storage.  Even though the ship class has seen many software and hardware upgrades in its service, the original bi-core design has been maintained.  The current refit of the Kearsarge utilizes a single standard M-6 Isolinear core, with the M-2 Multitronic Auxiliary Core. Both computer systems are managed by the LCARS version 1.2, and are interlinked with standard ODN conduits to the various quadratronic sub processors through out the ship.  The function of the secondary core has largely been relocated to simple information back up storage.  In an emergency, it can be reconfigured to operate most of the Kearsarge's primary systems such as navigation, propulsion, weapons, and life support, though on a limited capacity.  It should be noted that the secondary core has neither the computative speed, nor the operational data storage to maintain any of the three holosuites installed as crew recreational facilities.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Warp Propulsion Systems</title>
		<para>For reasons of simplicity in construction, the Kearsarge utilizes a Class-VII warp core. It is similar to, but 25% smaller then the core designed for the Excelsior Class. To save space, the core is mounted horizontally along the centerline of the ship's X-axis running for to aft with in the secondary hull.  The ejection protocols happen with in a 3 second time interval because of the sequences of explosive separation and ejection.  During a warp core breach, the core is ejected through a service hatch directly aft from the Kearsarge's secondary hull.  Though the Kearsarge has kept the original warp core configuration, it has an enhanced and upgraded multi port fuel injector system, along with self modulating field coils in the nacelles. The original warp core for the Mariner was rated at 1270 cochranes with a max velocity of Warp-8.5 for 12 hours, a max sustainable velocity of warp-6, and a cruising speed of warp-5.  The current Kearsarge warp core is rated at 1500+ cochranes, with a maximum velocity of warp-9.5 for 12 hours, a maximum sustainable velocity of warp-7.2, and a standard cruising speed of warp-5. </para>
		<para>NOTE: Though the original Mariner warp core was designed before the current Subspace Protection Act requirements, the newly rebuilt Kearsarge warp propulsion system has been certified as SPA safe.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
		<para>As can be expected, there have been many improvements in impulse propulsion designs in the last 80 years.  Although the Kearsarge's sub light speed is the same as the Mariner, it has a 30% greater acceleration rate and a 75% increase in efficiency.  The dual vent impulse drive is mounted directly aft of, and attached to the saucer section.  The impulse drive is designed to propel the ship up to and including 0.25c, with an acceleration rate from zero to 0.25c of 20 seconds, and a deceleration rate from 0.25c to zero in 40 seconds.</para>
		<para>Slush deuterium fuel for the impulse drive is stored in three self pressurizing and stabilizing, two primary tanks and one auxiliary.  The two primary tanks are located on apposing sides of the Impulse Motor, Deck-6 of the Saucer Section.  The auxiliary deuterium tank is located in the center portion of Deck-12 in the Secondary Hull.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Tactical Systems</title>
		<section>
			<title>Defensive Shields</title>
			<para>After extensive refit, the Kearsarge's shielding system consists of eight shield generators located at key points along the space frame.  Each generator is comprised of nine 24MW graviton polarity sources feeding into a single 470 milliconchrane subspace field distortion amplifier. During alert status, the shield generators can combine to provide a continuous gravitation load of 2016 MW with a maximum primary energy dissipation rate of 5.5 x 10^5.  Where as the Mariner's shields were rated at only half the gravitational load and energy dissipation rate. </para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Phaser Systems</title>
			<para>In its original configuration, the Mariner was outfitted with a mix of two separate phaser systems.  It mounted a total of six Type-VIII phasers in three banks of two.  Each bank covered a firing arc of 60-degree elevation and azimuth.  In addition, there were six Type-VII phasers, again mounted in 3 banks of two, covering any gap in arc left by the Type-VIII weapons system.</para>
			<para>During the Keararge refit, this bulky and inefficient weapons system was completely removed and replaced with a simpler, more powerful tactical system.  It was re-equipped with the now standard Type-IX phaser strip array.  There are a total of nine array strips placed along the space frame to give a near perfect 360-degree firing arc in both azimuth and elevation.   All of the Type-IX phaser arrays used on the Kearsarge is rated at maximum beam energy of 3.8 MW with a maximum tactical range of 225,000km.</para>
			<para>Phaser Arrays #1-2 are located in the upper forward saucer section on Deck-4 and cover the forward port, forward, and forward starboard firing arcs.  Both arrays are outfitted with 125 emitters each.</para>
			<para>Phaser Arrays #3-4 are located in the lower forward saucer section on Deck-6 and cover the forward port, forward, and forward starboard firing arcs.  Both arrays are outfitted with 125 emitters each.</para>
			<para>Phaser Arrays #5-6 are located on the outer broadsides of the port and starboard warp nacelles.  Both arrays are outfitted with 20 emitters each.</para>
			<para>Phaser Array #7 is mounted in the aft section of the secondary hull just above the shuttlebay on deck-12 and is outfitted with 10 emitters.  It covers the aft firing arc.</para>
			<para>Phaser Arrays #8-9 are mounted on the bottom of the secondary hull on deck-14.  Array #8 covers the lower port broadside, while the #9 array covers the lower starboard broadside.  Both arrays are outfitted with 10 emitters respectively.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Torpedo Systems</title>
			<para>Although the Kearsarge's launching system is highly modified, it has retained the original three photon torpedo launch systems lay out, taking up the entire space of Deck-8 inside the dorsal neck mount.  During the refit, the old "Manual Only" loader system for all three launchers were replaced with an automated loading system.  This reduced the number of personnel needed to maintain and man the launchers, with the added bonus of shortening the response time. Two launchers are situated facing directly forward, while a third launcher is mounted to fire directly aft.  All three launchers are mounted in such a way as to allow independent launching of torpedoes.  Each launcher has the capability of launching a steady stream of torpedoes with a firing rate of 20 torpedoes per minute, at a maximum range of 3,500,000km.</para>
			<para>All three launchers are controlled from a single fire control room known as the "Torpedo Room" located on Deck-9 inside the dorsal neck mount.  The Torpedo Room is separated into two sections.  The first section handles the firing control and targeting of the photon torpedoes, while the second section is a maintenance area where the torpedoes can be maintained or reconfigured.  Also located on Deck-9 is the Torpedo Bunker, which is the main storage area for the usual complement of the 150 photon torpedoes, 25 scientific probes, and 25 empty torpedo casings.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Command and Support Systems</title>
		<section>
			<title>Bridge</title>
			<para>The Bridge is of a similar layout to that of the Excelsior Class Heavy Cruiser, though 25% smaller.  At center is the Captain's chair, with the Helmsman and Navigator's seats directly in front.  Although there is no designated seat for the Executive Officer, it is usually assumed the Exec is manning one of the swing position duty posts while on the Bridge such as OPS, or Tactical.  The Bridge is located at the center of Deck-1.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Auxiliary Control</title>
			<para>The Auxiliary Control Room is located in the center of Deck-4 of the saucer section.  It is continually manned and maintained.  In the event of a ship wide catastrophe, all the major ship's functions and navigation can be controlled from here.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Armory</title>
			<para>The Ship's Armory is located adjacent to the Brig on Deck-14.  The Armory is stocked with a usual complement of 50 Type-I hand phasers, 100 Type-II hand phasers, 100 Type-III phaser rifles, 75 sets of kevlex body armor, 120 Anastazine gas grenades, 120 concussion grenades, and 120 photon grenades.   Access to the Armory is highly restricted to that of the ship's CO, XO, all the Department Heads, and the Security staff, and is granted only after a DNA palm print scan.</para>
			<para>To protect against a hostile boarding of the ship, there are also several weapons lockers strategically placed in prominent areas of the ship.  These areas include the Auxiliary Control, Bridge, Brig, Main Engineering, all the Transporter Rooms, the Shuttlebay, and the Torpedo Room.  During normal operations, only the Command and Security staff (as stated for the Armory) may gain access to the lockers.  During yellow or red alert status, any ship's crewmember may gain access via DNA thumb print verification.  Each locker contains 12 Type-II hand phasers. </para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Brig</title>
			<para>Located on Deck-14, the Brig is comprised of five cells, a common "watch" area and COS's office. The "watch" area is nothing more then a duty station in which a security officer can stand watch over the prisoners. Each cell is equipped with a small "drum" dispenser for the secure transfer of items and food both to and from the cell.  The drum has an opening on only one section of its curved surface, and is made out of 0.5cm solid duranium, which in turn is mounted to a framework of solid duranium that extends 25.0cm with in the bulkhead of the wall.  Once an object is placed with in the drum, the drum is rotated so that its opened section "faces" the opposite side of the wall.  For reasons of security, the controls for the drum dispenser are placed on the "watch" duty station and not with in the detention cell itself.  This is to prevent a prisoner from escaping his cell by using the drum dispenser to gain access to his cell controls.  There is a single food replicator mounted near the "watch" duty station and is totally inaccessible to cell occupants.</para>
			<para>Also housed in the Brig is the ship's vault. The vault is a secured storage compartment which can be used to safely store information and evidence in a criminal investigation, sensitive mission specific material or information that can not be stored in the ship's cargo bay or the ship's computers, currency, or personal items for the crew and passengers. The vault is separated into a safe, and 100 locked boxes. Either the safe, or the boxes can be individually preset to its own lock combination and climate controls. Access to the vault is granted only by senior officer identification. This identification is verified by voice print, optical retina scan, and palm print. All three must be successful for the senior officer to gain access to the vault. The Brig is located on Deck-14.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Chartroom</title>
			<para>The ship's Chart Room is located aft of the Main Bridge on Deck-1. The Chart Room is comprised of three main viewing displays and fifteen smaller ones, each with their own console. The Chart Room is basically an interactive library in which astrophysical data is prioritized, catalogued, and studied for scientific, navigational, or tactical needs.  Although this room is designed as a navigational aid, its primary use is for the scientific study of interstellar objects.  In times of war, the Chart Room can be easily reconfigured as a War Room in the event that a ranking fleet officer should wish to use the ship as his flag ship during strategic operations.  Using the various monitors at his disposal, a flotilla commander can keep track of the ebb and flow of battle from different perspectives, giving him an important aid in dictating the tactics of his overall command.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Main Engineering</title>
			<para>Main Engineering is located near the center of the secondary hull on Decks-10-11-12.  On either end of the compartment is a single three man turbolift which only operates with in Main Engineering itself.  The warp core lays horizontal along the floor of Deck-12 and runs from fore to aft.  The Chief Engineer's office is located on the forward end of the Engineering compartment on Deck-10 and is situated so that the Chief Engineer can oversee the operations of his department. </para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Utility Systems</title>
		<section>
			<title>Cargo Bays</title>
			<para>The main cargo bays are located in the lower aft section of the Secondary Hull between the shuttlebays, and the main deflector dish. There are four cargo holds in total. Each cargo bay is equipped with two entrances, one opening towards outer space for offloading via work bee, shuttlecraft, or space dock.  The second entrance is a duel access airlock opening into the ship's corridor.  The airlock acts as a buffer between the cargo hold and the rest of the ship.  Each cargo hold is compartmentalized, and can be configured to provide either a H, K, L, M, N, or N(2) environment for the safe storage of perishable cargo or to house life forms that exist in other terrestrial environments other then Class-M. This design gives the ship the capability of storing perishable cargo or housing life forms in their proper environment.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Tractor Beam Systems</title>
			<para>There are four tractor beam projectors located on the four outer corners of the space frame. Though they are meant for towing, they can be easily reconfigured as a repulser beam. In addition; the two aft tractor beams are designed to be able to tractor a damaged or escaping shuttle craft into the safety of the shuttlebay. All four tractor beam emitters are rigged so that an object can be "walked" into the desired position. For example: If a shuttlecraft is located foreword of the ship, the crewman manning OPS can lock onto the shuttle craft, and bring it far enough aft so that the aft tractor beams can haul it into the shuttlebay. Effective range of the tractor beams is 30,000km, depending on local relativistic conditions.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Transporter Systems</title>
			<para>There are a total of 7 transporters designed into the Kearsarge's deck plan. There are two standard six pad transporters, one port and one starboard in the saucer section.  In addition, there are two ten pad emergency transporters. One is located near sickbay in the saucer section, and the other is positioned with in the secondary hull. There are three cargo transporters, one in each of the primary cargo holds.  Ranges of the standard transporters are 40,000km, while that of the emergency and cargo transporters are only 15,000km respectively.  This transporter range is roughly double that of the Mariner's original transporter system.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Turbolifts</title>
			<para>There are 7 operational turbolifts.  Turbolift-1 is located in the center of the Saucer Section and has access from Deck-1 of the Saucer all the way to Deck-14 of the Secondary Hull.  Turbolift-2 is also located in the center of the Saucer, parallel with Turbolift-1, and has access from Deck-2 of the Saucer through Deck-14 of the Secondary Hull.  Turbolifts-2 and 3 have access from Deck-3 through Deck-6 of the Saucer Section, and are located port and starboard respectively.  Turbolift-7 is a cargo turbolift.  It is located in the aft section of the Saucer and has access from Deck-3 through Deck-14 of the Secondary Hull, and can traverse to each of the three main Cargo Holds.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Crew Support Systems</title>
		<section>
			<title>Crew Quarters</title>
			<para>When compared to more modern star ships, crew quarters are rather cramped. Enlisted, NE, and Junior Officers are billeted in pairs, each sharing a small common lounge area and bathing facilities. The lounge is equipped with a dining booth module, and a work station that can double as an entertainment center. The bathroom is equipped with a sink, toilet, and a sonic shower. The crewmen each receive a separate bedroom which is only large enough for a twin bed, a dresser, and a small closet. Senior Officers fair slightly better in that they do not have to share their living space with another officer. But their stateroom, sleeping arrangement, and bathing facilities are of the same design as the Junior Officers. The Captain, Executive Officer, and visiting V.I.P.'s fair much better. Each has a dining module roughly 25% larger then the junior officers, a bathroom with a whirlpool bath/ sonic shower, and a bedroom large enough for a walk in closet, a full sized bed, and a large work/entertainment station. Only the Captain, Executive Officer, and V.I.P. quarters are outfitted with food replicators similar to the ones found in either of the crew lounges.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Forecastle Lounge</title>
			<para>There are two crew lounges, the Forecastle, and the Fantail. The Forecastle Lounge is located in the forward most part of the saucer section on Deck-5.  This is usually considered as the Junior Officer, Enlisted and NE ranks lounge. Under usual conditions, there is a movie shown on the large display screen twice a week for the crew's enjoyment, although programming is subject to Captain's discretion.  Also located in the Forecastle Lounge is a well stocked and fully equipped game locker.  Stocked inside is a wide range of portable table top games for the crew to use at their leisure.   The locker may be stocked with such games as three dimensional chess, holo-battleship, and Fizbit.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Fantail Lounge</title>
			<para>The Fantail lounge is located on the aft most section of Deck-6.  It is smaller, and has a minor increase in creature comforts when compared to the Forecastle.  As such, it is usually considered as the command staff and VIP lounge.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Holosuites</title>
			<para>During the Kearsarge's refit, many of the modernized crew support systems used less volume, power, and computer resources then the antiquated systems they were replacing.  This afforded the Kearsarge the luxery of obtaining three Holosuites, one on either side of the Forecastle on Deck-5.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Gymnasium</title>
			<para>There is a small gymnasium located on the lower aft section of Deck-8.  It is equipped with a sparing wring for boxing/wrestling/fencing or other forms of hand to hand combat, and nautilus machinery to keep the crew in peek physical condition.  Should the situation arise, the Gymnasium's equipment can be easily stored, thus opening up the room's area to be used as an auditorium or act as an auxiliary storage room.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Galley</title>
			<para>Located near the center of Deck-4 is the ship's Galley.  At the time of the Mariner's construction contract, replicator technology was just starting to come of age.  Although capable of reproducing a variety of food selections, many starships of the era were equipped with both a replicator system, and a fully functioning Galley.  As replicator technology became more advanced, the importance of the Galley was reduced.  Currently, the Kearsarge's only Galley duties are that specified for the Captain's and Senior Officer's mess, formal social functions, emergency rationing of food during a crisis, and the immediate dietary needs specific of visitors and crew who's nutritional requirements can not be supported by the replicator system.  Food stuffs for the Galley are stored in three separate fully compartmentalized pantries, each compartment equipped with their own stasis field generators to preserve freshness.</para>
			<para>Because of power and equipment requirement factors during the refit, it was decided that the new and improved replicator units would be limited to the original locations of the antiquated units they were replacing.  These areas include: the Brig, both the Forecastle and Fantail crew lounges, the Captain's, XO's, and VIP's quarters, Main Engineering, Sickbay, the Shuttlebay, and the Transporter Rooms.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Medical Facilities</title>
			<para>The ship's Sickbay is located on Deck-5, in the very center of the saucer section, and is the most highly protected section in the entire ship. Sickbay is comprised of two examination rooms separated by a surgical room, which in turn is also bordered by a recovery room. Each examination room is outfitted with two biobeds. The surgical room is similarly outfitted with two bio beds, which are in turn modified specifically for delicate surgical procedures. The recovery room is outfitted with twelve bio beds that are designed more for a patient's comfort and recovery. In addition, there is an emergency aid station located on every deck near the turbolift entrance.  Each aid station is nothing more then an equipment locker housing three antigrav gurneys, and two fully stocked emergency first aid kits.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Auxiliary Spacecraft Systems</title>
		<para>As stated before, the shuttlecraft landing bay is located aft of the secondary hull. The launch bay is comprised of a double set of doors as a safe guard against mechanical failure or damage suffered from combat. The Keararge's Shuttlebay is large enough to handle the maintenance and offloading requirements for a standard complement of five shuttle craft. If a mission requires the use of a runabout, three shuttle craft may be swapped for the use of one runabout. The bay is capable of launching two shuttle craft at a time (or one runabout). During normal operations, as the double bay doors are opened, a level-4 force field is erected to keep the shuttlebay's atmosphere inside the ship while allowing for the safe launch or retrieval of shuttlecraft.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Technical Specifications</title>
		<section>
			<title>Dimensions and Structure</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Length">350 meters</member>
				<member role="Beam (Width)">137 meters</member>
				<member role="Height">60.2 meters</member>
				<member role="Decks">14</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Crew Complement</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Officers and Crew">375</member>
				<member role="Command">25</member>
				<member role="Engineering">75</member>
				<member role="Medical">15</member>
				<member role="Science">200</member>
				<member role="Security">60</member>
				<member role="Visiting Personnel">60</member>
				<member role="Maximum Evacuation Limit">2000</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Computer Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Core">M-6 Isolinear Data Core, M-2 Multitronic Data Core</member>
				<member role="Operating System">Starfleet Library Computer Access and Retrieval System (LCARS) 1.2</member>
				<member role="User Interface">MAJEL</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Warp Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Power Plant">One 1500+ cochrane M/ARA cores feeding two nacelles</member>
				<member role="Cruising Velocity">Warp 5</member>
				<member role="Maximum Sustainable Velocity">Warp 7.2</member>
				<member role="Maximum Velocity">Warp 9.5 (12 hours)</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Impulse Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Full Impulse">0.25c</member>
				<member role="Accellerate">20 seconds</member>
				<member role="Decellerate">40 seconds</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Defensive Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)">2016 MegaWatts</member>
				<member role="Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate">5.5x10^5 kilowatts</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Offensive Systems</title>
			<simplelist role="Torpedoes">
				<member role="Torpedo Tubes">3</member>
				<member role="Standard Payload (total)">150 photon torpedoes, 25 probes, 25 empty unequipped casings</member>
			</simplelist>
			<simplelist role="Phasers">
				<member>9 Type-IX Phaser Strips</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Deck Layout</title>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 1</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Bridge</member>
				<member>Chart Room</member>
				<member>Conference Room-A</member>
				<member>Ready Room</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 2</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>CO's quarters</member>
				<member>XO's quarters</member>
				<member>VIP quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 3</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Conference Room-B</member>
				<member>Emergency Transporter #1</member>
				<member>Fan Tail Officer's Lounge</member>
				<member>Food Locker #1-3</member>
				<member>Galley</member>
				<member>Officer's quarters</member>
				<member>Primary Computer Core Level-1</member>
				<member>Shield Emitters #1-2</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 4</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Auxiliary Control</member>
				<member>Auxiliary Life Support</member>
				<member>Auxiliary Power</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Forecastle Crew Lounge</member>
				<member>Phaser Array #1-2 (forward port, and forward starboard)</member>
				<member>Primary Computer Core Level-2</member>
				<member>Sickbay</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 5</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Auxiliary Sensory Grid</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Docking Airlock #1-2 (Port and Starboard)</member>
				<member>Holosuite #1</member>
				<member>Primary Computer Core Level-3</member>
				<member>Primary Transporter Rooms #1-2 (port and starboard)</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 6</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Auxiliary Cargo Holds 1-2</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Deuterium Storage Tanks A and B (port and starboard)</member>
				<member>Impulse Drive (aft)</member>
				<member>Phaser Array #3-4 (forward port, and forward starboard)</member>
				<member>Tractor Beam Emitters #1-2 (Forward-Port and Forward-Starboard)</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 7</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Emergency Transporter #2</member>
				<member>Photon Torpedo Room</member>
				<member>Photon Torpedo Bunker</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 8</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Photon Torpedo Launchers #1-2-3 (#1-2 for, #3 aft)</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 9</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Archeology Lab</member>
				<member>Geophysics Lab</member>
				<member>Meteorology Lab</member>
				<member>Primary Communications Array</member>
				<member>Quantum Mechanics Lab</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 10</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Botanical Lab</member>
				<member>Biochemistry Lab</member>
				<member>Biophysics Lab</member>
				<member>Main Deflector Dish</member>
				<member>Main Engineering Level-1</member>
				<member>Primary Life Support</member>
				<member>Shield Emitters #3-4</member>
				<member>Xenobiology Lab</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 11</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Cargo Transporter #1-2</member>
				<member>Main Deflector Dish</member>
				<member>Main Engineering Level-2</member>
				<member>Mechanical Engineering Lab</member>
				<member>Primary Cargo Hold #1-2</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 12</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Auxiliary Computer Core</member>
				<member>Cargo Transporter #3</member>
				<member>Cybernetics Lab</member>
				<member>Deuterium Storage Tank-C</member>
				<member>Main Engineering Level-3</member>
				<member>Phaser Array #7 (aft)</member>
				<member>Primary Cargo Hold #3</member>
				<member>Shield Emitters #5-6</member>
				<member>Shuttlebay</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 13</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Cargo Transporter #4</member>
				<member>Fusion Reactors</member>
				<member>Primary Cargo Hold #4</member>
				<member>Shuttlebay</member>
				<member>Waste Reclamation</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
		<section role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 14</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Armory</member>
				<member>Brig</member>
				<member>Gymnasium</member>
				<member>Holosuites #2-3</member>
				<member>Phaser Array #8-9 (port, and starboard)</member>
				<member>Shield Emitters #7-8</member>
				<member>Tractor Beam Emitters #3-4</member>
			</simplelist>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Ships of the Class</title>
		<simplelist role="ShipList">
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Kearsarge</productname>
				<productnumber>2367</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Baldric</productname>
				<productnumber>2368</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Beowulf</productname>
				<productnumber>2369</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Calypso</productname>
				<productnumber>2370</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Celestial</productname>
				<productnumber>2371</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Dutchman</productname>
				<productnumber>2372</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Iron Horse</productname>
				<productnumber>2373</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Marblehead</productname>
				<productnumber>2374</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="NPC">
				<productname>Extraneous</productname>
				<productnumber>2355</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="NPC">
				<productname>Redundant</productname>
				<productnumber>2359</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="NPC">
				<productname>Rhetorical</productname>
				<productnumber>2360</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="NPC">
				<productname>Rustolium</productname>
				<productnumber>2361</productnumber>
			</member>
		</simplelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Conclusion</title>
		<para>Even though new ship construction is starting to cover the gap left in the fleet after the two Borg incursions and the Dominion war, the Kearsarge has proven its metal, adding on to the history of an already illustrious service career.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Illustrations</title>
		<para>These other visual representations of the Kearsarge are available.</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="thumbnail">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Larry</firstname>
						<surname>Garfield</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-top-thumb.jpg" format="JPG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="full">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Bret</firstname>
						<surname>Godfrey</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-top.jpg" format="JPG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>Kearsarge, Top View</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="thumbnail">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Larry</firstname>
						<surname>Garfield</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-side-thumb.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="full">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Bret</firstname>
						<surname>Godfrey</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-side.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>Kearsarge, Side View</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="thumbnail">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Larry</firstname>
						<surname>Garfield</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-aft-thumb.jpg" format="JPG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="full">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Bret</firstname>
						<surname>Godfrey</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-aft.jpg" format="JPG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>Kearsarge, Aft</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="thumbnail">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Larry</firstname>
						<surname>Garfield</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-top-thumb.jpg" format="JPG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="full">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Bret</firstname>
						<surname>Godfrey</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-top.jpg" format="JPG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>Kearsarge, Top View</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="full">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Bret</firstname>
						<surname>Godfrey</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-bottom.jpg" format="JPG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="thumbnail">
				<objectinfo>
					<author>
						<firstname>Larry</firstname>
						<surname>Garfield</surname>
					</author>
				</objectinfo>
				<imagedata fileref="images/kearsarge-bottom-thumb.jpg" format="JPG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>Kearsarge, Bottom View</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
	</section>
</article>
