<article class="specification" id="kurtzman">
  <title>Kurtzman-class</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup role="Maintainer">
      <author>
        <firstname>Andrew</firstname>
        <surname>Robinson</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Primary Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Andrew</firstname>
        <surname>Robinson</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Original Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Andrew</firstname>
        <surname>Robinson</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword role="service">PC</keyword>
      <keyword role="category">Battlecruiser (Abramsverse)</keyword>
      <keyword role="variant">Medium</keyword>u
      <keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>7 June, 2010</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Assistant Engineering Director Lee Bridgeford</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>History and Mission Overview</title>
    <para>After the destruction of Vulcan in early 2251 and in response to the presence of a highly powerful craft from the future, Starfleet determined that in order to effectively defend the Federation against such potentially destructive forces, a more concerted effort should be made to produce fast, maneuverable and powerful ships capable of combating the significantly advanced technology of the future.</para>
    <para>It quickly became clear that, with the exception of Enterprise and other Starship Class craft, Starfleet simply didn't have enough combat focused ships. Whilst it wished to maintain its primary function as an armada for exploration, Starfleet Command also now appreciated that it needed to begin placing a greater emphasis on its role as a peacekeeping force in defense of the Federation.</para>
    <para>Prior to the Nero crisis, Starfleet's McKinley Shipyards in Earth Orbit had been in the early stages of primary spaceframe construction on a new rapid deployment patrol craft known then as the Governor Class. With the damage the primary fleet suffered at the hands of the Klingons in the Laurentian System and with the vast majority of all near-Earth craft destroyed at the Battle of Vulcan, Starfleet Engineering began issuing contract assignments to civilian design and construction corporations. With some small adjustments to the primary spaceframe, the design team at fledgling starship development contractor Wolfestar Systems was able to adjust it to accommodate one of their concept designs.</para>
    <para>Marketed as a combat specific rapid response and space superiority craft, the new Kurtzman Class Medium Battlecruiser marked a new era for Starfleet. With an emphasis on heavier weapons and shielding as well as enhanced structural integrity systems, Starfleet immediately ordered construction to continue on the Kurtzman.</para>
    <para>With the spaceframe already constructed, Wolfestar began an immediate adaptation of the pre-existing Governor concept. With so much physical and design work already complete, it was barely two years before the USS Kurtzman left drydock and began its shakedown cruise.</para>
    <para>The Kurtzman Class is designed to function in the following capacities:</para>
    <simplelist role="Mission Objectives">
      <member>Patrol of Federation borders and internal system borders</member>
      <member>Rapid response to incursion</member>
      <member>Command and Control support of larger battle groups </member>
      <member>Ground based combat troop transport</member>
      <member>Space based support of ground operations</member>
      <member>Red Zone combat operations command</member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Structure and Construction</title>
    <para>In appearance, the Kurtzman consists of a saucer connected to a tubular star drive section via a dorsal neck mounting. The twin warp nacelles are fitted to the aft section of the secondary hull via V shaped pylons. It is similar in appearance to the larger Starship Class craft. The Kurtzman's hull is composed of a duranium-tritanium alloy in a 30cm double layer separated with 15cm of enriched duraplast foam. The outer layer of hull plating is in a state of permanent polarization to enable greater unprotected resistance to enemy weapons fire. The duranium-tritanium trusses that support the outer hull are laser welded to form a permanent support chassis. </para>
    <para>During extreme emergency, explosive bolts are in place across the nacelle-pylon connections and across the neck of the saucer-star drive connections to enable either or all to be separated should it be deemed necessary. Either the star drive or saucer section can be configured to act as a life pod in case of disaster. An emergency impulse drive is contained within the star drive, allowing the star drive, once separated to operate at impulse speeds up to .15c. The saucer section is capable of standard maximum sublight speeds, but is incapable of attaining warp speed. Provided the warp core is viable, the star drive section will operate at normal warp speeds after the default warp field geometry is manually adjusted to a predetermined separation setting.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
    <para>Given the need for the Kurtzman to have an active and powerful sensor suite without the attendant scientific research facilities, a series of 200 sensors are distributed throughout the outer hull. These sensors are used for navigation, remote sensing, tactical analysis and early warning data collection. Each sensor can be operated independently or in series in both passive and active data collection mode. The whole forms the collective 'sensor array'.  The sensor array aboard the Kurtzman is one of the most powerful in current service, with a high resolution scan range of 1.5 light years and a low resolution range of 6.5 light years. Through the application of high power emissions diodes, the sensor array can be utilized as a jamming system to prevent enemy vessels from sending or receiving transmissions. Effective jamming range for this system at full power is 390,000km. It should be noted that effecting this jamming system also prevents the jamming vessel from utilising their own communications systems. Whilst not a science vessel by design, the Kurtzman does carry 50 empty torpedo casings which can, at need, be configured for scientific or exploratory purposes. </para>
    <section>
      <title>Computer Systems</title>
      <para>The Kurtzman is designed and built with a dual computer core system. It is outfitted with a D-3 Duotronic primary core, and a D-2 Duotronic secondary core. The primary core is located in the centre of decks 3, 4, and 5 of the saucer section, with the smaller back up core in the centre aft of the secondary hull of decks eleven and twelve. The function of the secondary core has largely been relegated to simple information back up and storage. In an emergency, it can be reconfigured to operate the Kurtzman's primary systems in a limited capacity, including navigation, propulsion, weapons, shields and life support.</para>
      <para>Each computer core is monitored from a main Computer Room on Deck 4, maintained by at least two active technicians at any one time. Any requests from the library computer must be issued through the main Computer Room via an access terminal or through the issuance of recorder tapes. The only information terminals capable of accessing the library computer without passing through the computer room are those in the Captain’s Quarters, the main Conference Lounge, Main Engineering, Sickbay and the Bridge.</para>
      <para>The Kurtzman uses a new wholly integrated Advanced Biometric Retrieval And Management System (ABRAMS) for verbal and tactile computer input. It responds to simple verbal requests and can perform simple tasks, though it is incapable of extended factor calculation without a tactile command input. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Warp Propulsion Systems</title>
    <para>The Kurtzman utilizes a horizontally mounted Class-VI warp core comprising six parallel linked reaction chambers feeding the two nacelles. Ejection protocols are in place should the core ever breach and through the application of explosive bolting technology and hydraulic pistons. Ejection will occur within seven seconds. During a warp core breach, the core is ejected through a series of six service hatches directly aft from the Kurtzman's secondary hull. The warp core for the Kurtzman is rated at 636 cochranes with a max velocity of TOS-Warp-8.6 for 12 hours, a max sustainable velocity of TOS-Warp-8, and a cruising speed of TOS-Warp-7.5.</para>
    <para>NOTE: Comparison of TOS warp values and the more modern TNG-VOY warp values can be found at http://www.star-fleet.com/ed/warp-chart.html, the EDept Warpt Chart.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
    <para>The dual vent impulse drive is mounted directly aft of, and attached to, the saucer section. The impulse drive is designed to propel the ship up to 0.25c, with an acceleration rate from zero to 0.25c of 14 seconds, and a deceleration rate from 0.25c to zero in 32 seconds. An emergency impulse system is in place aboard the Kurtzman. In the event of saucer separation or primary fusion generator failure, a series of three micro-fusion reactors powering three adjustable vector exhaust vents mounted in the central neck of the secondary hull are revealed through a group of retracting hull plates. These are capable of propelling the ship at a theoretical maximum speed of .10c and the separated secondary hull at a speed of .15c. Slush deuterium fuel for the impulse and warp drives is stored in three self pressurizing and self sealing tanks, two primaries and one auxiliary. These tanks are located in Main Engineering on deck 12. Deuterium reserves stored aboard the Kurtzman are sufficient for a one month cruise. After 20 days, the ship must return to a Starbase for resupply and refueling. </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Tactical Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Defensive Shields</title>
      <para>The shielding systems of the Kurtzman consist of eight shield generators located at key points along the spaceframe. Each generator is comprised of nine 18MW graviton polarity sources feeding into a single 352 millicochrane subspace field distortion amplifier. During alert status, the shield generators combine to provide a continuous graviton load of 1344 MW with a maximum primary energy dissipation rate of 3.7 x 10^5kw. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Phaser Systems</title>
      <para>The Kurtzman is outfitted with the now standard combination of two separate long range and point defense phaser systems.</para>
      <para>Four Type VIII retractable phaser turrets containing two emitter cannons each are mounted in the fore mid section of the saucer section, two dorsal and two ventral. These turrets, when called into action, rise from their holding pad and are capable of swiveling in a 360 degree arc with 180 degrees of azimuth. These turrets are capable of engaging targets at any angle, though a small area around the shuttle bay immediately aft of the neck support is unprotected. These weapons have an effective maximum range of 100,000km, producing 2MW of power per burst. When fired, one cannon charges for eight tenths of a second before releasing an extended lance of energy followed almost immediately by the second, providing an almost overlapping appearance and allowing for multiple target blanket firing by a single turret. Fully charged phaser turret batteries are capable of producing continuous fire for up to twenty two minutes before the turret shuts down, allowing a nine minute cool down and recharge period. In this manner, it is unwise for any Starship Captain to engage all weapons simultaneously, instead staggering fire to allow single turrets to recover sufficiently without leaving the ship defenseless.</para>
      <para>The second phaser system is the Point defense Phaser System (PDPS), comprising twelve Type VII retractable point defense phaser turrets mounted in pairs of three in front of each primary phaser turret. Each turret operates using the same maneuvering principle as the primary phaser systems (raising itself one metre lower than the primary turrets behind it), but each contains four emitter cannons operating in concert at a much lower output setting.</para>
      <para>The purpose of this system is to saturate the immediate space around the vessel with high volume, relatively low intensity fire, intercepting torpedo/missile weapons prior to reaching their target or combating numbers of fighter craft which could otherwise prove too maneuverable for the primary systems to hit. Each PDPS turret, when fired, charges an emitter for one hundredth of a second before emitting a toroidal pulse of energy. With each emitter operating in a cyclic fire pattern, a single turret is able to output four hundred bursts per minute. Each turret, operating at only 0.6MW output, is capable of sustaining short range (10,000km) fire for up to nineteen minutes before requiring a six minute cool down and recharge period.</para>
      <para>The Type VIII phaser turrets are rated at a maximum energy output of 2MW with a maximum range of 100,000km. The PDPS Turrets are rated at a maximum energy output of 0.6MW with a maximum range of 10,000km. These two turret systems are provided supplementary power from four dedicated fusion reactors, two each located on Decks 3 and 7 respectively. As standard, all phaser system batteries are maintained fully charged whilst in standby. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Torpedo Systems</title>
      <para>Deck 9 is entirely occupied by the Torpedo firing systems. The Kurtzman utilizes two torpedo tubes, both located at the forward edge of the star drive. The loading system is semi automated and must be monitored by groups of highly trained technicians. The torpedo systems are controlled from the primary Torpedo Room located on a raised platform above the loading docks on Deck 9. The torpedo loading system draws torpedoes from a magazine storage bay in the rear of deck 9 through a series of hydraulic lifting cranes. The torpedo is drawn from the magazine into the loading area directly behind the torpedo tubes. It must then be manually maneuverd into the tube using a locking pin which releases it from the lifting rack. Once the inner torpedo hatch is closed, the torpedo is locked into the launching mechanism which is capable of tracking individually through the full 360-degrees, allowing targets outside the firing arc of the launchers to be engaged. </para>
      <para>The torpedo room is continually manned by at least four torpedo technicians who monitor the status of all torpedo systems and perform required daily maintenance, including replacing damaged loading runners, monitoring torsional stresses on each of the loading systems and the weekly launcher scrubbing that is required to maintain the system at peak efficiency. </para>
      <para>The Kurtzman carries a standard load of 150 photon torpedoes and 50 empty casings. Each torpedo tube has a designated load time of eleven seconds and a standard fire rate of five torpedoes per minute. The Kurtzman is the first vessel to employ the new Mark-III Photon Torpedo. This weapon has an effective range of 1,000,000 km. The warhead consists of six frozen slugs of 300 grams each of matter and antimatter in magnetic suspension. Typical detonations yield the equivalent of 154.6 megatons. However, due to minute variations in the amount of matter/antimatter particles which begin the annihilation reaction, detonation yield may vary by an average of ten percent. Forcefield attenuation of the blast yields a shaped charge effect, allowing the total destructive energy to be unleashed on a desired target.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Command and Support Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Bridge</title>
      <para>The Kurtzman’s bridge is similar in layout to that of Starship Class ships, in compliance with Starfleet's desire to introduce more uniformity to its critical systems layout.</para>
      <para>The Bridge is located on deck 1. The center of the bridge is occupied by a raised platform on which the Captain's chair is placed. To the left and right of the Captain's chair are the tactical and operations stations. Tactical and Operations consist of two standing stations which receive sensor feeds from their appropriate grids. Behind these stations are transparent tactile interface panels which are suspended from floor and ceiling. These panels are capable of projecting any desired readout or view necessary to that station's function.</para>
      <para>Behind these panels along the rear edge of the bridge walls are the engineering stations. Each station is designed to be manned by two officers. Along the top of the bulkhead is a continuous engineering plot for all major systems in a panoramic monitor and each station is capable of controlling primary and secondary systems.</para>
      <para>The primary turbolift access to the bridge is between the two engineering stations, bringing visitors onto the bridge directly aft of the Captain’s chair. To the right of the left hand station is a doorway leading through to the tactical planning chamber which is used for all mission planning and operational scenarios. To the left of the right hand station is the exit to the Jeffries tube access for the Bridge deck.</para>
      <para>To the right of the tactical planning room doorway is the main communications station. In layout this is identical to the engineering station, but providing communications specific information and utilizing the long range subspace relay systems.</para>
      <para>To the left of the Jeffries tube access doorway is the main science station, usually occupied by the ships First Officer and/or Chief Science Officer. As with the other rear wall stations, this is identical in layout but provides active and passive sensor information as well as internal sensor readouts and station specific information.</para>
      <para>Directly in front of the Captain's chair, in a lowered area, are the Helm and Navigation/Weapons station. This station comprises a single long panel separated by a computer control interface and plotting tablet in the centre. The helm officer sits to the left, the navigator/weapons officer to the right.</para>
      <para>At the extreme front of the bridge is the main viewscreen, raised above all over stations to provide unobstructed view to all bridge officers.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Auxiliary Control</title>
      <para>The Auxiliary Control Room is located on deck 4. It is continually manned and maintained by four junior officers. In the event of a ship-wide catastrophe, all the major ship's functions can be controlled from here. In layout it is similar to the main bridge but smaller and without the sunken area or transparent panels. In the star drive, Main Engineering serves as auxiliary control, with primary systems being routed through a control room located adjacent to the primary engineering platform. A small viewscreen operates in the same capacity as its larger cousin and this control room can be manned by as few as four people. This control room has customizable stations capable of controlling each of the ships primary functions, but in four person mode the default stations are Navigation/Tactical, Conn and Science. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Armory</title>
      <para>The Ship's Armory is located on Deck 8, directly above the Torpedo Room. The armory is stocked with a usual complement of 100 Type-II hand phasers, 100 Type-III phaser rifles, 75 sets of body armor, 120 Anastazine gas grenades, 120 concussion grenades, and 120 photon grenades. Access to the armory is highly restricted. Only the ship's CO, XO, Department Heads, and the Security staff have access to the armory, and this is granted only after a DNA palm print scan. The armory is laid out in racks, each labelled and catalogued. Inventory of armory and weapons lockers contents is taken at the beginning of each duty shift and compared to a master readout contained within a secure section of the main library database. The armory is continually manned by a pair of security officers. </para>
      <para>To protect against a hostile boarding of the ship, there are also several weapons lockers strategically placed in prominent areas of the ship. These areas include the Auxiliary Control, Bridge, Brig, Main Engineering, Transporter Rooms, the Shuttlebay, and the Torpedo Room. During normal operations, only the Command and Security staff (as stated for the armory) may gain access to the lockers. During yellow or red alert status, any ship's crew member may gain access via DNA thumb print verification. Each locker contains 12 Type-II hand phasers, two tricorders and twenty four spare power packs with an effective life of forty five maximum setting shots each. The combined arms of the weapons lockers and armory are sufficient to supply every crew member </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Brig</title>
      <para>Located on Deck 10, the Brig is comprised of five cells, a common watch area and COS' office. The watch area is nothing more than a duty station in which a security officer can stand watch over the prisoners. Each cell is equipped with a small drum dispenser for the secure transfer of items and food to and from the cell. The drum has an opening on only one section of its curved surface, and is made out of a 1cm thick sheet of duranium alloy, which in turn is mounted to a framework of solid duranium that extends 25.0cm within the bulkhead of the wall. Once an object is placed with in the drum, it is rotated so that its opened section faces into the cell. For reasons of security, the controls for the drum dispenser are placed on the watch duty station and not within the detention cell itself. This is to prevent a prisoner from escaping his cell by using the drum dispenser to gain access to his cell controls. There is a single protein resequencer mounted near the watch duty station and is totally inaccessible to cell occupants.</para>
      <para>The protein resequencer is capable of transforming bulk protein into a variety of simple chain food stuffs such as ice cream, meats and potatoes. The cells themselves utilize a series of two recessed forcefield generators which deliver a painful, but relatively harmless shock to anyone who touches the field whilst active. When activated, the generators slide into place and glow with a soft yellow light. This allows the watch officer to continually monitor the cells occupants without allowing an opportunity to escape. </para>
      <para>Also housed in the Brig is the ship's vault. The vault is a secured storage compartment which can be used to safely store information and evidence in criminal investigations, sensitive mission specific material, information that cannot be stored in the ship's cargo bay or computers, currency, or personal items for the crew and passengers. The vault is separated into a safe and 100 locked boxes. Either the safe or the boxes can be individually preset to its own lock combination and climate controls. Access to the vault is granted only by senior officer identification. This identification is verified by voice print, optical retina scan, and palm print. All three must be successful for the senior officer to gain access to the vault. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Main Engineering</title>
      <para>Main Engineering is located near the centre of the secondary hull on Decks 11 and 12. At either end of the compartment is a single three man turbolift which only operates within Main Engineering. The warp core lays horizontally along the floor of Deck 12, fore to aft, separated from the main engineering bay by a series of walkways, plasma transfer pipes and water exchange junctions.</para>
      <para>Occupying the entire rear half of these two decks, Main Engineering is the second biggest single area on the ship. Plasma transfer conduits, optical data conduits, water transfer pipes and deuterium exchange lines occupy the majority of the floor space, requiring work terminals and the bulk of all engineering functions to be raised on walkways, crawlspaces and platforms. The two primary and one auxiliary deuterium storage tanks are mounted along the starboard wall behind the warp core. The antimatter storage tanks are similarly mounted along the port wall.</para>
      <para>The Chief Engineer's station and primary monitoring systems for engineering are located on a raised level platform at the centre of the deck. The engineering platform contains stations for monitoring all primary and secondary systems as well as the warp core status monitor. The Chief Engineer's station contains a bank of five screens mounted on the plasma conduits that feed them, providing customizable readouts for any of the ships systems as well as a computer access terminal and a diagnostics panel.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Utility Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Cargo Bays</title>
      <para>The main cargo bays are located in the lower aft section of the secondary hull, above the shuttlebay and behind the main deflector dish. There are four cargo holds in total. Each cargo bay is equipped with two entrances, one opening towards outer space for offloading via work bee, shuttlecraft, or space dock. The second entrance is a dual access airlock opening into the ship's corridor. The airlock acts as a buffer between the cargo hold and the rest of the ship. Each cargo hold is compartmentalized, and can be configured to provide a H, K, L, M, N, or N(2) environment for the safe storage of perishable cargo or to house life forms that exist in terrestrial environments other than Class-M. This design gives the ship the capability of storing perishable cargo or housing life forms in their proper environment. A further three cargo areas are located on decks 3 and 4 of the saucer section, with the same outward facing loading airlock and the inner double airlock. The saucer section cargo bays are used for storing spare parts for the impulse systems and emergency damage control equipment for the saucer section.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tractor Beam Systems</title>
      <para>There are two tractor beam projectors located fore and aft, the fore emitter is located across the neck of the saucer section, the aft emitter at the rear of the star drive. Effective range of the tractor beams is 22,500km, depending on local relativistic and delta-v conditions. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Transporter Systems</title>
      <para>There are a total of 4 transporters designed into the Kurtzman's deck plan. There are two standard six pad transporters, one on deck 2 directly beneath the main bridge and one on deck 10 in the star drive. In addition, there are two ten pad emergency transporters. One is located within the saucer section on deck 3, and the other is positioned within the secondary hull on deck 7. Ranges of the standard transporters are 30,000km, while that of the emergency and cargo transporters are only 11,250km respectively. The transport sequence aboard the Kurtzman takes 6 seconds to complete. The emergency transporters, by design, are outbound transport only because of the inability to target that many individual comm signals at a single time. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Turbolift Systems</title>
      <para>There are 7 operational turbolifts. Turbolift-1 is located in the centre of the Saucer Section and has access from Deck-1 of the Saucer all the way to Deck-15 of the Secondary Hull. Turbolift-2 is also located in the centre of the Saucer, parallel with Turbolift-1, and has access from Deck-2 of the Saucer through Deck-12 of the Secondary Hull. Turbolifts-3 and 4 have access from Deck-3 through Deck-6 of the Saucer Section, and are located port and starboard respectively. Turbolifts-5 and 6 are located port and starboard of the centre of the secondary hull and traverse from deck-9 to deck-12. Turbolift-7 is a cargo turbolift. It is located in the aft section of the Saucer and has access from Deck-3 through Deck-12 of the Secondary Hull, and can traverse to each of the three main Cargo Holds as well as each of the secondary cargo bays located in the saucer section. Each of the turbolifts is capable of traversing horizontally as it approaches the secondary hull. The horizontal shafts attached to each deck allow a turbolift to grant access to every deck without the need to use more than a single lift. With the exception of turbolift one, which is dedicated solely to servicing the Bridge, every other turbolift operates on computer controlled schedules that allow them to operate without a collision. This can occasionally lead to delay times whilst one lift waits for another to clear a shaft. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Crew Support Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Crew Quarters</title>
      <para>Enlisted Crewmen and Junior Officers are billeted in pairs, each sharing a small common lounge area and bathing facilities with separate bunk areas. The lounge is equipped with a dining booth module and a work station that can double as an entertainment centre. The bathroom is equipped with a sink, toilet, and shower. The crewmen each receive a bunk within their own separate area. This area consists of a small closet, single bunk style bed and a small chest of drawers. Senior Officers fare slightly better in that they do not have to share their living space. Despite this, their stateroom, sleeping arrangement, and bathing facilities are of the same design as the other Junior Officers. The Captain, Executive Officer, and visiting VIPs fare much better. Each has a dining module roughly 25% larger then the junior officers, a bathroom with a whirlpool bath, shower, and a bedroom large enough for a walk-in closet, a full sized bed, and a large work/entertainment station. Only the Captain, Executive Officer, and V.I.P. quarters are outfitted with food dispensers similar to the ones found in either of the crew lounges. The Captain's quarters include a computer access terminal. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Crew Recreational Facilities</title>
      <para>There are two crew lounges - one located in the forward most part of the saucer section on Deck 5 and one just forward of Main Engineering on Deck 10. Each lounge is capable of seating one hundred people at any given time in some good comfort. Under usual conditions, there is a movie shown on the large display screen twice a week for the crew's enjoyment in each lounge, although programming is subject to Captains discretion. Also located in the Lounge is a well stocked and fully equipped games locker. The default game supplies include a wide range of portable table top games for the crew to use at their leisure. The locker may be stocked with such games as Three Dimensional Chess, Battleships, Kal-toh, Three Dimensional Scrabble, Monopoly: the Federation Edition, and several decks of cards in varying cultural styles. </para>
      <para> There is a private mess for receiving VIPs and hosting senior officers located on deck 2, though its use is largely dependent upon the Captain of the day. This dining area has a separate galley preparation area and an entertainment screen suitable for displaying broadcasts of many types. The private dining area is capable of seating fifteen comfortably and is generally staffed by the Captain’s personal steward, two under-stewards and two sous chefs. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Gymnasium</title>
      <para>There is a large gymnasium located on the lower aft section of Deck 6. It is equipped with a sparring ring for boxing/wrestling/fencing or other forms of hand to hand combat and cardiovascular and weights machinery to keep the crew in peak physical condition. Should the situation arise, the Gymnasium's equipment can be easily stored, thus opening up the room's area to be used as an auditorium or act as an auxiliary storage room or stage area for theatre performances. At any given time, the gymnasium can comfortably contain forty people, though in theatre configuration it can easily handle eighty, the standard off duty complement at any given time. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Galley</title>
      <para>Located near the centre of deck 4 is the ship's galley. Although capable of reproducing a variety of food selections, the Kurtzman Class is equipped with both a food synthesizer system, and a fully functioning Galley. Food stuffs for the Galley are stored in three separate fully compartmentalized pantries, each compartment equipped with their own stasis field generators to preserve freshness. This provides something of an alternative to the standard cubed nutritional supplements offered by the food synthesizer system. </para>
      <para>The food synthesizer system is comprised of a matter re-sequencer system connected to the waste reclamation system. The matter re-sequencer recycles biological waste materials into simple protein and sucrose compounds in taste similar to meat/ dairy/ vegetable by-products such as ground beef, fish or poultry, cheeses, fruit juices and preserves but in appearance simple multicolored cubes. Although highly efficient, the re-sequencer is incapable of creating food stuffs with a complex layered formation as found in a turkey leg (with fat, bone and skin attached to the meat), or the fibrous consistency of fresh fruits and vegetables. </para>
      <para>Galley prepared or processed synthesized food stuffs are distributed via a computer controlled network of food dispensers. Any materials left over from the meal such as the dinner ware, or undigested food stuffs placed back into the dispenser are automatically recycled into the waste reclamation system. Each dispenser consists of a closed circuit micro transporter mounted as an enclosed wall unit in specified areas through out the ship. These areas include: the Brig, the crew lounge, the Captains, XO's, and VIP's quarters, Main Engineering, Sickbay, and the Shuttlebay. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Medical Facilities</title>
      <para>The ship's Sickbay is located on deck 5, next to the primary computer core in the centre of the saucer section, and is the most highly protected section of the ship. Sickbay comprises two examination rooms separated by a surgical room, which in turn is also bordered by a recovery room. Each area is separated by bulkhead walls with a common entrance leading from each to the main reception area. The reception area is outfitted with a nurse's station. The nurse's station contains a bank of monitors and panels along the rear wall which provide patient information readouts as well as recall databases for medical files. This station is separated from the reception area by a half moon desk at which the supervising nurses work and greet new arrivals.</para>
      <para>Each examination room is outfitted with nine biobeds. The surgical room is outfitted with two biobeds, which are in turn modified specifically for delicate surgical procedures. The recovery room is outfitted with twelve bio beds that are designed more for a patient's comfort and recovery. In addition, there is an emergency aid station located on every deck near the turbolift entrance. Each aid station is nothing more then an equipment locker housing three gurneys, and two fully stocked emergency first aid kits.</para>
      <para>The Chief Medical Officer's office is located between the two main examination rooms. It consists of a small laboratory setup for testing as well as a chemical synthesizer unit capable of producing almost any form of base chemical compound with a ready library of almost all current medicinal products available throughout the Federation. The CMO also has a desk with communications panel, computer access terminal and a series of screens across the wall above it which provides visual feeds to the examination and recovery rooms.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Auxiliary Spacecraft Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Shuttlebay</title>
      <para>The shuttlecraft bay is located aft of the secondary hull and occupies the entirety of decks 13, 14 and 15. Despite being an almost entirely open space, these three decks are broken into a number of distinct levels.</para>
      <para>The upper level contains spare parts storage for all shuttle maintenance in four suspended warehouses. Each warehouse contains a series of crane units that can retrieve any stored part after a request is input into the terminal outside each warehouse. Any large or unmanageable parts can be moved directly to shuttle storage bays by the crane units. This area is separated from the one below it by a large walkway grille and access is granted by an open personnel lift from the landing bay level only.</para>
      <para>This walkway also grants access to the main Shuttlebay control room, which is suspended between the warehouses at the rear of the shuttlebay. The control room is lined with portal windows facing forwards, providing a panoramic view of the entire shuttlebay and launch doors. Within the control room, a bank of five command and control stations is used to manage both air and crane traffic. These are permanently manned by senior technicians and are overseen by the Flight Control Officer who reports directly to the First Officer.</para>
      <para>The second level is broken into two sections. Pylon platforms are constructed along the sides of the shuttlebay to store shuttles when not actively flying. Access to these is granted by a series of dedicated walkways and open air personnel lifts along the inner hull. The centre of the space is taken up by the landing and launch lanes. Each bay contains a work maintenance area to facilitate external maintenance of removable parts. When launching, shuttles are used in rotation, the lower platforms rolling into launch position on the runway. In the case of upper platforms, the entire storage platform is lowered to the open platform beneath it and rolled into position in the same manner via antigravity cranes.</para>
      <para>When landing, the shuttle comes to rest on an open platform at the end of the runway and is rolled back into an open position either on the lower or upper storage deck.</para>
      <para>The shuttlebay launch doors occupy the entire rear hull plates of the star drive and comprise two separate units. The outer shuttlebay doors (the outer hull section) are withdrawn upwards into a dedicated space between the primary and secondary hulls. The segmented inner doors then retract horizontally, withdrawing along the back wall of the shuttlebay. Atmospheric shields engage when the inner doors are withdrawn, allowing environmental integrity to be maintained.</para>
      <para>The shuttlebay is capable of launching two shuttlecraft at a time, but can not accept landings whilst launches are in progress. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Technical Specifications</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Dimensions and Structure</title>    
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Length</term>
        <listitem><para>345 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Beam (Width)</term>
        <listitem><para>100 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Height</term>
        <listitem><para>172 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Decks</term>
        <listitem><para>15</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Crew Complement</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Officers and Crew</term>
        <listitem><para>495</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Evacuation Limit</term>
        <listitem><para>1800</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>      
    <variablelist>
      <title>Computer Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Core</term>
        <listitem><para>1 D3 Duotronic Core</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>1 D2 Duotronic Core</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Operating System</term>
        <listitem><para>Advanced Biometric Retrieval And Management System (ABRAMS)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>User Interface</term>
        <listitem><para>Advanced Biometric Retrieval And Management System (ABRAMS)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>        
    <variablelist>
      <title>Warp Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Power Plant</term>
        <listitem><para>One 636 cochrane M/ARA cores feeding two nacelles</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Crusing Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>TOS-Warp 7.5</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Sustainable Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>TOS-Warp 8</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>TOS-Warp 8.6 (12 hours)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Impulse Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Full Impulse</term>
        <listitem><para>0.25c</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Accellerate</term>
        <listitem><para>14 seconds</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Decellerate</term>
        <listitem><para>32 seconds</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Defensive Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)</term>
        <listitem><para>1344 MegaWatts</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate</term>
        <listitem><para>3.7x10^5 kilowatts</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Offensive Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Torpedoes</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Torpedo Tubes</term>
              <listitem><para>4</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Standard Payload (total)</term>
              <listitem><para>150 photon torpedoes</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>50 unequipped casings</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Phasers</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>4 Type-VIII Retractable Phaser Turrets</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>12 Type-VII Point Defense Retractable Phaser Turrets</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Deck Layout</title>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 1</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Bridge</member>
        <member>Conference Room A</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 2</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>CO's Quarters</member>
        <member>XO's Quarters</member>
        <member>VIP Quarters</member>
        <member>Transporter Room 1</member>
        <member>Private Mess</member>
        <member>Primary Phaser Turret Stowage</member>
        <member>Point Defense Phaser System Turret Stowage</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 3</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Conference Room B</member>
        <member>Emergency Transporter Room #1</member>
        <member>Food Locker #1-3</member>
        <member>Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Level-1</member>
        <member>Shield Emitters #1-2</member>
        <member>Fusion Reactors, Upper Phaser Systems</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 4</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxiliary Control</member>
        <member>Auxiliary Life Support</member>
        <member>Auxiliary Power</member>
        <member>Galley</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Level-2</member>
        <member>Computer Room</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 5</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxiliary Control</member>
        <member>Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Docking Airlock #1-2 (Port and Starboard)</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Level-3</member>
        <member>Primary Transporter Rooms #1-2 (port and starboard)</member>
        <member>Sickbay</member>
        <member>Crew Lounge</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 6</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxiliary Cargo Holds 1-2</member>
        <member>Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Deuterium Storage Tanks A and B (port and starboard)</member>
        <member>Impulse Drive (aft)</member>
        <member>Tractor Beam Emitter</member>
        <member>Gymnasium</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 7</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Emergency Transporter #2</member>
        <member>Turbolift Main Shafts Access</member>
        <member>Damage Control Equipment Storage</member>
        <member>Secondary Conference Room</member>
        <member>Fusion Reactors, Lower Phaser Systems</member>
        <member>Shield Emitters #3-4</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 8</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Brig</member>
        <member>Armory</member>
        <member>Phaser Control Room</member>
        <member>Primary Phaser Turret Stowage</member>
        <member>Point Defense Phaser System Turret Stowage</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 9</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Torpedo Rooms</member>
        <member>Torpedo Bay</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 10</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Main Engineering</member>
        <member>Engineering Workshop</member>
        <member>Tool Storage Rooms</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 11</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Cargo Transporter #1-2</member>
        <member>Main Deflector Dish</member>
        <member>Main Engineering Level-2</member>
        <member>Primary Cargo Hold #1-2</member>
        <member>Auxiliary Computer Core Level 1</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 12</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxiliary Computer Core Level 2</member>
        <member>Cargo Transporter #3</member>
        <member>Deuterium Storage Tank-C</member>
        <member>Main Engineering Level-3</member>
        <member>Primary Cargo Hold #3 </member>
        <member>Shield Emitters #5-6</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 13</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Shuttlebay Upper Level</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay Control Room</member>
        <member>Spare Parts Storage</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 14</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Shuttlebay Launch Level</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay Loading and Unloading</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay Engine Testing Facility</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 15</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Shuttlebay Lower Level</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay Maintenance and Storage Hangars</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay Maneuvering and Control Assemblies</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay Workshop and Fabrication Plant</member>
        <member>Shield Emitters #7-8</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Ships of the Class</title>
    <simplelist role="ShipList">
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Kurtzman</productname>
        <productnumber>1785</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Abrams</productname>
        <productnumber>1786</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Orci</productname>
        <productnumber>1787</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Baranoff</productname>
        <productnumber>1788</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Burk</productname>
        <productnumber>1789</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Chernov</productname>
        <productnumber>1790</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Lindelof</productname>
        <productnumber>1791</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Witz</productname>
        <productnumber>1792</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Giacchioni</productname>
        <productnumber>1793</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Mindel</productname>
        <productnumber>1794</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Brandon</productname>
        <productnumber>1795</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Markey</productname>
        <productnumber>1796</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Weisberg</productname>
        <productnumber>1797</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Chambliss</productname>
        <productnumber>1798</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Cunningham</productname>
        <productnumber>1799</productnumber>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <para>With the arrival and deployment of the Kurtzman Class Battlecruisers, it is the hope of Starfleet Command that no repeat of the Nero incident ever take place again. Should there be such a danger, it is deemed essential that ships designed specifically for the pursuit of warfare as mobile weapons platforms be available for rapid deployment as the vanguard of an offensive fleet.</para>
  </section>
</article>
