<article class="specification" id="mariner">
  <title>Mariner-class</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup role="Maintainer">
      <author>
        <firstname>EDept</firstname>
        <surname>Staff</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Primary Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Bret</firstname>
        <surname>Godfrey</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Original Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Bret</firstname>
        <surname>Godfrey</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword role="service">NPC</keyword>
      <keyword role="category">Cruiser (Movie Era)</keyword>
      <keyword role="variant">Medium</keyword>
      <keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>13 June 2002</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Assistant Engineering Director Bradley Joy and Steve Johnson</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>History and Mission Overview</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>Hamlet, Act-III, Scene-I</attribution>
      <para>"To be, or not to be: that is the question."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <para>As the Federation entered a new, yet tentative age of peace with the Klingons in the years that followed the Khitomer Accord, Star Fleet began to reassess the condition, inventory, and mission profile of its fleet.  Before that time, older designs such had been relegated to boarder patrol and training duties while newer, more capable designs slowly took over the role of deep space exploration.  As promised in the Khitomer Accord, Star Fleet began demilitarizing and dismantling the outpost network along the Klingon Neutral Zone, while at the same time reducing the size of its combat fleet.  Thus many ships of the old guard literally found themselves decommissioned over night.  Ironically, this practice created an even greater need for new ship construction.</para>
    <para>In 2295, Star Fleet Command initiated a directive for the construction of a new medium exploration cruiser design.  Several contractors were invited to participate in a bidding contest for the new class designation. A combination of speed, space frame durability, tactical effectiveness, and space exploration sciences were to be incorporated into the over all design. In the end it was the Salazaar Shipyards of Andoria that won the contract with their prototype, the USS Mariner.  After successful completion of the Mariner's shake down cruise, Star Fleet placed an order for a further 50 ships of the same class.  Though it was specifically designed as an exploration vessel, its mix of maneuverability, firepower, and Rodinium armor platting proved that the ship was a valuable tactical asset.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Structure and Construction</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>Henry IV, Part-2, Act-III, Scene-I</attribution>
      <para>"To the wet sea-boy in an hour so rude:  With all appliances and means to boot."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <para>In appearance, the Mariner is of a standard configuration.  The saucer section is attached to the secondary hull via a front dorsal neck mounting, while the twin warp nacelles are fitted to the aft section of the secondary hull via upward turned pylons.</para>
    <para>The majority of the Mariner's space frame is made up of pure titanium with three separate framed hull layers. Once the pluming and electrical systems were in place and covered by hull plating, titanium fiber enriched duroplast foam was pressure injected into the spaces between the hull layers for insulation and radiation shielding. The outer most hull has an additional 4.5 cm layer of homogeneously rolled rodinium armor plating. Rodinium, the hardest known substance in Federation Science, was until that time primarily used for shielding on static structures such as an orbital Outpost or Starbase.  Though its heavy mass prevents it from use in Starship structural components, it works well as a hull layer armoring against physical penetration or focused energy attacks. Upon completion, a nonreflecting thermo coat of battleship-grey was electro-magnetically bonded to the rodinium hull, giving the ship a dull finish.  On average, the over all hull thickness of a completed space frame is 30.0cm.</para>
    <para>During an extreme emergency, the saucer section was designed to be jettisoned from the secondary hull and act as a large life boat for the crew.  In such an occurrence, the impulse motor on the aft of the saucer section would act as the main propulsion drive and power generating plant.  Explosive bolts placed strategically along stress points with in the neck mount physically sever the saucer section from the secondary hull.  Once separated, the saucer can not be reattached to the secondary hull with out the services of a dry dock repair facility.  Maximum impulse speed of the Saucer section with the secondary hull jettisoned is 0.15 c.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>Hamlet, Act-V, Scene-1</attribution>
      <para>"Alas, poor Yorick, I knew him well!  A fellow of infinite jest, of most excellent fancy..."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <para>Along the hull of the ship are located a total of 135 sensors used for navigational, remote sensing, scientific, and tactical acquisition data collection. The sensory suite is designed for both active and passive data collection. In normal space flight operations, both methods are automatically employed simultaneously, though they can be reconfigured as active or passive only. Active sensory grids are echo collection devices that transmit a pulse signal, usually radio, optical, infrared, or subspace, and then interpret the rebounded signal in forms of cohesive data.  Passive sensory grids "listen" for physical and subspace signals that are given off by either a natural or artificial object.</para>
    <para>The sensory equipment installed on the Mariner Class has a high resolution range of approximately 2.5 light years, and 8.5 light years in low resolution.  Both figures are highly dependant on the current spatial conditions that the ship is experiencing. If the situation arises, the sensor grid can be used as an ECM device, effectively jamming most types of radio and subspace communications and navigational frequencies with decreasing effectiveness to a distance of 500,000km, depending on local relativistic conditions, though this will also render the ship's own subspace, and radio communication and navigational frequencies inoperable.</para>
    <para>In addition, the Mariner has on hand a usual complement of 25 pre-dedicated scientific probes, and another 25 empty torpedo casings ready for scientific or tactical augmentation.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Computer Systems</title>
      <para>The Mariner is designed and built with a dual computer core system.  It is outfitted with an M-6 Duotronic primary core, and an M-2 Duotronic secondary core.  The primary core is located in the center of decks 3, 4, and 5 of the saucer section, with the smaller back up core in the center aft of the secondary hull in deck-12.  The function of the secondary core has largely been relocated to simple information back up storage.  In an emergency, it can be reconfigured to operate most of the Mariner's primary systems such as navigation, propulsion, weapons, and life support, though on a limited capacity.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Warp Propulsion Systems</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>The Tempest, Epilogue</attribution>
      <para>"Gentle breath of yours my sails must fill, or else my project fails."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <para>The Mariner utilizes a Class-VII warp core. It is similar to, but 25% smaller then the core designed for the Excelsior Class. To save space, the core is mounted horizontally along the centerline of the ship's Z-axis running for to aft with in the secondary hull.  The ejection protocols happen with in a 3 second time interval because of the sequences of explosive separation and ejection.  During a warp core breach, the core is ejected through a service hatch directly aft from the Mariner's secondary hull.  The warp core for the Mariner is rated at 900 cochranes with a max velocity of TOS-Warp-9.6 for 12 hours, a max sustainable velocity of TOS-Warp-8.5, and a cruising speed of TOS-Warp-5.5.</para>
    <para><![CDATA[NOTE: Comparison of TOS (OME) warp values and the more modern TNG-VOY warp values can be found at:http://www.star-fleet.com/ed/Warp-chart.htm]]></para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>Richard III, Act-V, Scene-IV</attribution>
      <para>"A horse!  A horse!  My kingdom for a horse!"</para>
    </epigraph>
    <para>The dual vent impulse drive is mounted directly aft of, and attached to the saucer section.  The impulse drive is designed to propel the ship up to and including 0.25c, with an acceleration rate from zero to 0.25c of 29 seconds, and a deceleration rate from 0.25c to zero in 57 seconds.</para>
    <para>Slush deuterium fuel for the impulse drive is stored in three self pressurizing and stabilizing, two primary tanks and one auxiliary.  The two primary tanks are located on apposing sides of the Impulse Motor, Deck-6 of the Saucer Section.  The auxiliary deuterium tank is located in the center portion of Deck-12 in the Secondary Hull.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Tactical Systems</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>Hamlet, Act-III, Scene-I</attribution>
      <para>"Whether 'tis nobler in the mind to suffer the slings and arrows of outrageous fortune or to take arms against a sea of troubles..."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <section>
      <title>Defensive Shields</title>
      <para>The shielding system of the Mariner consists of eight shield generators located at key points along the space frame.  Each generator is comprised of nine 18MW graviton polarity sources feeding into a single 352 milliconchrane subspace field distortion amplifier. During alert status, the shield generators can combine to provide a continuous gravitation load of 2016 MW with a maximum primary energy dissipation rate of 2.0 x 10^5.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Phaser Systems</title>
      <para>The Mariner is outfitted with a mix of two separate phaser systems.  Being the primary phaser system, the Type-VIII's are typically mounted in the forward position with Type-VII's covering the broadsides and aft.  Both systems are designed to have independent firing control.  Regardless of Type, each phaser bank is equipped with its own fusion power pack which can be operated separate from the rest of the ship's systems, or they can draw their energy directly from the warp core via the main power couplings.  Each fusion power pack has a recharge rate of two hours, and can operate a phaser bank at full beam intensity for no longer then 15 seconds between recharging cycles.</para>
      <para>The Mariner has a total of six Type-VIII phaser emitters mounted in three separate banks of two.  Each bank covers a firing arc of 60 degrees azimuth and elevation.  One bank is located in the lower forward section of the saucer covering the forward arc while the second and third banks are on the upper saucer section covering the forward-port and forward-starboard arcs respectively.  Each of the Type-VIII emitters are rated for a maximum energy output of 2.6 MW at a range of 150,000 km.</para>
      <para>The Type-VII phaser emitters are also mounted in three separate banks of two, with a similar arc of 60 degrees azimuth and elevation coverage.  The first two banks are mounted on the underside of the saucer section, one facing port, and the second facing to starboard.  The third bank is mounted in the very aft section of the secondary hull just above the shuttlebay covering the aft firing arc.  Each of the Type-VII emitters are rated for a maximum energy output of 1.3 MW at a range of 75,000 km.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Torpedo Systems</title>
      <para>The Mariner mounts a triple photon torpedo launcher system which takes up the entire space of Deck-8 inside the dorsal neck mount.  Two launchers are situated facing directly forward, while a third launcher is mounted to fire directly aft.  All three launchers are mounted in such a way as to allow independent launching of torpedoes.</para>
      <para>Because of developmental problems with a newer automatic photon torpedo loading system, it was decided to outfit the Mariner with the standard manually operated loading system.  This reduced the firing rate of the torpedoes, but greatly increased the accuracy of the launch along with a reduced probability of a torpedo misfire.  All three launchers are controlled from a single fire control room known as the "Torpedo Room", located on Deck-7 inside the dorsal neck mount.  The Torpedo Room is separated into two sections.  The first section handles the firing control and targeting of the photon torpedoes, while the second section is a maintenance area where the torpedoes can be maintained or reconfigured.  Also located on Deck-7 is the Torpedo Bunker, which is the main storage area for the usual complement of the 150 photon torpedoes, 25 scientific probes, and 25 empty torpedo casings.</para>
      <para>Each of the three torpedo launchers has a designed rate of fire of 8 torpedoes per minute with an effective range of 2,630,000 km.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Command and Support Systems</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>Henry V, Act-III, Scene-I</attribution>
      <para>"I see you stand like greyhounds in the slips, straining upon the start.  The game's afoot!   Follow your spirit...."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <section>
      <title>Bridge</title>
      <para>The Bridge is of a similar layout to that of the Excelsior Class Heavy Cruiser, though 25% smaller.  At center is the Captain's chair, with the Helmsman and Navigator's seats directly in front.  Although there is no designated seat for the Executive Officer, it is usually assumed the Exec is manning one of the auxiliary duty stations located through out the Bridge.  The Bridge is located at the center of Deck-1</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Auxiliary Control </title>
      <para>The Auxiliary Control Room is located in the center of Deck-4 of the saucer section.  It is continually manned and maintained.  In the event of a ship wide catastrophe, all the major ship's functions and navigation can be controlled from here.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Armory</title>
      <para>The Ship's Armory is located adjacent to the Brig on Deck-14.  The Armory is stocked with a usual complement of 50 Type-I hand phasers, 100 Type-II hand phasers, 100 Type-III phaser rifles, 75 sets of body armor, 120 Anastazine gas grenades, 120 concussion grenades, and 120 photon grenades.   Access to the Armory is highly restricted to that of the ship's CO, XO, all the Department Heads, and the Security staff, and is granted only after a DNA palm print scan.</para>
      <para>To protect against a hostile boarding of the ship, there are also several weapons lockers strategically placed in prominent areas of the ship.  These areas include the Auxiliary Control, Bridge, Brig, Main Engineering, all the Transporter Rooms, the Shuttlebay, and the Torpedo Room.  During normal operations, only the Command and Security staff (as stated for the Armory) may gain access to the lockers.  During yellow or red alert status, any ship's crewmember may gain access via DNA thumb print verification.  Each locker contains 12 Type-II hand phasers.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Brig</title>
      <para>Located on Deck-14, the Brig is comprised of five cells, a common "watch" area and COS's office. The "watch" area is nothing more then a duty station in which a security officer can stand watch over the prisoners. Each cell is equipped with a small "drum" dispenser for the secure transfer of items and food both to and from the cell.  The drum has an opening on only one section of its curved surface, and is made out of 0.5cm solid titanium, which in turn is mounted to a framework of solid titanium that extends 25.0cm with in the bulkhead of the wall.  Once an object is placed with in the drum, the drum is rotated so that its opened section "faces" the opposite side of the wall.  For reasons of security, the controls for the drum dispenser are placed on the "watch" duty station and not with in the detention cell itself.  This is to prevent a prisoner from escaping his cell by using the drum dispenser to gain access to his cell controls.  There is a single food dispenser mounted near the "watch" duty station and is totally inaccessible to cell occupants.</para>
      <para>Also housed in the Brig is the ship's vault. The vault is a secured storage compartment which can be used to safely store information and evidence in a criminal investigation, sensitive mission specific material or information that can not be stored in the ship's cargo bay or the ship's computers, currency, or personal items for the crew and passengers. The vault is separated into a safe, and 100 locked boxes. Either the safe or the boxes can be individually preset to its own lock combination and climate controls. Access to the vault is granted only by senior officer identification. This identification is verified by voice print, optical retina scan, and palm print. All three must be successful for the senior officer to gain access to the vault. The Brig is located on Deck-14.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Chartroom</title>
      <para>The ship's Chart Room is located aft of the Main Bridge on Deck-1. The Chart Room is comprised of three main viewing displays and fifteen smaller ones, each with their own console. The Chart Room is basically an interactive library in which astrophysical data is prioritized, catalogued, and studied for scientific, navigational, or tactical needs.  Although this room is designed as a navigational aid, its primary use is for the scientific study of interstellar objects.  In times of war, the Chart Room can be easily reconfigured as a War Room in the event that a ranking fleet officer should wish to use the ship as his flag ship during strategic operations.  Using the various monitors at his disposal, a flotilla commander can keep track of the ebb and flow of battle from different perspectives, giving him an important aid in dictating the tactics of his overall command.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Main Engineering</title>
      <para>Main Engineering is located near the center of the secondary hull on Decks-10-11-12.  On either end of the compartment is a single three man turbolift which only operates with in Main Engineering itself.  The warp core lays horizontal along the floor of Deck-12 and runs from fore to aft.  The Chief Engineer's office is located on the forward end of the Engineering compartment on Deck-10 and is situated so that the Chief Engineer can oversee the operations of his department.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Utility Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Cargo Bays</title>
      <para>The main cargo bays are located in the lower aft section of the Secondary Hull between the shuttlebays, and the main deflector dish. There are four cargo holds in total. Each cargo bay is equipped with two entrances, one opening towards outer space for offloading via work bee, shuttlecraft, or space dock.  The second entrance is a duel access airlock opening into the ship's corridor.  The airlock acts as a buffer between the cargo hold and the rest of the ship.  Each cargo hold is compartmentalized, and can be configured to provide either a H, K, L, M, N, or N(2) environment for the safe storage of perishable cargo or to house life forms that exist in other terrestrial environments other then Class-M. This design gives the ship the capability of storing perishable cargo or housing life forms in their proper environment.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tractor Beam Systems</title>
      <para>There are four tractor beam projectors located on the four outer corners of the space frame. Though they are meant for towing, they can be easily reconfigured as a repulser beam. In addition; the two aft tractor beams are designed to be able to tractor a damaged or escaping shuttle craft into the safety of the shuttlebay. All four tractor beam emitters are rigged so that an object can be "walked" into the desired position. For example: If a shuttlecraft is located foreword of the ship, the crewman manning OPS can lock onto the shuttle craft, and bring it far enough aft so that the aft tractor beams can haul it into the shuttlebay. Effective range of the tractor beams is 22,500km, depending on local relativistic conditions.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Transporter Systems</title>
      <para>There are a total of 7 transporters designed into the Mariner's deck plan. There are two standard six pad transporters, one port and one starboard in the saucer section.  In addition, there are two ten pad emergency transporters. One is located near sickbay in the saucer section, and the other is positioned with in the secondary hull. There are three cargo transporters, one in each of the primary cargo holds.  Ranges of the standard transporters are 30,000km, while that of the emergency and cargo transporters are only 11,250km respectively.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Turbolift Systems</title>
      <para>There are 7 operational turbolifts.  Turbolift-1 is located in the center of the Saucer Section and has access from Deck-1 of the Saucer all the way to Deck-13 of the Secondary Hull.  Turbolift-2 is also located in the center of the Saucer, parallel with Turbolift-1, and has access from Deck-2 of the Saucer through Deck-14 of the Secondary Hull.  Turbolifts-3 and 4 have access from Deck-3 through Deck-6 of the Saucer Section, and are located port and starboard respectively.  Turbolifts-5 and 6 are located port and starboard of the center of the secondary hull and traverse from deck-9 to deck-13.  Turbolift-7 is a cargo turbolift.  It is located in the aft section of the Saucer and has access from Deck-3 through Deck-13 of the Secondary Hull, and can traverse to each of the three main Cargo Holds.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Crew Support Systems</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>Hamlet, Act-II, Scene-II</attribution>
      <para>"Oh God, I could be bounded in a nut-shell, and count myself a king of infinite space..."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <section>
      <title>Crew Quarters</title>
      <para>Enlisted, NE, and Junior Officers are billeted in pairs, each sharing a small common lounge area and bathing facilities. The lounge is equipped with a dining booth module, and a work station that can double as an entertainment center. The bathroom is equipped with a sink, toilet, and a sonic shower. The crewmen each receive a separate bedroom which is only large enough for a twin bed, a dresser, and a small closet. Senior Officers fair slightly better in that they do not have to share their living space with another officer. But their stateroom, sleeping arrangement, and bathing facilities are of the same design as the Junior Officers. The Captain, Executive Officer, and visiting VIP's fair much better. Each has a dining module roughly 25% larger then the junior officers, a bathroom with a whirlpool bath/ sonic shower, and a bedroom large enough for a walk in closet, a full sized bed, and a large work/entertainment station. Only the Captain, Executive Officer, and V.I.P. quarters are outfitted with food dispensers similar to the ones found in either of the crew lounges.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Crew Recreational Facilities</title>
      <para>There are two crew lounges, the Forecastle, and the Fantail. The Forecastle Lounge is located in the forward most part of the saucer section on Deck-5.  This is usually considered as the Junior Officer, Enlisted and NE ranks lounge. Under usual conditions, there is a movie shown on the large display screen twice a week for the crew's enjoyment, although programming is subject to Captain's discretion.  Also located in the Forecastle Lounge is a well stocked and fully equipped game locker.  Stocked inside is a wide range of portable table top games for the crew to use at their leisure.   The locker may be stocked with such games as three dimensional chess, holo-battleship, and Fizbit.</para>
      <para>The Fantail lounge is located on the aft most section of Deck-6.  It is smaller, and has a minor increase in creature comforts when compared to the Forecastle.  As such, it is usually considered as the command staff and VIP lounge.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Gymnasium</title>
      <para>There is a small gymnasium located on the lower aft section of Deck 14.  It is equipped with a sparing wring for boxing/wrestling/fencing or other forms of hand to hand combat, and nautilus machinery to keep the crew in peek physical condition.  Should the situation arise, the Gymnasium's equipment can be easily stored, thus opening up the room's area to be used as an auditorium or act as an auxiliary storage room.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Galley</title>
      <para>Located near the center of Deck-4 is the ship's Galley.  Although capable of reproducing a variety of food selections, Mariner Class is equipped with both a food synthesizer system, and a fully functioning Galley.  Food stuffs for the Galley are stored in three separate fully compartmentalized pantries, each compartment equipped with their own stasis field generators to preserve freshness.</para>
      <para>The food synthesizer system is comprised of a matter re-sequencer system connected to the waste reclamation system.  The matter re-sequencer recycles biological waste materials into simple protein and sucrose compounds resembling meat/ dairy/ vegetable byproducts such as ground beef, fish or poultry, cheeses, fruit juices and preserves.  Although highly efficient, the re-sequencer is incapable of creating food stuffs with a complex layered formation as found in a turkey leg (with fat, bone and skin attached to the meat), or the fibrous consistency of fresh fruits and vegetables.</para>
      <para>Galley prepared or processed synthesized food stuffs are distributed via a computer controlled network of food dispensers.  Any materials left over from the meal such as the dinner ware, or undigested food stuffs placed back into the dispenser are automatically recycled into the waste reclamation system. Each dispenser consists of a closed circuit micro transporter mounted as an enclosed wall unit in specified areas through out the ship.  These areas include: the Brig, both the Forecastle and Fantail crew lounges, the Captain's, XO's, and VIP's quarters, Main Engineering, Sickbay, the Shuttlebay, and the Transporter Rooms.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Medical Facilities</title>
      <para>The ship's Sickbay is located on Deck-5, in the very center of the saucer section, and is the most highly protected section in the entire ship. Sickbay is comprised of two examination rooms separated by a surgical room, which in turn is also bordered by a recovery room. Each examination room is outfitted with two biobeds. The surgical room is similarly outfitted with two bio beds, which are in turn modified specifically for delicate surgical procedures. The recovery room is outfitted with twelve bio beds that are designed more for a patient's comfort and recovery. In addition, there is an emergency aid station located on every deck near the turbolift entrance.  Each aid station is nothing more then an equipment locker housing three antigrav gurneys, and two fully stocked emergency first aid kits.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Auxiliary Spacecraft Systems</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>Hamlet, Act-I, Scene-V</attribution>
      <para>"There are more things in heaven and earth, Horatio, than are dreamt of in your philosophy."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <para>As stated before, the shuttlecraft landing bay is located aft of the secondary hull. The launch bay is comprised of a double set of doors as a safe guard against mechanical failure or damage suffered from combat. The Mariner's Shuttlebay is large enough to handle the maintenance and offloading requirements for a standard complement of five shuttle craft. The bay is capable of launching two shuttle craft at a time. During normal operations, as the double bay doors are opened, a level-4 force field is erected to keep the shuttlebay's atmosphere inside the ship while allowing for the safe launch or retrieval of shuttlecraft.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Technical Specifications</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Dimensions and Structure</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Length</term>
        <listitem><para>350 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Beam (Width)</term>
        <listitem><para>137 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Height</term>
        <listitem><para>60.2 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Decks</term>
        <listitem><para>14</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>      
    <variablelist>
      <title>Crew Complement</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Officers and Crew</term>
        <listitem><para>375</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Command</term>
        <listitem><para>25</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Engineering</term>
        <listitem><para>75</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Medical</term>
        <listitem><para>15</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Science</term>
        <listitem><para>200</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Security</term>
        <listitem><para>60</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Visiting Personnel</term>
        <listitem><para>60</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Evacuation Limit</term>
        <listitem><para>2000</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Computer Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Core</term>
        <listitem><para>M6 Duotronic core x1, M2 Duotronic core x1</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Operating System</term>
        <listitem><para>Windows 1.0</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>User Interface</term>
        <listitem><para>MAJEL 1.0</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>  
    <variablelist>
      <title>Warp Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Power Plant</term>
        <listitem><para>One 900 cochrane M/ARA cores feeding two nacelles</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Crusing Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>TOS-Warp 5.5</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Sustainable Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>TOS-Warp 8.5</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>TOS-Warp 9.6 (12 hours)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Impulse Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Full Impulse</term>
        <listitem><para>0.25c</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Accellerate</term>
        <listitem><para>29 seconds</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Decellerate</term>
        <listitem><para>57 seconds</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>  
    <variablelist>
      <title>Defensive Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)</term>
        <listitem><para>2016 MegaWatts</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate</term>
        <listitem><para>2.0x10^5 kilowatts</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>  
    <variablelist>
      <title>Offensive Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Torpedoes</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Torpedo Tubes</term>
              <listitem><para>3</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Standard Payload (total)</term>
              <listitem><para>150 photon torpedoes plus 25 scientific probes and 25 unequipped casings</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Phasers</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>6 Type-VIII Phaser Emitters in 3 banks of 2</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>6 Type-VII phaser emitters mounted in 3 banks of 2.</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Deck Layout</title>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 1</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Bridge</member>
        <member>Chart Room</member>
        <member>Conference Room-A</member>
        <member>Ready Room</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 2</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>CO's quarters</member>
        <member>XO's quarters</member>
        <member>VIP quarters</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 3</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Conference Room-B</member>
        <member>Emergency Transporter #1</member>
        <member>Food Locker #1-3</member>
        <member>Officer's quarters</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Level-1</member>
        <member>Shield Emitters #1-2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 4</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxiliary Control</member>
        <member>Auxiliary Life Support</member>
        <member>Auxiliary Power</member>
        <member>Galley</member>
        <member>Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Type-VIII Phaser Banks #1-2 (forward port, and forward starboard)</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Level-2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 5</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxiliary Sensory Grid</member>
        <member>Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Docking Airlock #1-2 (Port and Starboard)</member>
        <member>Forecastle Crew Lounge</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Level-3</member>
        <member>Primary Transporter Rooms #1-2 (port and starboard)</member>
        <member>Sickbay</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 6</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxiliary Cargo Holds 1-2</member>
        <member>Crew Quarters</member>
        <member>Fan Tail Officer's Lounge</member>
        <member>Deuterium Storage Tanks A and B (port and starboard)</member>
        <member>Impulse Drive (aft)</member>
        <member>Type-VIII Phaser Bank #3 (forward)</member>
        <member>Type-VII Phaser Banks #1-2 (port and starboard)</member>
        <member>Tractor Beam Emitters #1-2 (Forward-Port and Forward-Starboard)</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 7</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Emergency Transporter #2</member>
        <member> Photon Torpedo Room</member>
        <member>Photon Torpedo Bunker</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 8</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Photon Torpedo Launchers #1-2-3 (#1-2 for, #3 aft)</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 9</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Archeology Lab</member>
        <member>Geophysics Lab</member>
        <member>Meteorology Lab</member>
        <member>Primary Communications Array</member>
        <member>Quantum Mechanics Lab</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 10</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Botanical Lab</member>
        <member>Biochemistry Lab</member>
        <member>Biophysics Lab</member>
        <member>Main Deflector Dish</member>
        <member>Main Engineering Level-1</member>
        <member>Primary Life Support</member>
        <member>Shield Emitters #3-4</member>
        <member>Xenobiology Lab</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 11</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Cargo Transporter #1-2</member>
        <member>Main Deflector Dish</member>
        <member>Main Engineering Level-2</member>
        <member>Mechanical Engineering Lab</member>
        <member>Primary Cargo Hold #1-2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 12</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Auxiliary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Cargo Transporter #3</member>
        <member>Deuterium Storage Tank-C</member>
        <member>Main Engineering Level-3</member>
        <member>Type-VII Phaser Bank #3 (aft)</member>
        <member>Primary Cargo Hold #3</member>
        <member>Shield Emitters #5-6</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 13</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Cargo Transporter #4</member>
        <member>Fusion Reactors</member>
        <member>Primary Cargo Hold #4</member>
        <member>Shuttlebay</member>
        <member>Waste Reclamation</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 14</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Armory</member>
        <member>Brig</member>
        <member>Gymnasium</member>
        <member>Phaser Array #8-9 (port, and starboard)</member>
        <member>Shield Emitters #7-8</member>
        <member>Tractor Beam Emitters #3-4</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Ships of the Class</title>
    <simplelist role="ShipList">
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Mariner</productname>
        <productnumber>2342</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Bellerophon</productname>
        <productnumber>2343</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Dauntless</productname>
        <productnumber>2344</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Gallant</productname>
        <productnumber>2345</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Merrimack</productname>
        <productnumber>2346</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Monitor</productname>
        <productnumber>2347</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Reliance</productname>
        <productnumber>2348</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Renown</productname>
        <productnumber>2349</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Repulse</productname>
        <productnumber>2350</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="NPC">
        <productname>Dunsel</productname>
        <productnumber>2354</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="NPC">
        <productname>Fliver</productname>
        <productnumber>2356</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="NPC">
        <productname>Nolo</productname>
        <productnumber>2357</productnumber>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <epigraph>
      <attribution>All's Well that Ends Well, Act-V, Scene-III</attribution>
      <para>"All yet seems well; and if it end so meet, the bitter past, more welcome is the sweet."</para>
    </epigraph>
    <para>It is hoped that with the expanding frontiers of space, the Mariner class ships will lead the way, discovering what surprises may lay in store for that great "Undiscovered Country", the future.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Illustrations</title>
    <para>These other visual representations of the Mariner are available.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="full">
        <objectinfo>
          <author>
            <firstname>Bret</firstname>
            <surname>Godfrey</surname>
          </author>
        </objectinfo>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tm/mariner-side.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="thumbnail">
        <objectinfo>
          <author>
            <firstname>Larry</firstname>
            <surname>Garfield</surname>
          </author>
        </objectinfo>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tm/mariner-side-thumb.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Mariner, Side View</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="full">
        <objectinfo>
          <author>
            <firstname>Bret</firstname>
            <surname>Godfrey</surname>
          </author>
        </objectinfo>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tm/mariner-front.jpg" format="JPG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="thumbnail">
        <objectinfo>
          <author>
            <firstname>Larry</firstname>
            <surname>Garfield</surname>
          </author>
        </objectinfo>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tm/mariner-front-thumb.jpg" format="JPG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Mariner, Front View</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="full">
        <objectinfo>
          <author>
            <firstname>Bret</firstname>
            <surname>Godfrey</surname>
          </author>
        </objectinfo>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tm/mariner-aft.jpg" format="JPG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="thumbnail">
        <objectinfo>
          <author>
            <firstname>Larry</firstname>
            <surname>Garfield</surname>
          </author>
        </objectinfo>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tm/mariner-aft-thumb.jpg" format="JPG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Mariner, Aft View</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="full">
        <objectinfo>
          <author>
            <firstname>Bret</firstname>
            <surname>Godfrey</surname>
          </author>
        </objectinfo>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tm/mariner-bottom.jpg" format="JPG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="thumbnail">
        <objectinfo>
          <author>
            <firstname>Larry</firstname>
            <surname>Garfield</surname>
          </author>
        </objectinfo>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tm/mariner-bottom-thumb.jpg" format="JPG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Mariner, Bottom View</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</article>
