<article class="specification" id="Mythology">
  <title>Mythology-class</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup role="Maintainer">
      <author>
        <firstname>Robert</firstname>
        <surname>Archer</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Primary Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Robert</firstname>
        <surname>Archer</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Original Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Robert</firstname>
        <surname>Archer</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword role="service">PC</keyword>
      <keyword role="category">Explorer</keyword>
      <keyword role="variant">Deep Space</keyword>
      <keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>22 September, 2013</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Assistant Engineering Director Aaron Calhoun</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>History and Mission Overview</title>
      <para>In the early days of 2383, there were those in Starfleet, mostly in the Exploratory Division, who foresaw what was now becoming a new 'Golden Age of Exploration' for the Federation and its allies. Because of this there was an obvious need for a new multi-purpose deep space explorer, one that would recall the earliest values of the Federation.</para>
      <para>The designers decided upon a large ship platform that would house some of the finest sensors, warp engines, and shield systems that were offered during and after the Dominion War. At the same time these designers gave the ship ample weapons to defend itself in its missions of exploration and diplomacy. Finally, the designers built into the class many redundant and resilient systems, as well as expanded work areas to increase its endurance when far from Federation space. The designers hoped in later years that this design would replace the older Excelsior and Ambassador Class vessels in the fleet. They also intended it to be an alternate design to the proven Galaxy and Viking class explorers.</para>
      <para>However, as design work continued into the ending months of 2386, an alliance was forged between the Federation and the newly discovered Flea'tan Alliance. A technology exchange occurred between the two powers, and several ship design workers of the Alliance came to assist in the design of this and several other new classes. Once brought up to speed on how ship design work of Federation technology functioned, they began inputting their own technologies and ideas into the new vessel's framework. To this co-operative design came a new deep space explorer of a kind unseen since Starfleet's earliest days of co-operative expansion.</para>
      <para>As a year passed with final design work, June of 2387 finally heralded the first prototype to come out of the Utopia Planitia Fleet Yards. The USS Mythology NX-98711 was given over to Starfleet Command for full review and approval. Finding such a well stocked vessel able to fit many core mission profiles Starfleet Command in the final months of 2387 gave the approval for the official construction of the Mythology class deep space explorer.</para>
	  <section>
      <title>Mission Profiles</title>
	  <para>Due to its large size and self reliance, the Mythology class is well suited to the following mission profiles:</para>
    <simplelist>
      <member>Long term deep space exploration and patrols</member>
      <member>First contact with new races and entities</member>
	</simplelist>
	<para>With inclusion of its mission modules the Mythology has further expanded profiles:</para>
	<simplelist>
      <member>Large scale diplomatic functions</member>
      <member>Large scale cargo transport</member>
      <member>Large scale entertainment functions</member>
      <member>Large scale search and rescue operations</member>
      <member>Colonization of planets</member>
	  <member>Fleet level command and control</member>
      <member>Emergency evacuations</member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Structure and Construction</title>
      <para>The Mythology class is a large ship platform spanning 45 decks. Its saucer begins in an inset teardrop and angles out and back into a half oval near the rear. A thick, wide neck connects it seamlessly in an angled slope to the engineering hull. This hull section is like the top of a tear drop at the front, only to angle back near the aft section to a square broad base. The warp nacelles are mounted to the aft section of the engineering hull.</para>
      <para>The warp nacelles are positioned on short variable struts that enable the nacelles to project from the engineering hull in an upward 90 degree arc. The designers kept them as close as possible to the main space frame to reduce its profile were combat to occur, while at the same time allowing enough room for the nearby mission module docking areas to be easily swapped as needed.</para>
      <para>To further specify, decks 1 through 20 are in the saucer; 21 through 45 form the engineering hull.</para>
      <para>The hull structure of the Mythology is composed of a 75 / 25 mixture duranium / tritanium alloy double layered hull inset with hardened duranium fillings. The design was then transporter welded along the whole superstructure. Finally, the hull was covered with high density duranium alloy, with composite duranium plastic sheets, measuring 5.0 cm thick as a secondary layer of protection.</para>
	  <section>
      <title>Mission Modules</title>
      <para>The Mythology class has three mission module swap areas. The first is located aft of the bridge and below on an angle from shuttle bay 1 on decks 5 through 8; the other two are located in the engineering hull. They are placed on the lower aft port and starboard areas of the connecting structure on decks 30 through 33. These modules are easily hot swapped out at any star base that has such facilities. Typical swap over times range from 3 to 5 days. When a particular module suite is chosen by the Captain and Command officers for the mission ahead all three bays are used.</para>
      <para>The available modules are as follows:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Expanded Cargo Module</term>
          <listitem><para>In their default configuration these modules are open bay areas often used for on hand spare parts or supplies for the mission ahead. This allows the Mythology further cargo storage for long range missions or large scale supply efforts.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Planetary Colonization Module</term>
          <listitem><para>This suite of modules gives the Mythology class the ability to operate as a colonization ship. When installed it gives:</para>
		  <simplelist>
			<member>Quarters for up to 500 colonists</member>
			<member>Six months of consumables</member>
			<member>Various colony supplies for construction and setup</member>
			<member>Essential and specialized terra-forming equipment storage</member>
		  </simplelist></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Expanded Diplomatic Module</term>
          <listitem><para>This suite of modules gives expanded diplomatic meeting rooms. When installed it gives:</para>
		  <simplelist>
			<member>Twelve Ambassadorial quarters each</member>
			<member>Two hundred staff quarters each</member>
			<member>One conference hall complex with bar and mess area for 200 guests</member>
			<member>12 twelve seat briefing rooms</member>
			<member>Facilities and quarters, for up to 100 members of the press</member>
			<member>All areas are capable of supporting H, K, or L environments</member>
		  </simplelist></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Expanded Entertainment Module</term>
          <listitem><para>When installed it gives the Mythology expanded entertainment capabilities, including:</para>
		  <simplelist>
			<member>Sixteen holosuites</member>
			<member>Six recreation and performance halls for live performances</member>
			<member>Three 100 yard long twelve feet deep swimming pools with spa facilities</member>
			<member>Three casinos with two deck bars</member>
			<member>Three cargo and replication areas for entertainment storage and small scale fabrication</member>
			<member>Fifteen fusion generators to support the added power demands of each module, five generators are located in each module.</member>
		  </simplelist></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
          <term>Expanded Weapons and Fleet Operations Control Module</term>
          <listitem><para>This suite of modules when installed gives the Mythology expanded weapon set-ups, as well as the ability to more easily coordinate fleet operations. It also includes the capacity for tactical missions where heavy scale boarding actions are required.</para>
		  <simplelist>
			<member>Six Type VIII phaser arrays, two to each module, with 25 emitters each, each array outputting 2.6 megawatts to a range of 150,000 km</member>
              <member>25 Marine personnel barracks in module one in the saucer</member>
              <member>A fleet operations and control suite in module one in the saucer to coordinate fleet movements and activities</member>
              <member>Two auxiliary craft bays in module two and three each with two Danube class runabouts with included heavy weapons pod, and Marine personnel carrier module</member>
              <member>The modules each come equipped with the needed power, supply and equipment and storage areas</member>
		  </simplelist></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
          <term>Search and Rescue Operations Module</term>
          <listitem><para>This suite of modules gives the Mythology the ability to evacuate and treat critically injured refugees from stricken sites, as well as providing enhanced material for large scale search and rescue missions and medical relief efforts.</para>
		  <simplelist>
			<member>50 JO sized quarters in module 1 in the saucer, each room capable of holding 4 people comfortably</member>
              <member>One cargo bay in module 1, containing relief and medical supplies for the treatment of refugees aboard ship</member>
              <member>Two 50 biobed triage sickbays in modules 2 and 3</member>
              <member>20 medical crew quarters, ten to each module in modules two and three in the engineering hull</member>
		  </simplelist></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
          <term>Flea'tan Compression Relay Jump Core Module</term>
          <listitem><para>Located on decks 40 and 41, just behind the primary warp core, is located a modular area for the sole use of the experimental Flea'tan Compression Relay Jump Core. This modular area is set up for the use of this core for those Mythology ships in the Fleet 5 and 6 areas of operation where the relay network is in use. For those Mythology ships not in such operational areas this modular bay is left empty and open for use as the crew sees fit to accommodate mission needs in flight.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
      <section>
      <title>Sensor Systems</title>
	  <para>The Mythology houses the Class 10 sensor system. This system design layout gained high praise by scientists and tactical minded designers alike during the later stages of the Dominion War for its reliability and ease of use over older systems and design set-ups. The system has a maximum high resolution range out to 5.0 light years, and a low resolution range out to 17.0 light years. The system has built in redundancies that allow it to function at varying reduced levels if damage occurs, far above presently fielded designs. The sensor pallets are arranged in circular clusters along the lines of the saucer and in square clusters along the sides ventral and dorsal of the engineering hull. The main deflector itself is located along decks 30 through 33 in the engineering hull.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Computer and Network Systems</title>
	  <para>The Mythology comes equipped with three computer cores. The primary and secondary cores were enhanced with bio-neural processing circuity to speed up response times. The third core is solely made up of standard isolinear data storage chips and processors. The primary core is located on decks 8 through 11. The secondary core is located on decks 30 through 33. The backup core is located in the aft section of the neck areas of the engineering hull, on decks 23 through 25.</para>
	  <para>In normal operations the combination core in the saucer handles all primary ship operations; the second combination core handles any further demands in normal operations as the need arises. Only when both cores are damaged or offline does the tertiary core come online. When in operation, it can only run critical ship systems such as life support, engines, basic sensors, manual limited weapon targeting and navigation.</para>
	  <para>The Mythology uses bio-neural circuitry for all primary systems and a back up isolinear network for secondary systems during normal operations. To further improve its redundancy and survival capabilities, the back up isolinear network is able to operate critical primary systems if the bio-neural circuitry is compromised or damaged. To aid in preventing infections the bio-neural circuitry uses the I-MUN Mark II filter series.</para> <para>The combination cores use the LCARS OS using the MAJEL interface. The saucer and engineering hull cores house UHPAVS (Upgraded Hacking Prevention and Anti Virus Scanner), as well as RSUEP (Really Stupid User Error Prevention) data programs. However, the standard isolinear backup core lacks this feature, as well as the more advanced functions of the MAJEL interface. Captains commanding these ships are strongly warned to keep genius inebriated adolescents, high risk crew members or visitors away from consoles in such an emergency. During use of specialized mission modules, the engineering hull combination computer core handles all functions of the mission modules.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Holographic Systems</title>
	  <para>The Mythology has holo-emitters situated at key points across the ship: in this case the bridge, 17/18 forward, the gym, the cargo bays and main engineering. This allows the ship's two EMH Mark IV programs to appear in these areas besides the sickbays, holodecks and holosuites. The EMH Mark IV programs are located in both the primary and secondary computer cores. This allows two programs to be active at any given time.</para>
  </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Warp Propulsion Systems</title>
      <para>Given the ships large size, and the designers plans to give the Mythology class the most self reliance and sufficiency capable for long deep space missions, it is equipped with the Class 10 warp core. The core was retrofitted for ease of use and maintenance for long term missions far from Federation supply and refitting yards.</para>
	  <para>This core feeds two nacelles, outputting 7,912 cocharanes, giving the Mythology a standard cruising speed of warp 6.8, a max sustainable speed of warp 9.6, a maximum velocity for twelve hours of warp 9.98, and an emergency speed of warp 9.99. Due to its larger than usual size and power demands, the ship is slower than others that would mount the Class 10 core.</para>
	  <para>The nacelles are mounted on variable pylons, which also house their support systems. As with much of the ship they contain reinforced superstructure, and both primary and secondary warp coils.</para>
      <para>Ejection systems propel the Class 10 warp core out the top of the engineering hull in an emergency.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
      <para>The Mythology houses two impulse engines. These two engines can propel the ship to a maximum thrust of .25c in seventy-five seconds and from full impulse to a complete stop in one-hundred fifteen seconds. The two engines are mounted port and starboard on the aft quarter of the saucer on decks 18 through 20. As with much of the design the reactors for these engines are reinforced to be resistant to extended and strenuous use far beyond more commonly used designed engines.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Tactical Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Defensive Shields</title>
	  <para>The Mythology mounts the Type 10 shield system. Emitters are placed in key positions along the whole width and breadth of the ship's frame. The maximum graviton load that can be sustained is 2150 megawatts and a maximum dissipation rate of 5.84 x 10^5 kW. The shield system is also equipped with metaphasic programming for close solar body entry and radiation anomalies.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Phaser Systems</title>
	  <para>The Mythology uses ten strips of Type 10 phaser arrays. They are positioned as follows:</para>
	  <simplelist>
			<member>One horseshoe strip ventral and dorsal along the saucer with 200 emitters each.</member>
            <member>One strip along the underbelly of the engineering hull behind the main deflector with 100 emitters each.</member>
            <member>One strip ventral trailing down the connecting neck, stopping above the warp nacelles, with 100 emitters each.</member>
            <member>One strip dorsal and ventral along the aft section of the engineering hull, with 100 emitters each.</member>
            <member>Two strips port and starboard along the aft section of the engineering hull with 75 emitters each.</member>
            <member>Two strips port and starboard on the nacelle pylons with 50 emitters each.</member>
		  </simplelist>
		<para>Each strip can output 5.1 megawatts out to 300,000 kilometers.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Torpedo Systems</title>
	  <para>The Mythology is armed with two Type 4 burst fire torpedo launchers; each launcher is capable of firing up to 5 torpedoes every 10 seconds. Each launcher is positioned one forward and one aft upon the engineering hull contained in the connecting structure, on decks 35 through 37.</para>
	  <para>The ship carries 350 casings: 145 of these are for photon torpedoes, 50 for quantum torpedoes, 5 are kept empty in reserve, 5 are Tricobalt devices, and a further 145 are for specialized probes. They have a maximum effective range of 3,500,000 km.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Command and Support Systems</title>
	<section>
    <title>Bridge</title>
      <para>The Mythology class bridge is located on Deck 1; it is arranged in a circular shape. The bridge is equipped with easy modular setup for refits, repairs and replacement as time and natural wear and tear takes its toll on the ship. The aft section of the bridge contains nine banks of consoles, default setup from port to starboard is:</para>
	  <simplelist>
			<member>Support Science 1</member>
            <member>Support Science 2</member>
            <member>Support Science 3</member>
            <member>Engineering Support 1</member>
            <member>Engineering Support 2</member>
            <member>Engineering Support 3</member>
            <member>Miscellaneous / Auxiliary 1</member>
            <member>Miscellaneous / Auxiliary 2</member>
            <member>Miscellaneous / Auxiliary 3</member>
		  </simplelist>
	  <para>Two rectangular consoles for the tactical and security officers are located just forward of the wall stations. Directly starboard to the tactical officer are the Operations and Mission Ops stations. Two small auxiliary panels to either side of these spots can be configured for use as needed for mission specific guests.</para>
      <para>A guide rail circles down the middle area of the bridge. Just forward of the railing from port to starboard are the Executive Officer, Captain, Counselor and two mission specialist chairs. Handy flip up consoles give critical data access to each officer and guest. In the right arm rest of the Captain's chair is a flip up holder which contains a clip for a type 2 phaser. An optional hat, jacket or trophy rack, depending on the Captain's preference, connects to a front baseboard of the tactical and security consoles. Along the starboard wall of the bridge are the Helm and 2nd officers stations and directly across on the port wall are the Chief Science Officers and Chief Engineers bridge stations.</para>
      <para>At the front of the bridge is the view screen. On either side of this are two science related holo projector units allowing 3-D views of interesting objects to be shown. The bridge has three turbo lifts: two forward, one port and starboard of the view screen and one aft starboard. Along various console edges and other places that could cause injuries during stumbles or falls is 2.5 cm of soft foam padding.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Ready Room</title>
      <para>The ready room is located to the aft port of the bridge; it contains a desk, couch, two chairs and replicator, plus small areas for personal effects. An emergency access tube near the aft wall bulkhead behind the COs desk is located in the aft portion of this room down to deck 2, which connects to the Jeffries tubes there.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Briefing Room</title>
      <para>Located forward starboard of the bridge, just aft from the turbolift, is the briefing room. This room curves around the outer edges of the bridge. A large table able to seat twelve is present, as well as a large display screen along the bridge facing wall. A holo projector is present for more careful study of 3-d diagrams and simulations shown compared to those on the bridge.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Holding Cells</title>
      <para>Though not normally meant to house combat prisoners or other large scale groups of trouble makers, the Mythology nonetheless has four holding cells. Each area can house five occupants comfortably or ten if comfort room is not a concern. Two of these facilities are located on deck 10 port and starboard in the saucer section. Two more are located on deck 40 port and starboard. As a strict precaution in case of power loss, the cells have an emergency five hour generator to prevent prisoner escape. In addition each cell guard is armed with a Type 2 phaser set to wide heavy stun under normal operating conditions.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Security Office / Armoury</title>
      <para>This complex is located in the aft section of decks 14 and 15 in the saucer. From the office located in this section, the Chief of Security has the ability to control all holding cell functions, most security related matters to the ship, and track all security and tactical personnel. The armoury is also along the middle portion of these decks port and starboard, housing enough Type 2 phasers to arm the whole ship's crew if needed, as well as 200 Type 3 phaser rifles for the ship's security forces. This two deck complex also houses two training rooms.</para>
      </section>
	  <section>
	  <title>Science Labs</title>
      <para>All along decks 13 through 15 of the saucer are located the assorted science labs of the Mythology class. Each of these labs also house small holo-projectors to allow full careful 3-D study of various topics. Along the forward port areas of deck 26 in the engineering hull are smaller secondary support and generalized science labs. The Chief Science Officer's office is located on deck 13 attached to the larger general science lab complex. This office allows the CSO to maintain full control and observation at any given time of what their staff is studying and testing.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Main Engineering</title>
      <para>Main engineering runs along almost all of the central part of decks 40 to 42 with support areas along the lower reaches of decks 43 in these same areas. The warp core raises the full height of engineering on decks 40 to 42. The Chief Engineers office is located on the main work area of deck 41 facing the core. From here the officer can oversee all power functions, status of repairs and engineering teams under their charge.</para>
	  <para>Core ejection systems for the core and antimatter pods lead up a chute out the top of the engineering hull. As an extreme back up precaution, there is a manual release system at the top of the core which will engage the pressurized ejection systems, launching the core out of the hull via a pneumatic pump system. This can be utilized in a situation where the power required for the automatic ejection system fails, though use of this system is a last measure, and carries a high risk of injury to the crew member who engages it, owing to the risk of explosive gases released.</para>
	  <para>Also contained here is the much smaller Flea'tan Compression Relay Jump Core module: this two deck module aligns itself to the rear of the Class X warp core on decks 40 and 41.</para>
	  <para>Monitoring systems and consoles for each power source are also aligned in a square around this whole double decked oval shaped room.</para>
	  <para>In an emergency this area can be converted into a secondary bridge.</para>
  </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Utility Systems</title>
    <section>
      <title>Cargo Bays</title>
	  <para>The Mythology houses four large cargo bays in the saucer and two smaller in the aft section of the engineering hull. Each cargo bay holds a single cargo transporter each. The large primary cargo bays are situated along the outer edge of the saucer on decks 5 and 6 two on each side. The smaller secondary bays are located port and starboard at the aft most areas of deck 45 in the aft quarter of the engineering hull near the fourth shuttle bay positioned port and starboard. Each of these bays houses an exterior door for access while in dock. These access doors are covered by a sliding panel of duranium hull plate, which retracts when needed. The larger primary cargo bays in the saucer can also serve as a docking port for cargo ships if required for special sensitive cargo, utilizing an extending airlock docking clamp.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tractor Beam Systems</title>
	  <para>The Mythology is equipped with two tractor emitters. The two large tractor emitters are housed in the aft dorsal section of the engineering hull, on deck 45, and at the front of the neck of the connecting spine above the forward facing torpedo tube, on deck 35.</para>
      <para>The emitters can handle a total mass of 7,500,000 metric tons out to 3,000 km.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Transporter Systems</title>
	  <para>The Mythology has eight transporter rooms, which are each capable of transporting six personnel at a time. Two transporter rooms are on deck 8, two are on deck 9, two are on deck 23, and two are on deck 24. Each transporter system has a range of 40,000 km.</para>
      <para>Two emergency 12-person transporters are located port and starboard in the saucer on deck 18 along the central axis and another two are located on deck 29 in the forward area of the engineering hull near the main deflector dish, each with a range of 15,000 km.</para>
    </section>
	<section>
      <title>Turbolift Systems</title>
	  <para>The turbolift car systems run the length and breadth of all decks to critical hub areas. The cars themselves are made from reinforced duranium construction. Each car holds a small pack with an emergency medical and field engineer kit in case of crew becoming trapped owing to ship-wide catastrophe. Due to the needs of reinforcement and the storage space needs of the emergency kits these cars are 1.3 meters in circular radius larger then others around the Federation.</para>
    </section>
	<section>
      <title>Machine Shop</title>
	  <para>The Mythology's machine shop is located on decks 31-33 in between the ship's 2nd and 3rd Mission Module areas.</para>
	  <para>http://www.star-fleet.com/library/bookshelf/tm/machineshop.html</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Crew Support Systems</title>
	<section>
    <title>Sickbay</title>
      <para>The Mythology houses two large sickbays in the saucer port and starboard of deck 12. A smaller one in the engineering hull is housed on deck 39. The larger sickbays house 50 biobeds with 5 surgery and isolation bays. The smaller sickbay holds 25 beds with 2 small surgery and isolation bays. All three sickbays house emergency life support and power systems to run critical equipment for 24 hours, as well as redundant isolation systems for airborne pathogens.</para>
	  <para>The Chief Medical Officers office is located in Sickbay 1 on deck 12, able to monitor all patient and staffs current status.</para>
	  <para>The sickbay in the engineering hull is used as a nurse's station in normal operating conditions, except during times of yellow or red alert status.</para>
	  <para>The ship's two EMH Mark IV programs can also be run in these locations.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Counselling Suites</title>
      <para>The ship's counselling offices are located on deck 11 port in the saucer. A total of six offices are present to serve the civilian and Starfleet crew's counselling needs.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Holographic Entertainment Facilities</title>
      <para>The Mythology houses five holosuites and five holodecks. The holosuites are located along the outer edge of decks 16 and 17 of the saucer, three to port and two to starboard. Two holodecks are located port and starboard on deck 16, with three more holodecks located in the engineering hull on decks 37 and 38 of the engineering hull.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Gym</title>
      <para>The ship's Gym is found at the forward areas of deck 17 and contains various exercise equipment from across the Federation and allied races. The room is able to allow work out 30 crew members at a time. The room also has variable gravity settings for those wishing a heavier workout. In an emergency the gym can double as a triage center for mass injuries able to support 45 patients and medical staff.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Recreation Hall</title>
      <para>The ship's Recreation Hall is located directly below the ship's gym on decks 18 and 19. The Recreation hall contains many non-holographic forms of entertainment. These include both board and card games, two tennis tables, two pool tables, a small 18-meter long, 3.7-meter deep pool, four bowling lanes, and a small beverage bar. This room is able to contain up to 50 people at any given time.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>17/18 Forward</title>
      <para>17/18 Forward is connected directly to the ship's gym and the Recreation Hall at the front of the saucer section. It curves around them in a half arc contouring to these two areas.</para>
	  <para>A full-service kitchen and galley are on the port side of the room providing freshly prepared fare for visitors and crew alike. The room has twelve replicators, three on each deck area port and starboard.</para>
	  <para>Deck 17 of this room has a large table to support parties seating 16 people. A small holographic display can show forms of entertainment as well. Five smaller tables of 2 to 6 crew in size are also on this top floor. About 26 to 30 people can be accommodated comfortably in this area.</para>
	  <para>Deck 18 of this room is accessed by two safety stairwells angled down from 17. This area contains 15 tables of varying size from 3 to 10 crew in size. About 45 people can be accommodated comfortably in this area.</para>
	  <para>Large open observation windows provide scenic viewing in general operations. During yellow or red alert statuses however, plating of duranium slides down to aid in preventing decompression in case of hull damage. During large scale injuries these two rooms can contain up to 50 triage patients and 25 medical staff.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Arboretum</title>
      <para>The Mythology contains three arboreta. A large one on deck 14 of the saucer, and two small ones on decks 26 and 38 in the engineering hull. All three contain various plants, herbs and flowers from across Federation space.</para>
	  <para>Benches and paths wander through all three areas providing a true planet like experience, which looks out upon the stars through windows, without the need for a holodeck or suite. These areas are cared for by civilian crew groundskeepers.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Civilian / Family Support Shelters</title>
      <para>Located on deck 20 of the saucer and decks 21, 37 and 38 of the engineering hull are emergency shelter areas for non-combat crew and civilian and family personnel.</para>
	  <para>These rooms set up to house up to 50 people each, contain emergency life support and food storage for up to a week of survival needs. In addition they are able to be isolated by level 10 force fields and contain reinforced duranium walls and ceiling structures.</para>
	  <para>These areas are only used by such personnel in a case of shipwide emergency or red alert status. During such occupation two junior officers are assigned to each room as shelter leaders.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Schooling Facilities / Nurseries</title>
      <para>Located on decks 15, 16, 23 and 24 near the ships family quarters are the ships four schooling facilities and nurseries.</para>
	  <para>These facilities are manned by civilian personnel for teaching the children of the crews families and taking care of any babies among the crew</para>
	  <para>Like the emergency family areas, these areas contain emergency life support and food storage for up to a week of survival needs.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Diplomatic Hall</title>
      <para>Because many of its missions were hoped to entail first contact and exploration beyond the bounds of Federation space, the Mythology class is equipped with a spacious diplomatic hall capable of supporting up to 40 people at any given time. The entire hall complex is located on deck 2 of the saucer; it has a slight oval circular shape with four entry ways, two to port two to starboard, from the turbolifts. The hall is completely open allowing partition panels and tables to be arranged as needs require by the crew during flight. Eight exterior viewing ports are arranged around the hall. Finally, the hall contains floor and ceiling mounting points for display panels, briefing screens or other devices as needed.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>General Purpose Areas</title>
      <para>Located on decks 20 aft in the saucer and 21 and 22 in the engineering hull are three general purpose areas. These areas are left open and only sparsely finished to allow the ship's crew the ability to adjust the area's layout to suit needs while in flight. This can include anything from spare parts storage to special personnel needs or visiting VIP offices. The areas can be set up to accommodate any known environment type and has the ability to produce gravity effects up to five times Earth standard gravity.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>CO's Quarters</title>
      <para>The COs Quarters are located on deck 3 starboard and are spacious and open. The room is divided into three areas: a living and work area, a sleeping area with private storage. The living and work area has two couches, a table, desk and workstation with table. The bedroom has a large king-sized bed and bathroom, complete with a three person hot tub. Connecting to this is the COs storage room, allowing personal effects to be easily on hand when wanted. This storage room is a 3x2 meter rectangular shaped room.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>XO's Quarters</title>
      <para>The XOs Quarters are located on deck 3 port, and are slightly smaller than the COs. The room is divided into two areas; a living and work area and a sleeping area. The living and work area holds one large and one small couch, a table, desk and workstation with table. The bedroom has a king-sized bed and bathroom, with a smaller two person hot tub.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Department Head Quarters</title>
      <para>The DH quarters are located in a ring around deck 4. These are smaller than the XOs quarters and are divided into two areas; a living and work area and a sleeping area. The living and work area holds a medium-sized couch, a desk and workstation with table. The bedroom holds a single queen-sized bed, bathroom and single person sized hot tub.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Junior Officer Quarters</title>
      <para>The JO Quarters are located all along decks 5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 11, 16, 17, 18, 19 and 20 in the saucer, as well as a smaller number on decks 25, 27, 35, 36, 44 and 45 in the forward section of the engineering hull. These quarters hold a small living and work area with two chairs, a desk and work station with table. The bedroom holds a twin-sized bed and stand up sonic shower stall.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Non-commissioned Crew Quarters</title>
      <para>These quarters are almost the same size as the JO quarters. They house a combination living, work, and bedroom/sonic shower stall area. They hold a small corner table that doubles as a work area, as well as a twin-sized bed against the wall. They are located along the middle section of decks 27, 28, 35, 36, 44 and 45, as well as a few in the saucer on decks 8, 10 and 11 in the middle forward areas.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>VIP Quarters</title>
      <para>The VIP Quarters are the same size and set-up as the COs quarters. There are twelve of these rooms arrayed along decks 6 and 7. These quarters can be configured for any environment as required for the visiting VIPs.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>General Guest Quarters</title>
      <para>The general guest quarters are the same size and set-up as the JO quarters. There are 25 of these quarters arrayed between decks 4, 5 and 12 in the saucer as well as another 25 in the engineering hull on decks 34 and 35. These quarters can be configured for any environment as required for visiting people.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	  <title>Family Quarters</title>
      <para>These are quarters sized the same as a Department Head's quarters but set-up instead to house up to a four occupant family. They are located on decks 15 and 16 of the saucer and 23 and 24 of the engineering hull.</para>
  </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Auxiliary Spacecraft Systems</title>
      <para>The Mythology class holds four shuttle bays. Shuttle Bay 1 is located on the rearward area of decks 2, 3, and 4 of the saucer. Bays 2 and 3 are located on the neck slope of the engineering hull on decks 29 and 30. Bay 4 is located on the underside of the engineering hull near the aft section of the ship located on decks 43, 44, and 45.</para>
	  <para>A side note in the development of the Mythology class was the creation and deployment of the newer Longevity class runabout.</para>
	  <para>Bay 1 holds the following auxiliary craft:</para>
	  <simplelist>
		<member>4 Armadillo class shuttles</member>
        <member>2 Longevity class runabouts</member>
	  </simplelist>
	  <para>Bay 2 holds the following auxiliary craft:</para>
	  <simplelist>
		<member>2 Armadillo class shuttles</member>
        <member>5 Workbees</member>
	  </simplelist>
	  <para>Bay 3 holds the following auxiliary craft:</para>
	  <simplelist>
		<member>4 Armadillo class shuttles</member>
        <member>2 Longevity class runabouts</member>
	  </simplelist>
	  <para>Bay 4 holds the following auxiliary craft:</para>
	  <simplelist>
		<member>4 Longevity class runabouts</member>
	  </simplelist>
	  <para>Because of its mission of peace and exploration the Mythology is not designed to house fighters in these bays.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Technical Specifications</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Dimensions and Structure</title>    
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Length</term>
        <listitem><para>700 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Beam (Width)</term>
        <listitem><para>450 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Height</term>
        <listitem><para>216 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Decks</term>
        <listitem><para>45</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Crew Complement</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Officers and Crew</term>
        <listitem><para>900</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Family and Civilian Personnel</term>
        <listitem><para>100</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Visiting Personnel</term>
        <listitem><para>100 (without modules)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Evacuation Limit</term>
        <listitem><para>10,000</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>      
    <variablelist>
      <title>Computer Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Core</term>
        <listitem><para>Isolinear data storage core with bio-neural processing x2, Isolinear data storage and processing core x1</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Operating System</term>
        <listitem><para>Starfleet Library Computer Access and Retrieval System (LCARS) 7.0</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>User Interface</term>
        <listitem><para>MAJEL OS</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Add-On Software Suites</term>
        <listitem><para>RSUEP (Really Stupid User Error Prevention)</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>UHPAVS (Upgraded Hacking Prevention and Anti Virus Scanner)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>        
    <variablelist>
      <title>Warp Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Power Plant</term>
        <listitem><para>One 7,912+ cochrane MARA core, feeding two nacelles</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Cruising Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>Warp 6.8</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum Sustainable Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>Warp 9.6</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximum  Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>Warp 9.98 (12 hours)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Emergency Velocity</term>
        <listitem><para>Warp 9.99</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Impulse Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Full Impulse</term>
        <listitem><para>0.25c</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Acceleration</term>
        <listitem><para>75 seconds</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Deceleration</term>
        <listitem><para>115 seconds</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Defensive Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)</term>
        <listitem><para>2,150 MegaWatts</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate</term>
        <listitem><para>5.84 x 10^5 kilowatts</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Offensive Systems</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Torpedoes</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Torpedo Tubes</term>
              <listitem><para>2x Type 4 Torpedo Tubes</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Standard Payload (total)</term>
              <listitem><para>145x photon torpedoes</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>50x quantum torpedoes</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>145x probes</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>5x tricobalt devices</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Phasers</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>10x Type-X Phaser Strips</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Deck Layout</title>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 1</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Bridge</member>
        <member>Conference Room</member>
        <member>Ready Room</member>
        <member>Holo-crew Projection Support Systems</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
    <section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 2</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Bridge Support Systems</member>
        <member>Diplomatic Hall</member>
		<member>Holographic Crew Projection Support Systems</member>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 1 Launch Control</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 3</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Holo-Crew Projection Support Systems</member>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 1 Storage</member>
        <member>CO's Quarters</member>
        <member>XO's Quarters</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 4</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 1</member>
        <member>Department Head Quarters</member>
        <member>General Guest Quarters</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 5</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Docking Ring (Port/Starboard)</member>
        <member>General Guest Quarters</member>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>Primary Mission Module Housing</member>
        <member>Upper Cargo Bay 1 and 2 (port/starboard)</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 6</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>VIP Quarters</member>
        <member>Lower Cargo Bay 1 and 2 (port/starboard)</member>
        <member>Primary Mission Module Housing</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 7</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>VIP Quarters</member>
        <member>Primary Mission Module Housing</member>
        <member>Phaser Array</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 8</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>Upper Primary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Control Room 1</member>
        <member>Primary Mission Module Housing</member>
        <member>Transporter Room 1</member>
        <member>Transporter Room 2</member>
        <member>Phaser Array Service and Support Systems</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 9</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Primary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Service and Storage Room 1</member>
        <member>Transporter Room 3</member>
        <member>Transporter Room 4</member>
        <member>Sensor Pallets</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 10</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Primary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Core Service and Storage Room 2</member>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>Holding Cell 1</member>
        <member>Holding Cell 2</member>
        <member>Holding Cell Support Systems</member>
        <member>Backup Sensor Pallets</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 11</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>General Guest Quarters</member>
        <member>Counselling Suite</member>
        <member>Lower Primary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Primary Computer Control Room 2</member>
        <member>Sensor Pallets</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 12</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Sickbay 1</member>
        <member>Sickbay 2</member>
        <member>CMO's Office</member>
        <member>Sickbay Support Systems</member>
        <member>Shield Generator</member>
        <member>Backup Sensor Pallets</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 13</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>CSO's Office</member>
        <member>General Science Labs 1-3</member>
        <member>Exobiology Labs 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Astrometrics Labs 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Planetary Science Lab 1</member>
        <member>Shield Generator</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 14</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>COS's Office</member>
        <member>Security Training Room 1</member>
        <member>Upper Armoury Storage</member>
        <member>General Science Labs 4-6</member>
        <member>Planetary Science Lab 2</member>
        <member>Cybernetics Labs 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Upper Stellar Cartography</member>
        <member>Arboretum 1</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 15</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Lower Armoury Storage</member>
        <member>Security Training Room 2</member>
        <member>Lower Stellar Cartography</member>
        <member>Family Quarters</member>
        <member>Schooling Facility / Nursery 1</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 16</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>Family Quarters</member>
        <member>Holosuites 1-5</member>
        <member>Upper Holodecks 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Schooling Facility / Nursery 2</member>
        <member>Small Tractor Emitters</member>
        <member>Tractor Emitter Support Systems</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 17</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Gym</member>
        <member>17 Forward</member>
        <member>Upper Kitchen and Support Systems</member>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>Lower Holodecks 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Shield Generator</member>
        <member>Turbolift Maintenance Room 1</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 18</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Upper Recreation Hall</member>
        <member>18 Forward</member>
        <member>Lower Kitchen and Support Systems</member>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>Emergency Transporter Rooms 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Upper Impulse Engines 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Impulse Engine Service Rooms 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Upper Deuterium Storage Tanks 1 and 2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 19</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Lower Recreation Hall</member>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>Civilian/Emergency Shelter Areas</member>
        <member>Impulse Engines 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Deuterium Storage Tanks 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Deuterium Fill Ports 1 and 2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 20</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>Civilian/Emergency Shelter Areas</member>
        <member>General Purpose Area 1</member>
        <member>Saucer Modular Areas 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Lower Impulse Engines 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Lower Deuterium Storage Areas 1 and 2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 21</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>General Purpose Area 2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 22</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>General Purpose Area 3</member>
        <member>Holographic Crew Support Systems</member>
        <member>Sensor Pallets</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 23</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Family Quarters</member>
        <member>Schooling Facility / Nursery 3</member>
        <member>Transporter Room 5</member>
        <member>Upper Tertiary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Tertiary Computer Control Room 1</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 24</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Transporter Room 6</member>
        <member>Tertiary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Tertiary Computer Core Service and Storage Room</member>
        <member>Sensor Pallets</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 25</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>Lower Tertiary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Tertiary Computer Control Room 2</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 26</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>General Science Labs 7-10</member>
        <member>Arboretum 2</member>
        <member>Science Lab Support Systems</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 27</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>Upper Secondary Docking Port</member>
        <member>Shield Generator</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 28</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>Emergency Transporter Rooms 3 and 4 Support Systems</member>
        <member>Lower Secondary Docking Port</member>
        <member>Secondary Docking Port Service and Support System</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 29</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Emergency Transporter Rooms 3 and 4</member>
        <member>Upper Shuttle Bays 2 and 3</member>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 2 and 3 Control Room</member>
        <member>Upper Deflector Dish</member>
        <member>Upper Deflector Dish Control</member>
        <member>Deflector Dish Support Systems</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 30</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 2 and 3</member>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 2 and 3 Support Systems</member>
        <member>Secondary and Tertiary Mission Module Housing</member>
        <member>Upper Secondary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Secondary Computer Control Room 1</member>
        <member>Deflector Dish</member>
        <member>Deflector Dish Support Systems</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 31</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Secondary and Tertiary Mission Module Housing</member>
        <member>Secondary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Secondary Computer Core Service and Storage Room 1</member>
        <member>Upper Machine Shop</member>
        <member>Deflector Dish</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 32</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Secondary and Tertiary Mission Module Housing</member>
        <member>Secondary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Secondary Computer Core Service and Storage Room 2</member>
        <member>Machine Shop</member>
        <member>Deflector Dish</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 33</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Secondary and Tertiary Mission Module Housing</member>
        <member>Lower Secondary Computer Core</member>
        <member>Secondary Computer Control Room 2</member>
        <member>Lower Machine Shop</member>
        <member>Lower Deflector Dish</member>
        <member>Lower Deflector Dish Control</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 34</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Machine Shop Storage</member>
        <member>Turbolift Maintenance Room 2</member>
        <member>Shield Generator</member>
        <member>Sensor Pallets</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 35</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>Torpedo Control Room</member>
        <member>Upper Probe Storage</member>
        <member>Upper Torpedo Casing Storage</member>
        <member>Backup Sensor Pallet</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 36</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>Torpedo Launchers 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Torpedo Service and Support Systems</member>
        <member>Torpedo Casing Storage</member>
        <member>Probe Storage</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 37</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Upper Holodecks 3-5</member>
        <member>Civilian/Emergency Shelter Areas</member>
        <member>Lower Torpedo Casing Storage</member>
        <member>Lower Probe Storage</member>
        <member>Large Tractor Emitter</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 38</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Civilian/Emergency Shelter Areas</member>
        <member>Lower Holodecks 3-5</member>
        <member>Arboretum 3</member>
        <member>Tractor Emitter Support Systems</member>
        <member>Sensor Pallet</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 39</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Sickbay 3</member>
        <member>Sickbay Support Systems</member>
        <member>Backup Sensor Pallet</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 40</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Upper Main Engineering</member>
        <member>Upper Warp Core</member>
        <member>Compression Relay Jump Core Module</member>
        <member>Holding Cells 3 and 4</member>
        <member>Holding Cell Support Systems</member>
        <member>Warp Core Ejection Hatch</member>
        <member>Warp Core Pneumatic Manual Ejection Control Room</member>
        <member>Upper Deuterium Storage Tanks 3 and 4</member>
        <member>Upper Anti-Matter Storage Tanks</member>
        <member>Anti-Matter Storage Ejection Hatches</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 41</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Main Engineering</member>
        <member>CE's Office</member>
        <member>Engineering Maintenance Labs 1 and 2</member>
        <member>Warp Core</member>
        <member>Warp Core Support Systems</member>
        <member>Holographic Crew Support Systems</member>
        <member>Deuterium Storage Tanks 3 and 4</member>
        <member>Deuterium Fill Ports 3 and 4</member>
        <member>Anti-Matter Storage Tanks</member>
        <member>Compression Relay Jump Core Module</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 42</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Engineering Maintenance Labs 3 and 4</member>
        <member>Lower Warp Core</member>
        <member>Lower Deuterium Storage Tanks 3 and 4</member>
        <member>Anti-Matter Storage Tanks</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 43</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Upper Shuttle Bay 4</member>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 4 Control Room</member>
        <member>Secondary Engineering Support Systems</member>
        <member>Pneumatic Manual Ejection System Mechanism</member>
        <member>Lower Anti-Matter Storage Tanks</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 44</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 4</member>
        <member>Cargo Bays 3 and 4</member>
        <member>Tertiary Docking Hatch</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
	<section role="Deck">
      <title>Deck 45</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member>Junior Officers' Quarters</member>
        <member>NCO Quarters</member>
        <member>Shuttle Bay 4 Support and Storage Systems</member>
        <member>Large Tractor Emitter</member>
        <member>Tractor Emitter Support Systems</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Ships of the Class</title>
      <para>Mythology class ships are named for legends and mythologies of cultures from around the Federation and its allies.</para>
    <simplelist role="ShipList">
      <member role="PC">
        <productname>Mythology</productname>
        <productnumber>98711</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Mythos</productname>
        <productnumber>98712</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Legend</productname>
        <productnumber>98713</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Lore</productname>
        <productnumber>98714</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Cthulu</productname>
        <productnumber>98715</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Nessie</productname>
        <productnumber>98716</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Sasquatch</productname>
        <productnumber>98717</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Unicorn</productname>
        <productnumber>98718</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Cerberus</productname>
        <productnumber>98719</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Wyvern</productname>
        <productnumber>98720</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Pixie</productname>
        <productnumber>98721</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Imp</productname>
        <productnumber>98722</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="PC">
		<productname>Eden</productname>
        <productnumber>98723</productnumber>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
	<para>The following ships are commissioned and held in reserve for use in NPC only status and may be reused as needed by gamemasters.</para>
	<simplelist role="ShipList">
      <member role="NPC">
        <productname>Gre'thor</productname>
        <productnumber>98724</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="NPC">
		<productname>Fek'lhr</productname>
        <productnumber>98725</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="NPC">
		<productname>Kuvah'magh</productname>
        <productnumber>98726</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="NPC">
		<productname>Qui'tu</productname>
        <productnumber>98727</productnumber>
      </member>
      <member role="NPC">
		<productname>Sha Ka Ree</productname>
        <productnumber>98728</productnumber>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
      <para>The Mythology class is one of the largest deep space exploration classes fielded by the Federation in recent years. It is designed to handle any number of possible mission profiles, but does not specialize in any one category. Its primary assets are adaptability, endurance and survivability where other ships may not be able to venture. With its co-designed construction the Mythology embodies the best that the Federation and her allies have to offer for the years ahead.</para>
  </section>
</article>
