<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="techmanual.xslt"?>
<article class="specification" id="nimitz">
	<title>Nimitz-class</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup role="Maintainer">
			<author>
				<firstname>Randy</firstname>
				<surname>McCullick</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Primary">
			<author>
				<firstname>Randy</firstname>
				<surname>McCullick</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Original">
			<author>
				<firstname>Randy</firstname>
				<surname>McCullick</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword role="service">PC</keyword>
			<keyword role="category">Dreadnought</keyword>
			<keyword role="variant">Heavy</keyword>
			<keyword role="mark">II</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>29 November 2003</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Engineering Director Barret Vogtman</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<sect1>
		<title>History and Mission Overview</title>
		<para>The original Nimitz-class was designed after Wolf 359 to give Starfleet a more military vessel than the Galaxy-class. It served well into the Dominion War. However, the Nimitz was beginning to show it's obsolescence in the war, and it was obvious a new design would be needed. The Nimitz-class was recalled. Finding the essence of the design still serviceable, Starfleet decided a "refit" was needed, much like the one the Constitution- and Excelsior-classes had decades earlier.</para>
		<para>The original Nimitz design team was brought back in to redo the ship from the superstructure up. Advancements that were developed for the Defiant- , Intrepid- , Prometheus- , and Sovereign-class projects were incorporated into the new Nimitz design.</para>
		<para>Thus, the Nimitz-class refit is a modification of the original Nimitz designs, incorporating the latest in technologies, as well as incorporating Starfleet's new special weaponry that had been in development since Wolf 359.</para>
		<para>The function of the Nimitz is to serve as follows:</para>
		<simplelist>
			<member>Provide a highly defensible Tactical "Flagship" during Fleet Actions.</member>
			<member>Provide an orbiting departure ship and ground support for planet side military operations.</member>
			<member>Provide a heavy duty patrol vessel on Starfleet's most dangerous borders, as well as a search and destroy vessel for the Federations more heavily armed and dangerous internal threats (such as the Orion Syndicate).</member>
		</simplelist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Structure and Construction</title>
		<para>The Nimitz-R is a huge behemoth of a vessel, almost a kilometer and a half in length. In appearance, it resembles a giant Sovereign-class with a few notable exceptions.</para>
		<para>The first of which is that on the rear-top of the primary hull (behind the main bridge), there is a third Warp Nacelle.</para>
		<para>Secondly, the rear of the vessel ends abruptly, housing a second dish array, similar in design to the main deflector.</para>
		<para>Finally, the Primary Hull of the Nimitz appears bloated compared with that of the Galaxy or Sovereign.</para>
		<para>Once you get closer, other things are noticeable.</para>
		<para>First off, there are 12 large tube-like mountings on the Primary Hull, 6 dorsal, 6 ventral. These house the Main Phaser cannons.</para>
		<para>Secondly, there is a large, square, armored shuttle bay door on the front of the secondary hull, above the Main Dish and torpedo array. This is the forward launch door of the hangar system. The aft side of this deck has a more traditional "Clamshell" door that is seen on the Constitution-Refit and the Sovereign-classes.</para>
		<para>Thirdly, the skin of the Nimitz is a bit of an odd color for a Starfleet vessel, a dusky grayish black. This is due to the quantoberilium shell grown over the hull. Quantoberilium is a crystalline substance that works like Ablative Armor, but is slightly more durable, and takes longer to evaporate under direct sustained fire. Quantoberilium can also regenerate from minor damage, but moderate or severe damage to the shell will require replacing the effected panels and a slight growth period.</para>
		<para>Finally, the next thing noticeable is that the hull is not smooth like on most starships, but seems to bulge at various points with the various weapon packages giving it a very warty appearance.</para>
		<para>The Nimitz only has three windowed locations: Deck 2 Forward, Deck 12 Aft, and on the bottom at Deck 48.</para>
		<para>The Nimitz is capable of Saucer separation, functioning as two independent Warp Capable vessels. The Saucer has a maximum speed of Warp 4.5 and a cruising speed of Warp 3.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Sensors</title>
			<para>The Nimitz has limited Science systems, being a mostly combat vessel. Its long-range sensors have a 4 LY high, 10 LY low ranges on extended scanning. Its lateral sensors are mediocre, enough to categorize another vessel, analyze a new weapon or technology, or to do a preliminary survey on an unknown celestial body. Any detailed analysis has to be done by another ship.</para>
			<para>However, the ship's navigational sensors are top of the line, providing fast and detailed information for the navigator. These high gain sensors are especially useful for high warp navigation, or wave motion jumps. These feed into a Sirius Cybernetics Corporation class 3 navigational computer separate from the main computer. However, if the computer is damaged or inoperable, the main computer can take over the load.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Computer Systems</title>
			<para>The Nimitz contains 4 of the Sirius Cybernetics Corporation's latest P10 computer cores, along with bioneural systems, the best Starfleet can offer. It has 2 in the primary hull, 2 in the secondary Hull. These systems run an LCARS derivative for the time being, though Starfleet is looking into alternatives. These computers are powerful enough to contain a low-grade A.I. It is a semi-sentient A.I. and S.S.C. has given in several default personalities that can be chosen for it.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Navigational Dish/Rear Array</title>
			<para>Both the navigational deflectors and the aft dish array help augment the long-range sensors. Designed for multitasking purposes, these devices can handle the additional power load of the Deflector, the sensors, tractor beams and much more. While each system is capable of independent function, normally their emissions are joined into these arrays to boost gain and power, as well as minimize emission signatures.</para>
			<para>Also, there is a small non-dish "micro deflector" on the front of the Primary Hull. This deflector is used only if the Primary hull is in Warp after a separation.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Expansion Labs</title>
			<para>Expansion support for the Nimitz can include two mission specific science labs, but are not included with the default Nimitz package. The can be installed at a drydock with industrial-grade transporters at the cost of some of the spare crew quarters.</para>
		</sect2>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Warp Propulsion Systems</title>
		<para>The Nimitz uses three of the latest Leeding Engines Inc. Type 8 Nacelles, uprated for Maximum Warp Efficiency. Cruising speed for these new space/time friendly nacelles is Warp 8, with Maximum sustainable speed at Warp 9.6. Maximum overall speed is Warp 9.986. </para>
		<para>The Nimitz's original space compression technology is still in place. The type 7/M Duocore powers the main engines of the ship, providing 1900+ Cochranes of Warp Energy to power the beast. This device is essentially two twin 1000+ Cochrane cores structurally merged into one unit.</para>
		<para>The Primary hull also has a small 400+ Cochrane Auxiliary Warp Core for running the ship in separation mode.</para>
		<para></para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Wave Motion Engine</title>
			<para>The Nimitz now comes standard equipped with a Wave Motion Engine. This FTL system works by "diving" the ship directly into subspace instead of wrapping subspace around the ship. This is done by using a compressed mix of Tachyon, Tetryon and Chronotrons to temporarily "rift" space/time. This essentially folds space so that the ship can travel light years in a matter of minutes, somewhat similar in effect to that of a wormhole. This jump has to be calculated exactly or else the results could be disastrous. Some or all of the ship could be lost in subspace for all eternity, or can emerge in the wrong space/time position (say, the nucleus of a star), causing damage or destruction to the ship.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
		<para>Standard Impulse Engines are located on in the Primary Hull (Aft P/S) and in the secondary Hull (Aft Amidships). These are Leeding Engines Class 8 Drives and have a limit of .75c sustained /.95c theoretical max. It takes 3 seconds for the Nimitz to go from dead stop to full impulse, and an additional 7 seconds for the Nimitz to reach Maximum Impulse.</para>
		<para>The Nimitz uses a Reaction Control System similar to that of the other starships like the Enterprise-D.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Tactical Systems</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Defensive Shields</title>
			<para>The Nimitz employs the most powerful shields used on Starfleet vessels today. The shield generators are capable of handling a maximum continuous graviton load of 4082 Megawatts, and is capable of a maximum energy dissipation rate of 8.2125*10^5 kilowatts These shields refresh every 30 seconds and at that time the shield frequency harmonics are randomly recalibrated automatically by the ship's AI.</para>
			<para>In addition, the Nimitz uses the new ESS Regenerative Shielding system that was designed for the Prometheus-class and is also used on the Sovereign-class. This system uses an energy absorption cell to divert power back into the shielding system once damaged. This allows the shields to regenerate at a rate of 22.4 MW of Graviton Load per second until fully regenerated.</para>

		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Phaser Systems</title>
			<para>The Nimitz has benefited greatly from the research implemented on Sovereign- and Defiant-class vessels and sports four Type XII Pulse Phaser Cannon Arrays. These arrays are really pulse only in the fact that their configuration matches that of the Pulse Phasers used on the Defiant, the Emitters, however, are a Type XII as used on the Sovereign and these guns need a few seconds to recharge before firing another shot. These phasers are capable of 5.75 MW of maximum output per single emitter.</para>
			<para>Each Array consists of three cannons and is located on the front of the Primary Hull (2 dorsal, 2 ventral). The cannons are directly grafted to the hull, which has a "turntable" design allowing for a 170-degree firing range. However, the conveyer is slow, needing a few seconds to retarget. In addition, conveyer freezer is a key problem once hull damage is taken. Starfleet has given this system the go, but is looking to upgrade later with improvements. The guns can be controlled in unison from a Bridge or independently from 4 gunnery rooms on their respective decks.</para>
			<para>Taking the rest of the firing arc not covered by the main guns is a series of 10 standard Type XII phaser arrays, of the same make as the Sovereign. These are located on the Aft of the primary hull (D/V, P/S) as well as additional arrays on the hard point connect, the neck (above the hanger, facing forward), the port and starboard sides, the nacelles and the aft of the secondary hull. This finishes off the 720-degree range. These phasers are capable of 5.6 Megawatts of maximum output per single emitter.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Torpedo Systems</title>
			<para>The Primary hull of the Nimitz has 6 basic torpedo launchers. These launchers allow for a five torpedo Spread and are located exactly 60-degree from each other along the outer rim of the hull. In addition, the secondary hull houses 2 advanced launchers allowing a 10 torpedo maximum spread. These are located below the hangar on the front, and at the base of the rear of the secondary hull. The Nimitz stocks 200 quantum torpedoes and 600 photon torpedoes, with the ability to manufacture more of the photon torpedo casings and charge them from the anti-matter consumables on board. Due to the rare nature of the materials needed to construct quantum torpedoes, these cannot be replicated.</para>
			<para>The Nimitz has 15 probes on board rigged for remote detonation. These probes have look like standard Class I probes, but are actually Type DI probes, and once remote activated to go hot will lock onto it's target and detonate within range, doing approximately a Mark VIII torpedo's equivalent in damage.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Interphasic Systems</title>
			<para>The Nimitz employs the Mark III interphasic generator. This generator doesn't work through phase-cloak technology like its predecessors. Instead, this device generates a quantum phase variance within the ship, cause the ship to "slip" between dimensional planes. The phase variance is not complete enough to totally switch dimensions, and as a result, the ship is "stuck" between dimensions, until the device is shut off. As a result the ship no longer appears to register on sensors and can travel in this ghostly state. However, the ship does have problems using its sensors while in this state. Because it doesn't use cloaking technology, this device does not violate the Treaty of Algernon.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Holo-Generator</title>
			<para>The Nimitz has a total of six hologenerator systems on the primary Hull. These generators use a combination of holotechnology and sensor baffling to create either overlaps on the ship, making it identify to sensors as a different vessel, or to create fake support vessels outside the ship. The hologenerator can keep track of up to six separate images. The hologeneration system provides the visual overlay for naked eye checks, while the sensor baffling puts out a false sensor signal that will misidentify the ship(s) as whatever is currently programmed. The sensors on the Nimitz will record attempts by other ships to strike the ship with weapons, calculate damage, and adjust the holoimages and sensor readings accordingly.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Wave Motion Gun</title>
			<para>The Wave Motion Gun works on the same principle as the Wave Motion Engine; that of compressing and emitting particles. Instead of using a little of the ships power to compress tachyons and chronotrons, however, it uses ALL the ships power and compresses Gravitons. The Wave Motion Gun takes approximately 1 minute to charge, during which the ship is reduced to reserve power only, as main AND auxiliary power is being channeled into the gun. The compress gravitons are then fired though the Main Deflector Array, and straight at a target. The ship takes several seconds after firing to reestablish all of its systems. Between this the ship is helpless and cannot return fire, move (other than RCS "targeting") or use shields. Because of this, use of this gun is a very risky gamble. However, as the beam itself is made of gravitons, shields can only strengthen it, and the gravitational forces that compose this beam are equivalent to a Black Hole, crushing anything in its path. The ship itself is held in place by the inertia of firing such a weapon held in check by the actual force of the beam itself.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Command and Support Systems</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Bridge</title>
			<para>The Nimitz-class has four bridges. There are manned at all times in the event of the loss of one or more during combat. These bridges are located as follows:</para>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Main Bridge: Deck 1  </member>
				<member>Battle Bridge #1: Deck 24 (Lowest point of the primary hull)  </member>
				<member>Battle Bridge #2: Deck 13 (hard point connect) </member>
				<member>Battle Bridge #3: Deck 48, aft  </member>
			</simplelist>
			<para>In the event that all 4 bridges are destroyed, the ship can be run from Main Engineering.  </para>
			<para>The Main Bridge follows the standard Starfleet style; a central command seat surrounded by various support stations. The command chair is on a raised platform in the center of the bridge. In this instance, the "horseshoe" wraps all the way around to the edges of the command chair, essentially cocooning the captain. On the inner part of the horseshoe are various tactical displays and readouts, as well as a manual steering column, dual joystick configuration. On the Port side of the "horseshoe" is the communications station. This station is designed to take vocal intraship communications off of Ops and extraship Communications off of Mission Ops freeing them for more duties. Regulations state that this station need only be manned in an emergency, however certain COs may decide to have the station manned at all times. On the starboard of the "horseshoe" is the Executive Officer's station. Also called the "Redundant" station, this station can mimic the function of any other bridge station with the push of a button. This is used in the event another bridge station becomes inoperable. The rear of the bridge has the following stations: Science, Mission Ops, Engineering 1, and Engineering 2. As science does not play a critical role on the Nimitz, it has been reduced to one station while Engineering has been given a second station, one devoted completely to maintenance of Tactical Systems. Finally the front of the bridge contains three stations, from port to starboard: Ops, Helm, and Navigation. They are arranged in an "open box" formation with Helm facing the front view screen.</para>
			<para>Secondary Bridges have a similar configuration, but tend to be slightly smaller in size. </para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Security</title>
			<para>Security on the Nimitz is extensive. The Nimitz hosts 10 brig complexes; 4 in the main security section on Deck 10, and 6 in "the pit" on Deck 45. In addition, the cargo holds in Deck 45 can be converted to additional prisoner storage, provided there's nothing in them. The anti-intruder and force field lockdown systems are all rated to Starfleet's current standards and beyond.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Communications</title>
			<para>As the Nimitz is an important piece of military hardware, communications on the Nimitz is top-of the line and fully encrypted. In addition to main communications, there is a Holo-communications system in an alcove on the main bridge. In addition, there is an emergency communications console off of Main Engineering in the secondary hull.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Utility Systems</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Cargo Bays</title>
			<para>The Nimitz has several cargo bays and can hold up to 132,000 cubic meters of cargo. As stated previously, some of these holds if emptied can be converted to security cells. Key cargo bays are on Decks 3, 13, 15, and 45.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Tractor Beam Systems</title>
			<para>The Nimitz employs Starfleet's current maximum power tractor beams for towing large vessels. Instead of being on a separate emitter, these beams are routed through the navigational arrays for better control. These beams can tow 7,500,000 M.T. @ 1 km through 1 M.T. at 20,000km. In addition, they can be refined down to exerting pressure down to 1m2. The main hangar has Beta level Tractors with power ranging from 1,000,000 MT at 1km to 250kg at 20,000km.Shuttle bays 1-3 have Alpha Level Tractors for towing in small vessels. These range from 500,000mt at 1km to 100 kg at 20,000km.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Transporter Systems</title>
			<para>The Nimitz employs 6 standard transporters, having 4 in the primary hull and 2 in the secondary hull. The Nimitz also has 6 emergency transporters, 2 in the primary hull, and 4 in the secondary hull. Finally, the Nimitz has 4 cargo transporters, 2 on Deck 15, 2 on Deck 45. All pads are security locked and required command authorization before they can be activated, this lockdown is overridden in the event of an evacuation alert, or if the auto-destruct is active.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Industrial Replicator Systems</title>
			<para>Due to the frequent necessity of repairs on combat vessels, the Nimitz has a network of small industrial replicators located throughout Engineering in the primary and secondary hall. These are used to replicate parts and equipment needed to perform on the spot repairs. The Nimitz also hosts 3 industrial grade replicators, 1 in Main Engineering in the primary hull, and 2 in Main Engineering in the secondary hull. These room size replicators are used to replicate large components (like hull plating) and other raw materials too large to be replicated in a regular replicator. With these a Nimitz can stay self-sustained for up to 2 years unless a system with a rare material is damaged, or a main system is utterly destroyed.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Crew Support Systems</title>
		<para>The Nimitz uses standard Starfleet turbolifts and Jeffries tubes, and also incorporates a series of access ladders and hatches approximately 250m from each other on each deck. Each deck is segmented, and can be isolated by emergency force fields or in some cases by emergency doors.</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Sickbay</title>
			<para>The Nimitz class incorporates a top-flight sickbay center only outdone by the Ogawa-class. The entire inner part of Deck 11 is a Medical Bay, excluding the lift shafts and the computer cores. Another Med Bay is housed in Deck 35, used in crisis situations. The Nimitz is declared a first responder to any Class 1 Emergency and therefore must be capable of handling a medical crisis. Up until this point, the Nimitz had not incorporated an EMH on its design. However, the designer caved with the refit and the Nimitz-R now has a Mark IV EMH in its sickbay. Sickbay, Bridge, Engineering, Shuttle Bays, and Hangars, have been outfitted with Holo-emitters to use in this situation. In a future upgrade, Starfleet is considering rigging the holo-emitter system ship wide at a later date.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Quarters</title>
			<para>The Nimitz holds 2,115 officers and crew standard. This frequently breaks down to approximately 25/75% Officer/crew ratio. Because of this high demand for Crew volume, the Nimitz has spartan crew surroundings. Crewmen and junior officers are lodged in bunk style quarters, and the senior officers get their own one room cabin. Families are not allowed on the Nimitz. These cabins are the only modular part of the Nimitz design, and they can be reconfigured at any drydock with Industrial Transporters. This does allow for adding removing quarters with unique environments. Each crew and guest quarter has a replicator in it, as do all major ship areas.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Recreational Facilities and Necessities</title>
			<para>Recreational facilities on the Nimitz are limited. Facilities are limited to 2 personal room sized holosuites and a main lounge. These are located on Deck 12. A Nimitz can add more recreation facilities at the cost of crew quarters. There is one small lounge on each deck, fully equipped with a replicator, usually right next to a unisex bathroom. Bathrooms are located every 200 meters on each deck.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Auxiliary Spacecraft Systems</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Hangar</title>
			<para>The Nimitz houses a main fighter hanger on Decks 27-29, right above the main defector dish. This is a through deck hanger, allowing fighters to takeoff/land from either the front or rear. The Nimitz maintains a squadron of 12 fighters, the grade of which varies per ship.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Shuttlebay</title>
			<para>Also, the Nimitz carries 3 shuttle bays, the main one on decks 2-3 and the 2 extra ones on Decks 13-14 of the secondary hull. The main shuttle bay holds 6 shuttles normally, and can launch 2 shuttles simultaneously. The auxiliary shuttle bays can hold 2 each and can launch 1 shuttle at a time.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Technical Specifications</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Dimensions and Structure</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Length">1,412 meters</member>
				<member role="Beam (Width)">850.2 meters</member>
				<member role="Height">550.3 meters</member>
				<member role="Decks">50</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Crew Complement</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Officers and Crew">2,115</member>
				<member role="Visiting Personnel">100</member>
				<member role="Maximum Evacuation Limit">50,000</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Computer Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Core">4 Serius Cyberetics Corporation Polytronic 10 cores</member>
				<member role="Operating System">Starfleet Library Computer Access and Retrieval System (LCARS)</member>
				<member role="User Interface">EDDIE or Custom SSC Compatible A.I.</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Warp Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Power Plant">One 1900+ cochrane XFY Duocore (2 1000+cochrane cores) feeding three nacelles (2 nacelles in seperation), one  400+ Cochrane Auxiliary Warp Core feeding one nacelle (Seperation only)</member>
				<member role="Cruising Velocity">Warp 8</member>
				<member role="Maximum Sustainable Velocity">Warp 9.6</member>
				<member role="Maximum Velocity">Warp 9.986 (12 hours)</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Impulse Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Full Impulse">0.25c</member>
				<member role="Accellerate">10 seconds</member>
				<member role="Decellerate">20 seconds</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Defensive Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)">4082 MegaWatts</member>
				<member role="Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate">8.2125*10^5 kilowatts</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Offensive Systems</title>
			<simplelist role="Torpedoes">
				<member role="Torpedo Tubes">6 basic launchers, 2 Advanced Launchers</member>
				<member role="Standard Payload (total)">600 photon torpedoes, 200 quantum torpedoes</member>
			</simplelist>
			<simplelist role="Phasers">
				<member>11 Type-XII Phaser Arrays</member>
				<member>12 Type XII Pulse Phaser Cannons in 4 sets</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Deck Layout</title>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 1</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Bridge</member>
				<member>Ready Room</member>
				<member>Conference Room</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 2</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>CO's Quarters</member>
				<member>VIP Quarters</member>
				<member>Main Shuttle Bay (top)</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 3</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Sen. Officer's Quarters</member>
				<member>Cargo Bays 1-2</member>
				<member>Main Shuttle Bay (Bottom)</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 4</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Officers Quarters</member>
				<member>Main Shuttle Bay (Maintenance)</member>
				<member>Gunnery Room 1</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 5</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Officers Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 6</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Officers Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 7</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Computer Core</member>
				<member>Junior Officers Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 8</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Junior Officers Quarters</member>
				<member>Gunnery Room 2</member>
				<member>Computer Core</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 9</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Computer Core</member>
				<member>Junior Officers Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 10</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Main Security</member>
				<member>Armory</member>
				<member>Brigs</member>
				<member>Computer Core</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 11</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Sickbay</member>
				<member>Impulse Engines</member>
				<member>Lateral Sensor Array</member>
				<member>Matter Storage</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 12</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>12-Aft (lounge)</member>
				<member>Holosuites 1-2</member>
				<member>Rec. Room</member>
				<member>Transporters 1-2</member>
				<member>Primary Hull Engineering</member>
				<member>Impulse Engines</member>
				<member>Aux. Warp Core</member>
				<member>Torpedo Bays 3-8</member>
				<member>Hologeneration Matrix</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 13</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Industrial replicators 1-2</member>
				<member>Battle Bridge #2</member>
				<member>Impulse Engines</member>
				<member>Primary Hull Torpedo Storage</member>
				<member>Antimatter Storage</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 14</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Micro-deflector</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 15</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 16</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Gunnery Room 3</member>
				<member>Shuttle Bay 2 and 3</member>
				<member>Cargo Holds 3-4</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 17</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Shuttle Bay 2 and 3 (Maintenance)</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 18</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 19</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 20</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Gunnery Room 4</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Water Tanks</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 21</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Raw Carbon and Silicon Storage for replicators</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 22</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Shield Generators for Primary Hull</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 23</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>SIF and IDF Fields Generators for Primary Hull</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 24</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Battle Bridge #1</member>
				<member>Torpedo Storage</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 25</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Torpedo Storage</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 26</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 27</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Hangar</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 28</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Hangar</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 29</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Hangar</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 30</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Computer Cores 3-4</member>
				<member>Main Forward Torpedo Bay</member>
				<member>Torpedo storage</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 31</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Computer Cores 3-4</member>
				<member>Main Forward Torpedo Bay</member>
				<member>Torpedo storage</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 32</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Main Deflector Dish Begins</member>
				<member>Computer Cores 3-4</member>
				<member>Impulse Engines</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 33</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Computer Cores 3-4</member>
				<member>Emergency Transporters 3-4</member>
				<member>Rear Torpedo Tube</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 34</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Rear Torpedo Tube</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 35</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Aux. Sickbay</member>
				<member>Rear Emitter Dish Begins</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 36</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Deuterium Holds 1-2</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 37</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Deuterium Holds 1-2</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member></member>
				<member></member>
				<member></member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 38</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Deuterium Holds 1-2</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 39</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Deuterium Holds 1-2</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member>Secondary Hull Lateral Sensor Array</member>
				<member></member>
				<member></member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 40</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Main Engineering</member>
				<member>Main M/ARA</member>
				<member>Industrial replicators 3-4</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 41</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Wave Motion Engine/Gun</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
				<member></member>
				<member></member>
				<member></member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 42</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Emergency Transporters 5-6</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 43</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Sensory</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 44</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Battle Bridge #3</member>
				<member>Crew Quarters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 45</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Secondary Brigs 6-10</member>
				<member>Cargo Transporters 3-4</member>
				<member>Cargo Bays</member>
				<member>Rear Def. Dish Ends</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 46</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>SIF And IDF Fields for Secondary Hull</member>
				<member>Engineering</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 47</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Aux and Reserve Power Stations</member>
				<member>Engineering</member>
				<member>Water Tanks</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 48</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Main Deflector Dish Ends</member>
				<member>Shield Generators for Secondary Hull</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 49</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Engineering - Maintenance and Plumbing</member>
				<member>Raw Carbon storage for food replicators</member>
				<member>Raw Silicate storage for industrial replicators</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 role="Deck">
			<title>Deck 50</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member>Anti-hydrogen generators and storage</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Ships of the Class</title>
		<para>The following ships are in cold storage and can be overhauled to current standard.</para>
		<simplelist role="ShipList">
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Andorian</productname>
				<productnumber>2019-D</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Eisenhower</productname>
				<productnumber>82363</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Entente</productname>
				<productnumber>82371</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Federation</productname>
				<productnumber>82365</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Horta</productname>
				<productnumber>82370</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Nimitz</productname>
				<productnumber>82360</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Star Union</productname>
				<productnumber>82366</productnumber>
			</member>
		</simplelist>
		<para>In addition, Starfleet has authorized these two replacement vessels for Nimitzes lost.</para>
		<simplelist role="ShipList">
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Patton</productname>
				<productnumber>92365</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Nelson</productname>
				<productnumber>92364</productnumber>
			</member>
		</simplelist>
		<para>Finally, Starfleet has authorized the following new Nimitzes to be constructed at a later date as needed:</para>
		<simplelist role="ShipList">
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Bolian</productname>
				<productnumber>92366</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Caitian</productname>
				<productnumber>93279</productnumber>
			</member>
			<member role="PC">
				<productname>Star Empire</productname>
				<productnumber>92368</productnumber>
			</member>
		</simplelist>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Conclusion</title>
		<para>The Nimitz is a battle vessel, plain and simple. It is frightening large, frightening powerful, and can take a pounding that would turn other vessels to fine powder. It is up to the Captain and the crew to use this power responsibly in way most conductive to Starfleet business.</para>
	</sect1>
</article>
