<article class="techreport" id="eunix-ce">
	<title>EUNIX-Core Element</title>
	<titleabbrev>EUNIX-CE</titleabbrev>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup role="Maintainer">
			<author>
				<firstname>Owen</firstname>
				<surname>Townes</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Primary">
			<author>
				<firstname>Owen</firstname>
				<surname>Townes</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Original">
			<author>
				<firstname>Owen</firstname>
				<surname>Townes</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword role="type">Starship</keyword>
			<keyword role="category">Computer System</keyword>
			<keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>17 June 2001</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Engineering Director Bret Godfrey</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Description</title>
		<para>Designed as an upgrade of the EUNIX system, the Core Element replaces the pre-existing isolinear/bioneural mix with a Quantum/Sub-Quantum state processor assisted by isolinear and bioneural elements. The Quantum/Sub-Quantum state processor computes not by 1s and 0s, but by the 16 quantum states of an electron and the 16 sub-quantum states of the three constituent particles of an electron.  These create a multiplicative state, allowing for a data bit to exist in one of 768 states.  The concept of a quantum-state processor has been around since the turn of the 21st century.  The possibility for a sub-quantum state processor has been considered since the late 22nd century.  Indeed, the technology has not been the major drawback.  Instead, the programming logic necessary to interpret 768 possibilities has been incredibly difficult to integrate until recent philosophical advances have enabled such logic programming to take place. </para>
		<para>The core element contains a number (dependent on core size) of one cubic centimeter packets of high-density hydride ion plasma.  Each packet is surrounded by a state detector which, much like the scanners in a transporter (Heisenberg compensator included), reads the states of the electrons and sub-electrons and alters them as new data is written. </para>
		<para>Output of the state detectors is routed and managed by bioneural and isolinear circuitry and secondary processors.</para>
		<para>While the detector equipment takes up a sizable amount of space (a cube approximately 4 cm on a side), the increase in processing power means that starship cores can be greatly reduced in size.  This naturally allows the already decentralized EUNIX cores to take up less space and even be located in space that otherwise would be wasted. </para>
		<section>
			<title>Designer's Note</title>
			<para>I would like to thank Michael Bourdaa, who entertained a discussion with me about quantum processors, and revealed that evidence is growing of the three sub-electron particles. </para>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>
