<article class="techreport" id="eunix">
  <title>Endocyclic Unified Neural Integrated Xenotechnologies</title>
  <titleabbrev>EUNIX</titleabbrev>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup role="Maintainer">
      <author>
        <firstname>Owen</firstname>
        <surname>Townes</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Primary Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Owen</firstname>
        <surname>Townes</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <authorgroup role="Original Designers">
      <author>
        <firstname>Owen</firstname>
        <surname>Townes</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword role="type">Starship</keyword>
      <keyword role="category">Computer System</keyword>
      <keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>9 September 1999</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Engineering Director Colin Wyers</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>The EUNIX system is a network of processing nodes spread throughout a starship. Standard fiberoptic cables are used to transmit between nodes and between sub-nodes within each processing node. ODN conduits between nodes are encased in a subspace field sustainer which allows data to transmit at FTL velocities. Each node is a bank of processors in and of itself. Depending on the purpose of the node, its composition varies from almost completely bioneural to completely isolinear.  Bioneural circuitry is used for specialized, repeated tasks, from shield modulation to warp core monitoring. Isolinear units are used for higher processing requirements. Isolinear and bioneural sub-nodes are used concurrently in combinations deemed most suited to the tasks assigned each node. </para>
    <para>Also, the multiple nodes provide backup and support for other nodes. There are virus blocks between each node and due to the de-centralization of processing, rendering the computer inoperable is impossible for all but the most skilled intruders with access to high-level codes.</para>
    <para>Nodes are placed in space that might otherwise be useless, while the space normally taken up by bulky processing cores is used instead for other functions.</para>
    <para>A programming glitch gives the EUNIX computer system a thick Scottish burr. Other than that, software functions as per spec.</para>
  </section>
</article>
