<!--<!DOCTYPE qandaset PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">-->
<qandaset id="faq-gmd">
  <blockinfo>
    <title>Gamemaster Department FAQ</title>
    <corpauthor>Gamemaster Department</corpauthor>
    <author role="GMDir">
      <honorific>Gamemaster Director</honorific>
      <firstname>Sarah</firstname>
      <surname>Hemenway</surname>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>8 June 2005</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </blockinfo>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>What do all of these acronyms mean?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>AGM</term>
          <listitem><para>Advanced Gamemaster</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>AGMDir</term>
          <listitem><para>Assistant Gamemaster Director</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>FGM</term>
          <listitem><para>Full Gamemaster</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>GM</term>
          <listitem><para>General term for a Gamemaster of any level</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>GMDir</term>
          <listitem><para>Gamemaster Director</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>GMM</term>
          <listitem><para>Gamemaster Mentor</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>GMT</term>
          <listitem><para>Gamemaster Trainee</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>GMO</term>
          <listitem><para>Gamemaster Observer</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>JGM</term>
          <listitem><para>Junior Gamemaster</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>SGM</term>
          <listitem><para>Senior Gamemaster</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>How do you become a GM?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>In order to become a GM, you must pass through the GMT program. There are four requirements for entrance into the program:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>you must have been a member of STF for at least six months;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>you must have an out-of-character rank (the highest rank you've ever played is your OOC rank) of Lieutenant;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>you must have three licensed GMs that you've served with recently fill out the GMT program recommendation form (if you haven't served with three GMs, you can have your CO and/or XO recommend you instead);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>you must pass the Academy GM exam with a score of 80%.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Then, you'll be paired with a Gamemaster Mentor (GMM) and together, you two will be placed on a ship. At the end of the mission, if all goes well, you'll become a Junior Gamemaster (JGM).</para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>What happens after you take the GM exam?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>After you take the GM exam, and meet the requirements listed in FAQ #2, you'll be given a GMM, who is an experienced GM, to provide guidance in planning your first mission and to advise you as necessary on how to run it. Then, you and your GMM will locate a ship to run your mission on. You'll have 60 days to run your mission under his/her watch. At the end of the 60 days, the CO of the ship, your GMM, and the GMDir will convene to decide if you've done well. If you have, the GMM will be removed and you'll continue on to finish your mission. At the end of the mission, you'll become a JGM and be a licensed GM.</para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>Do you have to take the GM exam?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>Yes.</para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>How do I attain a higher GM classification?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>After you pass the GM exam, you're considered to be a prospective GM. Once everything is in order and you're waiting to be placed on a ship, you're considered to be a GMT. After your training mission is finished successfully, you'll become a JGM automatically. From there on out, you have to apply for any classification increases. After you complete three successful missions or you've been GMing actively for 18 months, you can apply to become a FGM (full Gamemaster). After you complete ten successful missions or you've been GMing actively for three years, you can apply to become an AGM (advanced Gamemaster). After you complete twenty successful missions or you've been GMing actively for five years, you can apply to become a SGM (senior Gamemaster). You can't count your training mission toward any increase after JGM. All classification increases must include proper documentation in the GM Archive and are at the discretion of the Gamemaster Director.</para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>What are my responsibilities as a GMM?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>As a GMM, your primary purpose is to advise the GMT in all steps of running their first mission. This includes everything from the planning through the actual execution. After 60 days, you convene with the CO and GMDir to decide if the GMT is ready to be out on his or her own. If your GMT needs more time to prove that s/he is ready to be on his or her own, you may request an unlimited number of 30-day extensions to remain on board to observe. If s/he is ready to fly solo, you'll be removed from the ship, however, you're still your GMT's best resource for any questions s/he might have. In the event that your GMT is removed before their initial 60 days are complete, you'll be obligated to wrap up their mission for continuity's sake. After the initial training period, you'll not be obligated to do so, however, as the person who probably knows the most about the mission, it's highly encouraged.</para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>How do I become a GMM?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>GMMs must be FGM classification or higher. If you meet this requirement, all you need to do is email the GMDir and you'll be placed on a list. Most likely, you'll be assigned a GMT when you're already on the ship that s/he is going to GM.</para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>When can a GM destroy a ship?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>Sometimes a ship ends up getting destroyed in the course of a mission.  The GM cannot do that on his own, however.  The GM, CO, and Fleet Commander must all agree for a ship to be destroyed.  Otherwise, the GM will have to find some other means of being destructive.  When a ship is destroyed it is normally replaced with a new ship of the same name and class, but with a letter extension (e.g., NCC-1701-A becomes NCC-1701-B).  If the new ship is going to have a new name or class, that is between the CO and the President as it requires a Presidential Edict.</para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>When should a GM void a post?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>Sometimes a player (or the GM) may make a post that unwittingly ignores something that already happened, is completely unrealistic, or breaks some law of physics (Star Trek or real) or STF.  In those cases, either the person who posted the note or the GM may declare the post "void"; it then never happened.  If the GM does so, he must also say why.  The GM should <emphasis>not</emphasis> void posts that do something the didn't expect, only those that are <quote>irreconcilable with the actions in one or more other posts; with the laws of STF, reason, or decency; or with previously established RPG events.</quote></para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
  <qandaentry>
    <question>
      <para>When can a GM kill a character?</para>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <para>Under normal circumstances, Gamemasters may not cause the death of a character on a ship that is controlled by a member of STF. The situations in which a Gamemaster may cause the death of a character on a ship that is not a Non-Player Character (Nameless Ensign) are as follows:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>AWOL. If the character has been declared AWOL, the Gamemaster may do whatever he likes with it, without restriction.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The player gives consent to the Gamemaster, for whatever reason.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the character does something particularly suicidal that in "real life" would have gotten him killed, The GM is permitted to void the post and issue a "Death Notice", a warning to not be to be so quick to die.  If the character does so a second time, the GM may do the same but must e-mail the player, CO, and XO.  If the character gets himself killed a third time, then and only then may the GM kill the character.  It's up to the CO if the player will be allowed to start a new character or will leave the ship.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>Don't be too quick to issue Death Notices!  Often there are better ways to handle a situation, and the GM may not place a character in a position where death is the only option.  Unlike the real world, there must always be a way out.</para>
    </answer>
  </qandaentry>
</qandaset>
