<article class="whitepaper" id="location-ferenginar">
  <title>Ferenginar</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Amanda</firstname>
        <surname>Noon</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>27 October 2001</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Unknown</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <!--<indexterm>
    <seealso>
      <link linkend="species-ferengi">Ferengi</link>
    </seealso>
  </indexterm>-->
  <section>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Environment</term>
        <listitem><para>Class M</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Primary Species</term>
        <listitem><para>Ferengi</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Natural Satelites</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Artificial Satelites</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Affiliation</term>
        <listitem><para>Ferengi Alliance</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Entry Type</term>
        <listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source</term>
        <listitem><para>"Family Business" (DS9), among others</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>Wet, very wet, would sum up Ferenginar's climate. So much so that Ferengis find "the smell of rotting vegetation and the rivers of muck" endearing. So wet that the Ferengi have 178 different words for rain. Crisp is not a part of the Ferengi vocabulary. Ferenginar is the homeworld to the Ferengi Alliance. Also to be found are the offices of the Ferengi Commerce Authority; 40th floor Tower of Commerce and Ferengi Futures Exchange. Similar to the Stock Exchanges on Earth in 20th/21st centuries. Ferenginar's centre of commerce is knows as the Sacred Marketplace. The Grand steps of the Sacred Marketplace are used by the Grand Nagus to make important proclamations. The administrative centre is located in the spire topped Tower of Commerce, a part of the Sacred Marketplace. It is the tallest building in the Ferengi Alliance. All business activity in the entire Ferengi Alliance, both on and off-world is regulated at the Tower of Commerce.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>History</title>
    <para>Unknown to the Federation until 2364 when first contact was made at Delphi Ardu. The Ferengi history we know of dates back 10,000 years when they first began to use currency.</para>
  </section>
</article>
