<article class="whitepaper" id="location-mars">
  <title>Mars</title>
  <subtitle>Sol IV</subtitle>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Philip</firstname>
        <surname>Stonness</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>21 August 2002</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Unknown</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Environment</term>
        <listitem><para>Class K</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Primary Species</term>
        <listitem><para>Human</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Natural Satelites</term>
        <listitem><para>Phobos and Deimos</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Artificial Satelites</term>
        <listitem><para>Utopia Plantitia Shipyards</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Affiliation</term>
        <listitem><para>United Federation of Planets</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Entry Type</term>
        <listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source</term>
        <listitem><para>Various</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>Named after the Greek god of war, this is the fourth planet orbiting Sol in sector 001. It is generally red in colour, due to the concentration of iron present in Mars' atmosphere and the outer layer of soil. This planet has many canyons believed to have once carried water throughout the planet.</para>
    <para>The 'red planet' lies at an average of 227,936,640 Kilometers from Sol. It's volume, or size, and gravity are both approximately 1/10th that of Earth(Sol III). A Martian year is about double that of Earth's, at about one revolution per 687 terran days. Martian days are about 25 hours each.</para>
    <para>Mars has many colonies that house thousands of people. One such colony is Martian Colony 3.</para>
    <para>Because of the extremely thin air within Mars' atmosphere and low gravity, sub-orbital flight is made easy in comparison with other inhabited planets in general.</para>
    <para>In orbit and on the surface is the Utopia Plantitia Ship Yards. This installation launched many famous ships, such as the U.S.S. Enterprise NCC-1701-D and U.S.S. Voyager.</para>
    <para>Adding to the defense of Sector 001 is the 'Mars Defense perimeter', a series of small unmanned craft designed to protect the inner planets of the Sol system. This perimeter was easily thwarted however by the Borg in 2367 after a cube destroyed more then 30 ships at Wolf 359.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>History</title>
    <para>It was first settled by humans in the year 2103, 40 years after warp drive was invented. The first settlements were designed after the "Millennium Gate", a large self-sufficient commercial center built on Earth in the late 20th century. Martian rights were dictated by the Fundamental Declaration of the Martian Colonies. However, this planet was hardly free of crime at this point in history. At that time there was a serial killer that murdered many women. This madman, 200 years later, was found out to be an alien entity feeding off of fear from it's victims. This discovery was made by the U.S.S. Enterprise NCC-1701.</para>
    <para>Early in Mars' history was the Ares IV spacecraft, it was of the Mars modules in service by NASA. It went missing early in the 21st century. No human had known what happened to the capsule or how it disappeared, but this mystery was soon unraveled by the U.S.S. Voyager while in the Delta Quadrant. Voyager encountered a massive moving sub-space 'cloud' or 'storm' that had been moving through space for eons. Upon closer investigation, it was found that the Ares IV has been entrapped by the storm. The Voyager crew soon found that the astronaut that had piloted Ares IV had survived being inside the storm for several days after his entrapment.</para>
    <para>Physical exploration of this minute planet began in the late 20th century, where NASA and the Soviet Union sent many unmanned probes to gather valuable data on Mars. On of the most famous is the Pathfinder project(a massive project launched by NASA), which brought back many photographs of the planet's surface and other valuable data. In 1996, NASA released information pertaining to a meteorite that was thought to be from Mars. This rock housed fossils of micro organisms, which was thought to be evidence of life on Mars.</para>
  </section>
</article>
