<article class="whitepaper" id="location-obaine">
	<title>Obaine Nebula</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Mike</firstname>
				<surname>Rouse-Deane</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>18 April 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Unknown</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Abstract</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Affiliation</term>
				<listitem><para>United Federation of Planets</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Entry Type</term>
				<listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>The Obaine Nebula is located deep within Fleet 2's borders. The nebula itself is full of plasma, though plans of the plasma being mined was dropped when the team of scientists discovered its volitile nature. The nebula consists of tons of plasma, which attracts to warp cores and other electrical devices. The nebula also eminates a large quantity of delta radiation, though annoculations are required when entering the nebula, the nebula has been nicknamed "the hell pit".</para>
		<para>Within the Nebula contains a small group of asteroids, which have always been there. These rocks shield the radiation effect as well as the strong plasma forces. Although testing has been carried out on the nebula itself to harness the energy from the plasma and hopefully produce a stable plasma to use in warp cores, no test so far as been successful.</para>
		<para></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>History</title>
		<para>The USS Nautilus, after a specific mission, entered the nebula. Unfortunately, the crew and ship felt the massive pressure of working within it, with many crewmembers getting radiation posioning of spots and warts which leaked out yellow puss. The ship itself was contained in a shield, which took most of the Nautilus' power. After the ship was supposidly attacked by an unknown ship, their warp core was stolen and never seen again.</para>
	</section>
</article>
