<article class="whitepaper" id="location-qonos">
  <title>Qo'noS</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Emma</firstname>
        <surname>Rouse-Deane</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>16 October 2001</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Unknown</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
<!--   <indexterm> -->
  <section>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Environment</term>
        <listitem><para>Class M</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Primary Species</term>
        <listitem><para>Klingon</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Natural Satelites</term>
        <listitem><para>Praxis</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Artificial Satelites</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Affiliation</term>
        <listitem><para>Klingon Empire</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Entry Type</term>
        <listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source</term>
        <listitem><para>Star Trek: VI, "Sins of the Father" (TNG), and others</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>Qo'noS is located in Klingon space in the Beta Quadrant and is the capital planet of the Empire. From space it is seen as a large green world. It consists of a large landmass which is dominated by a vast ocean. Qo'noS tilts on it's axis, which gives a range of climates and temperatures, and gives rise to extremes of both hot and freezing weather. Like earth it is a few degrees cooler at the poles. The Capital of Qo'noS is First City, where the Great Hall is located. This is a ceremonial building, which dominates the skyline. The Great Hall functions both as a parliament, and as a supreme court. It is the seat of Klingon Government. It's architecture reflects the Empire's military style, and the structures give the appearance of enormous fortresses.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Places of Interest</title>
      <simplelist>
        <member role="The Kri'Stak Volcano">A mountain on Qo'noS where legend tells that Kahless the Unforgettable forged the first bat'leth by dropping a lock of his hair into the lava.</member>
        <member role="Lursor">A lake on Qo'noS. History says that it was here that Kahless the Unforgettable finished forging the bat'leth. He dropped the burning lock into the water, and twisted it to make a blade.</member>
        <member role="Mekro'vak">A province or region of Qo'noS, where Lady Grilka comes from.</member>
        <member role="The Caves of Kahless">Subterranean chambers which are often used in the Day of Honor ritual, where participants are required to drink mot'loch.</member>
        <member role="Tong Vey">The city that was destroyed by Emperor Sompek. Around 10,000 of Sompek's warriors laid seige to the city, before it finally surrendered. Sompek then ordered the city burned and the occupants killed.</member>
        <member role="Quin'lat">Another ancient city. It was here that a great storm struck, whilst Kahless the Unforgettable was visiting. One warrior went outside to face the storm in order to 'stand before the storm and make it respect him'. He was instead killed. Kahless later commented, 'The wind does not respect a fool'.</member>
      </simplelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>History</title>
    <para>The planet was seeded with life 4 billion years ago, along with Earth, Vulcan and Cardassia to name a few. In 2293, Qo'noS suffered severe environmental damage when Praxis, their key energy producing facility at the time suffered a catastrophic explosion that ended up shattering the moon, leaving only a small fragment behind. It was estimated that Qo'noS would have used up all of it's oxygen within 50 years, if resources were not spent into rectifying the problem. The Klingon Empire needed to reroute it's financial spending, and could no longer afford it's military campaign with the Federation. It was this key event that led to the peace initiative that was undertaken by Gorkon, then Chancellor of the Empire.</para>
  </section>
</article>
