<article class="whitepaper" id="location-quanta">
  <title>Quanta</title>
  <subtitle>Quantas I</subtitle>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Jason</firstname>
        <surname>Lee</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>19 April 2002</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Unknown</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <!--<indexterm>
    <seealso>
      <link linkend="species-quasian">Quasian</link>
    </seealso>
    <seealso>
      <link linkend="location-quantas">Quantas</link>
    </seealso>
  </indexterm>-->
  <section>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Environment</term>
        <listitem><para>Class L</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Primary Species</term>
        <listitem><para>Quasians</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Natural Satelites</term>
        <listitem><para>32 small moons (Varying from 32 meters in diameter to 128 meters)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Artificial Satelites</term>
        <listitem><para>None</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Affiliation</term>
        <listitem><para>Quasians</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Entry Type</term>
        <listitem><para>Custom</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The 32 small moons of Quanta are in spherical in shape and maintain orbits in which are not very far apart. The Quasians have calculated that these 32 moons will never crash into the planet or into each other so long as nothing happens to them. Quanta has an approximate diameter of 12,800 miles. The flora and fauna are primarily blue in color and vary in size. There are a few green planets, but they are rare to find. The planet has primarily good weather, however, there are a few bad storms occasionally. The Quasians have discovered an alien artifact which is lead to be the reason how the Quasians exist with 31 other selves and 31 other planets on different dimensional levels.</para>
    <para>The Quasian government is an orderly and organized one, consisting of 32 representatives as a collective council for their planet. These 32 representatives are usually the 32 wisest and smartest people of all Quasians. This council is usually referred as the Quantar. Under the council, there are 32 committees that do various administrative tasks ordered by the council. These committees have 32 people each, and are either hired or voted by the people into office. In the event of an emergency or a disagreement, the 32 committees may meet, vote for one representative for each committee and form the Quasian Council of Agreement. The Quasian Council of Agreement is made of the 32 original representatives plus the 32 elected representatives of committees. The Council may include up to 32 elective representatives of the people, if the need arises. The Quasian Council requires 2/3 in agreement of all those present.</para>
    <para>Quanta has many oceans, all which interconnect together. The Quasians have cities underwater due to the fact that the land mass of the planet is only about 32% of the planet. There are many sea creatures, including a dolphin like creature which the Quasians refer as dophians.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>History</title>
    <para>The planet's enviroment has not been altered in anyway. The Quasians do not have a history of industrialization by using fire as a source of power. The Quasians never had an ozone layer type problem due the fact that they primarily use hydropower more. Many of the Quasians' battles have occurred on or under water since the Quasians valued the parts of land that was available. However, the Quasians have learned many useful water technology which also made the land underwater just as valuable as the land above water. As a result, most of the battles on Quanta have occurred on Quanta's oceans.</para>
  </section>
</article>
