<article class="whitepaper" id="location-risa">
	<title>Risa</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Jason</firstname>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>25 March 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Unknown</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Abstract</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Environment</term>
				<listitem><para>Class M</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Primary Species</term>
				<listitem><para>Risan</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Natural Satelites</term>
				<listitem><para>1</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Artificial Satelites</term>
				<listitem><para>None</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Affiliation</term>
				<listitem><para>United Federation of Planets</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Entry Type</term>
				<listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Source</term>
				<listitem><para>"Captain's Holiday" (TNG) and others</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>Risa is a luxurious tropical resort paradise with many beaches which attracts millions of guests each year. In addition, Risa is renowned for its uninhibited sexuality another reason why millions of guests come to Risa. Risian sexuality is very much part of their culture. Identified by a decorative emblem on their foreheads between the eyes, Risians often initiate or respond to the desire for sexual relations through the use of a small statuette called a Horga'hn, the Risian symbol of sexuality. Display of a Horga'hn announces that the owner wishes to participate in jamaharon, a Risian sexual rite.</para>
		<para>Risa orbits a multiple stars and is in the same sector as Starbase 12. Risa benefits from the most elaborate weather control system in the Federation despite the fact that it is a rain-soaked and geologically unstable jungle in its natural state. In addition, Risa seems to be hosts to many conferences in the Federation. It lies at least 6 hours in a Runabout from station Deep Space 9. It is interesting to note that the Risian computer has information on all the guests on Risa, and can tell one if someone has made arrangements for arrival.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>History</title>
		<para>Risa has been the focal point for the fate of superweapon Tox Uthat stolen from the future in 2366. Picard and a woman named Vash who proclaimed to be an assistant to an archeologist who spent many years in searching for the Tox Uthat. Vash apparently already discovered the Tox Uthat and hid it from a Ferengi named Sovak. Vash used Sovak in order to gain passage to Risa since she didn't have any funds to take her to Risa. Picard figured out that Vash had already discovered the Tox Uthat and contacted the Enterprise to do a level 14 transport on his order. When the Vorgons, a group of aliens claiming to be a security team, tried to take it from Picard; Picard ordered the transport which destroyed the Tox Uthat. It is presumed that the Vorgons have returned to the past in order to stop Picard.</para>
		<para>Risa has been part of the abortive Ktairain Expansion plot using an addictive mental game in 2368. Lastly, it played to a series of protests by the reactionary New Essentialists movement in 2373. The New Essentialists used ecological terrorist activities as part of their protests.</para>
	</section>
</article>
