<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">-->
<article id="textbook-administrative">
	<title>Administrative Menu</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Katherine</firstname>
				<surname>Dedul</surname>
				<email></email>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>2</revnumner>
				<date>28 June 2011</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Revised by Kat Dedul</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>20 September 2005</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Added to the Library</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section id="admin-intro">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Welcome to the Admin course, designed for COs, XOs, and GMs to get them acquainted with the functions of the administrative menu. There is no exam to take, or grade to worry about. This course simply goes through the functions of all the administrative areas of the ship.</para>
		<para>Now, if you look on the ship's MOTD (Message Of The Day), along the top right-hand side, you will see 3 brand new tabs ("Admin", "Edit", and "E-mail"), we will examine the functions of each of these new tabs in detail throughout this course.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="admin-101">
		<title>Lesson One: The Tabs</title>
		<para>Before we go into a lot of detail, it's time to discuss the basic functions of these three new tabs.</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Admin</term>
				<listitem><para>The place COs/XOs and GMs go to add new characters, view all characters on the ship, create log entries and add and remove subscribers as well as a few other functions that will be discussed in greater detail over the next few pages of the course.</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Edit</term>
				<listitem><para>This is where you can edit the MOTD, both the basic look of it and simply updating your own special section of it. You need to be familiar with HTML coding as well as other codes that may be employed in the maintenance of the MOTD. If only to avoid undoing someone's hard work by accidentally deleting code.</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>E-mail</term>
				<listitem><para>Sends a mass e-mail to all subscribers on your board. Not recommended for use, it may be a good idea to simply ignore this and carry on. Generally, if you need to reach all the members of your crew, it would probably be easiest to simply post a note on the ship regarding it rather than to spam everyone who has happened to subscribe to your board. We'll go into what subscribers are and how that works later in the course.</para><listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section id="admin-102">
		<title>Lesson Two: Characters - Editing & Creating</title>
		<para>The first two options under the Admin tab will be discussed together as they are related.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Character List</title>
			<para>This link brings you to the list that is your full roster, including AWOLed and unrostered characters, unrostered NPCs, unrostered GM Controlled Characters, etc.</para>
			<para>This section allows you to see the "sort order" of every character on the ship. Sort order sets the order in which the character displays on the roster, without sort order, every character is organized alphabetically by character name. COs can organize characters however they wish(as an XO or GM, you may want to adhere to the sort orders to keep your CO happy).</para>
			<para>To start the editing process either to assign a sort order or some other option, you click on the character name on the roster or in the character list. This brings up the character information screen and you'll note in the top right-hand corner of the window is an "edit" tab, clicking on that brings up the character editing screen.</para>
			<para>The options available under this screen are numerous, let's discuss them one by one:</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Rank</term>
					<listitem><para>Obviously as CO, you'll occasionally see the need to promote people. This permits you to select their rank from a drop down menu. It is very important to note that as CO, you can only promote a character above the rank of Lt. Commander if that player already has a rank higher than Lt. Commander or with permission from your FComm. When in doubt, ask your FComm, they should be able to clear up any confusion you might have on this topic.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Position & Custom Position</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Again, typically COs only use this function, but occasionally an XO may be given permission by the CO to use this. Position is another drop-down menu, with all the standard positions organized by department. Note, the CNS is located under the medical department and the CTO is located under the security department.</para>
						<para>If you have a unique swing position on your ship(i.e: a lot of alt-RPGs are in this situation, but some standard ships can have these too), you'll be using the "custom position" option, which is a dialog box permitting you to type in whatever you please.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Character Name</term>
					<listitem><para>This can be changed by you or by the owner of that character. Generally when adding a new character to the ship, you'll use this box to note the character name.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Rostered</term>
					<listitem><para>This option is a drop down menu that permits you to choose whether or not that character displays on the public roster that is viewable by everyone(That character will still display on your administrative roster). You may also be using this tab to unroster an AWOL player for a period before deleting them completely from the roster.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Species</term>
					<listitem><para>Allows you to assign a species or race to each character(Human, Vulcan, etc.). Regular players do not have the option of editing this, but COs should ensure that any changes to this are at the wish of the player of the character.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Sort-Order</term>
					<listitem><para>This option permits you to select the order in which that character displays on the roster. You can assign more than one person to the same sort order. For example, if you have five Lieutenants on the ship, you can assign them all "4" and they'll appear after those at level 1, 2, and 3, but will display alphabetically within their "order". You have the numeric range of -10(first to display on roster) to 10(last to display on roster), so you have quite a range of numbers by which to sort characters on your roster.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Biography</term>
					<listitem><para>Allows you or the owner of the character to enter a biography, limited HTML tags are allowed(The ones permitted are listed beneath the dialogue box as well as a bit more information about links). Very rarely will you use this function, as it's available to the owners of the characters to edit for themselves. I think for the most part this is a "hands-off" type of section of the character edit screen.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Audience</term>
					<listitem><para>Permits you to select the area or ship to which a particular character is assigned. The default of the present ship you're working from is automatically checked off(i.e: if you're editing from the USS Genesis that's the box that will be checked). Typically you'll only look at this quickly to ensure there isn't a bug in the system and to make sure you're keeping that character on the right ship. As an aside note, the only areas you will see under the audience option are the areas to which you are a subscriber.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Height, Age & Weight</term>
					<listitem><para>Permits you to assign a height, age and weight to a particular character. Again unless it is your own character that you are editing, you will only be uploading info given to you by the author of that character. Only administrators can access these three boxes.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Authoring Information</term>
					<listitem><para>Assigns which user this character belongs to. You'll need to know a person's username in order to use this.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Create New Character</title>
			<para>Clicking this will bring you back to the already familiar character edit screen, only it'll be completely blank. Assign all the information you have on the new character by filling in the boxes(typically Rank, Position, Character Name, Rostered, Sort Order). You will notice one big difference between the edit and create character screen, you do not have the option of selecting an audience when creating a new character.</para>
			<para>At the bottom, you'll need to ensure you choose the proper "owner" of the character.  In order to do this, you'll need to know the username of the person you wish to add, full names will not work(Unless of course that person's username and full name are the same, in which case it would work).</para>
			<para>When editing and creating characters, you have the option to preview your changes/creation by clicking "preview" instead of "submit". On the preview screen, your changes appear right at the top, with the regard submit character boxes down below. In order for changes to be made permanent on your ship, you need to click "submit".</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>
