<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">-->
<article id="textbook-command-xo">
	<title>Executive Officer Command Course</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Robin</firstname>
				<surname>Bird</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
            <revnumber>3</revnumber>
            <date>20th May 2010</date>
            <revdescription>
              <para>Course proctor changed to Robin Bird</para>
            </revdescription>
          </revision>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>2</revnumber>
				<date>16th February 2009</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Course proctor changed to Anthony Martin</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>		
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section id="xo-intro">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Jim Rohn</attribution>
			<para>"Leadership is the challenge to be something more than average."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>Welcome to the Star-Fleet Command Course for Executive Officers (XO). You might be thinking about taking your first steps towards that coveted centre chair, a newly appointed XO wanting to do the best job you can or an experienced XO wanting to make sure you have everything covered. This course should deal with everything you want to know!</para>
		<para>This course aims to break down the basics and to provide you with the essential information that anyone needs to be a successful XO in any environment. All areas will be covered from in character work to out of character work.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-101">
		<title>What is an Executive Officer (XO)?</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Wikipedia definition of Executive Officer</attribution>
			<para>"In many militaries, an Executive Officer (XO) is the second-in-command, reporting to the Commanding Officer (CO). The XO is typically responsible for the management of day-to-day activities, freeing the commander to concentrate on planning the unit's next move. The XO also takes charge in the absence of the commander, and the position is frequently a stepping stone to a command position."</para> 
		</epigraph>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>STF Definition of an Executive Officer (XO) taken from Fleet Command and Other Mundane Matters (FCOMM)</attribution>
			<para>"Executive Officer (XO) In addition to RPG duties, the XO is responsible for assisting other members of the ship as needed. The CO may enlist the aid of his XO in fulfilling his ship management duties, but the CO will remain ultimately responsible for them. The XO's primary responsibility is to take over as acting CO (aCO) should the CO declare an LOA. An XO may declare the CO AWOL with the consent of the Fleet Commander and assume the position of acting CO until such time as the President appoints a new CO. A CO may appoint his own XO with the consent of the Fleet Commander, should the Fleet Commander choose to exercise such authority. No individual may hold more than one XO position simultaneously. The XO of Academy Training Ships does not count towards this limit. Acting XO does not count towards this limit."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>The position of XO is one of support to the commanding officer as well as running your ship efficiently. In the chain of command all Department Heads report to you about the day to day running of their departments and the welfare of the crew. You then in turn report that to the CO.</para>
		<para>An XO manages the ship effectively and efficiently making best use of the resources available. You manage your Department Heads, who in turn manage their own departments. You will interpret the wishes of your Commanding Officer and pass them down in the chain of command.</para>
		<para>Just as a DH forms a bridge on the ship, the XO does too. You are the link between the Captain and the crew. Very few of the crew themselves will have direct contact with the Captain, since most situations and matters will be dealt with by the Department Heads or by you.</para>
		<para>You are the first and foremost link in the chain of command, the Captain's right hand and immediate support, as well as the main reporting figure for the crew and department heads. You advise the Captain and interpret the CO's orders for your juniors.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-102">
		<title>What is an XO's Job In Character (IC) and Out of Character (OOC)?</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Dwight D. Eisenhower</attribution>
			<para>"You do not lead by hitting people over the head - that's assault, not leadership."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>An XO has a vital job on a ship in making the ship fun for everyone. The XO can help to create and maintain a fun, positive atmosphere, as well as ensuring that the DH's and junior officers have plenty of work to be busy.</para>
		<para>The best ships in STF have an active XO that pushes the crew to higher effort and enthusiasm. This is done by example and encouragement.</para>
		<para>It is possible to break down the job of a good Executive Officer into two main areas, In Character (IC) work and Out of Character (OOC) work.</para>
		<section>
			<title>In Character</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>It is the job of a good Executive Officer (XO) to ensure that your ship is run efficiently and your officers have plenty of work to do. You will be required to give your staff tasks. These may be sim related tasks or tasks delegated to you by the CO.  You should feel free to issue orders within the limitations of the main sim, but never at the expense of the main sim. You should never issue orders that will detract from the progress of the main sim. For example, if the main sim requires the input of the science department, don't order them all off ship to a party. However, if the security department has little to do, you may wish to speak to the Chief of Security and suggest in character he runs some security drills.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Your job is to give professional advice, alternatives and feedback to the CO, when given the opportunity to do so. This does not mean speaking out of turn in front of other officers or behaving in an inappropriate manner. You are at the top of the chain of command and your officers look to you for an example. You should give the CO your opinion, but once that decision is made you should support it. Feel free to request a word in private if the situation requires it. Never argue with your CO in public. Remember you must support the chain of command as it is the principle all military vessels operate upon. Once the CO makes their decision, you must support them.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Your job is also to interpret the advice and reports given to you by your Department Heads. Remember, each DH is considered to be an expert in their own field. If you had a medical emergency you would want a Doctor's opinion as they are an expert. Feel free to ask and invite your DH's to give you advice, but it is your job to pass that information onto the Captain, outside of a briefing room environment. Just as you should never countermand your CO, you should always support your DH too, but the decision of what information to bring forward to a CO is yours.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Your job is to accept the orders from your superior, the CO, and to pass them onto your Department Heads for action. This may require holding a briefing with individual DH's or multiple persons briefing with several Department Heads or their teams. Keep your crew busy and keep them informed, just as you would if this was real life.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Enforcing discipline. It is an overlooked part of an XO's in character work. If a crew member has misbehaved it is traditionally the XO's responsibility to both resolve and act upon the situation. Remember that there are different types of potential incident. With regards to minor misdemeanors, such as an officer being repeatedly late for duty, improperly dressed or arguing with a superior officer, then the XO can issue appropriate punishment such as assigning extra duty shifts or cleaning duties. Punishments should always fit the crime. Serious misdemeanors, such as being drunk on duty, should be investigated and reported to the CO with recommendations for punitive punishment. A crime, such as theft or assault is a serious offence and should be officially referred to the Chief of Security for investigation. The CO should be kept notified at all times and a decision made about punitive punishment or, if deemed necessary, preparation for court martial.  It is in your interest to help crew members develop correctly. Bad behaviour should not be encouraged or permitted. However, the punishment should always fit the crime. Although the XO has powers to enforce discipline and punish misdemeanors, they cannot authorize demoting someone or to having them brigged. That will require permission from the CO.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Set an example. You have to set an in character example for the crew and show them what is acceptable behaviour and conduct. If you act in an unprofessional way then your junior officers may do the same things too. You are setting the discipline and tone for the ship. You are an experienced officer, a role model for the junior officers.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Lead by example. This means give orders and make posts to keep active. Feel free to make use of the ship's facilities. Go take your physical, have a counseling evaluation. Demonstrate to people how to keep active.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Take an interest in the welfare of the ship and the crew. Meet with DH's on a routine basis to discuss readiness and efficiency, but also the welfare of their staff. Take an interest in the activities. Hold competitions and events to build interest. Remember, on the Enterprise they had drama societies, musical events, sporting events and even competitions for the children. Start something interesting for your crew! The Ship's Counsellor, if there is one, is the expert on the welfare of the crew, but you are the one responsible. So work with the counselor too!</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>One of the most pleasant aspects of In Character XO work is the fact that you have the right to recommend people for promotion to your CO. Of course he has the right to refuse too!!! If you do make promotion recommendations, make sure you do it in the right context. Ensure you discuss this with your CO OOC first to obtain their permission to post about it. There is nothing worse than someone reading and getting their hopes up, but nothing coming of it, or worse the CO saying "No way!"  Once you have permission from the CO, discuss it In Character with the Captain in private as you would any other performance evaluation. This is an excellent between sims filler and can help maintain the moral of the crew.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>After the end of a mission, feel free to review the performance of departments in character. Have discussions with the DH's and feel free to agree in character actions or improvements. This is another good way of dealing with the time between sims and keeping active. It is also something that you would do and encourage in the military. Learn from your mistakes!</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Out of Character</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>As XO you almost certainly will be more involved in the recruiting process for the ship. The CO may even delegate recruitment to you. Recruitment is covered in more details later on. However, it becomes even more important for you to create a positive atmosphere as XO and, just as in character; it is your responsibility to set an example for your junior officers/DHs out of character. So make them feel at home, send them a welcome email, get to know them and make sure they have plenty of work to do. Don't argue with people on the ship and always conduct discussions via email.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>OOC Comments on a ship can be either positive reinforcement or destructive. Too many and a ship can lose its' way, too few and a ship can seem cold. The simple rule is to keep your comments limited to those of a positive nature. Praise people for good posts. Praise people for initiative. Discourage negative threads and comments. Always monitor the amount of OOC and if you think a player is posting too many OOC comments at the expense of IC comments, then you should drop them a polite email about it.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Although it is always good practice to praise a crewmember in public and on the ship, never criticize a crewmember in public. In certain situations being firm about a situation is required, but always send any criticism about a player via email, copied to your CO. There is nothing more destructive than criticism on a ship. People react in haste and in anger to negative comments. This can effect the enjoyment of any player on a ship, even those not involved.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Support your CO. In character and out of character, you should never disagree with your CO in public. In character you speak in private, OOC you should talk to your CO in IM or via Email. This preserves the chain of command and reduces the chances of a disagreement.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>On the best ships it is not only the GM that will provide work for people. A sim might last four months or more, or the GM might go on LOA. It is your responsibility to help provide both additional work for the non involved departments and to help progress the sim. The temptation to get creative, get involved or tied up in fun side sims is great, but as XO you must have one eye on advancing the main sim. A side sim should never be complicated or involve a great deal of work. For example, a crewman falling over and breaking an arm will keep medical occupied. Contact the GM see where you can help with the main sim if required.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>There are various basic administration tasks, but these are outlined in more detail later.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-103">
		<title>The Chain of Command</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Grace Murray Hopper</attribution>
			<para>"You manage things, you lead people."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>So far there has been a lot of mentions of the chain of command, but what exactly is it?</para>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Wikipedia Definition</attribution>
			<para>"In a military context, the chain of command is the line of authority and responsibility along which orders are passed.</para>
			<para>The line of command will generally go from a higher-ranked soldier who gives the order, i.e. an officer, down to a lower-ranked soldier who is ordered to perform, i.e. a common soldier.</para>
			<para>In general, military personnel give orders to only those directly below them in the chain of command and receive orders from only those directly above. For example, a common soldier who has difficulty carrying out an order is likely to be disciplined for not observing the chain of command if he skips the officer who is in direct command of him and directly appeals to a higher-ranked officer in his chain of command.</para>
			<para>The concept of chain of command also implies that higher rank alone does not entitle a person to give commands. For example, an officer of a given military unit cannot directly command common soldiers of another unit, because this officer is outside of their chain of command. If the officer needs something from the soldiers of another unit, he is generally expected to approach an officer along their chain of command."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>In STF we operate a Chain of Command. In character on a ship a JO should report to a DH, that DH should report to the XO, the XO to the CO and the CO to Starfleet Command. The Chain of Command operates as a two way filter. Orders filter down and information filters upwards. The DH is the first step in the link and they will pass the information up to you, or handle what problems they can at their level.</para>
		<para>The XO effectively then filters the information from the DH's decides what is important to pass onto the Captain and does so. In Character it should be rare that the XO cannot handle all but the most serious of problems before involving the Commanding Officer. That does not mean you keep the Captain out of the information loop, you will just keep him informed with standard reports.</para>
		<para>As with any situation there is some degree of flexibility. In a crisis department heads should and will report directly to the Captain. The Captain may bypass you accordingly. It is a matter of what is necessary to the situation required. In a crisis you don't have time to gather information and filter it to the Captain.</para>
		<para>Out of Character the same system should apply, but in practice the XO is often, but not always, the first port of call for most problems. If you cannot resolve them, then you should then refer the issue to the CO, who will then refer it onto the FComm if required. Don't feel by using the chain of command you are letting anyone down. Better to get a problem resolved than sitting on one and letting it grow. Always keep your CO informed as to any OOC problems that may be passed to you for your attention.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-104">
		<title>What are an XO's powers?</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Robert Greenleaf</attribution>
			<para>"Good leaders must first become good servants."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>Sadly, if you were expecting a huge power trip, you are in the wrong place. There are very few decisions that an XO can make and very little authority with which to make them. IC and OOC the CO is the person in charge. They make the decisions and you just get to enforce those decisions as orders.</para>
		<para>Your power comes in supporting the CO and forming a bond of trust and respect. In time the CO will come to trust your recommendations and may choose to implement them, or even delegate responsibilities to you. Remember to learn and observe as one day that big centre chair will be yours!</para>
		<para>You will be able to update the MOTD and deal with basic administration. In the end the XO is there primarily to cover in the event that the CO is on LOA or AWOL. Even then you should run your decisions passed the Fleet Commander (FComm) first. Keep the ship ticking over!!</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-105">
		<title>Giving Orders</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>General George S. Patton</attribution>
			<para>"Be willing to make decisions. That is the most important quality in a good leader."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>Giving orders doesn't come easily to everyone. For you to be a successful XO you have to believe that you are the right person for the position. The structure of STF is based upon a military environment and as such you have both the rank and authority of your position to give orders...and expect them to be obeyed!</para>
		<para>If you have given an order and it wasn't obeyed, then you are entitled to an explanation. Don't doubt your own authority. You have the position. You have the rank. Be confident!</para>
		<para>Orders given as XO can be categorized into three main areas.</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Independent Orders</emphasis> - this is where your XO character might have been left in charge of the ship or of a landing party. Your orders here come from your own instincts and authority. You are in charge. You are the senior officer. Make your decisions, but know that you will be accountable for your decisions later.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Delegation</emphasis> - This is where you assign a task given to you to a lower ranking officer. This might be just passing the CO's orders down to your DH's. It might well be you delegating an aspect of your own duty to a DH, like an inspection visit. Remember to pass on orders and tasks clearly. If necessary hold a briefing. Make sure you give all the information needed to perform a task.</para></listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Assisting the CO</emphasis> - This is both IC and OOC. OOC the CO might require you to help them with something that needs to be done. Remember, your authority as XO of a ship does extend OOC as well. Confirm what the CO wishes you to do first before making OOC demands on players. IC this could be helping to run the bridge while the ship is under attack. Think Riker issuing orders on the bridge of the Enterprise, whilst Picard commands the ship under attack. It is an emergency situation so give your orders. Any time you are giving orders to help to assist the CO they fall under this category.</para>
				<para>A good example would be in a battle situation. You have reports of damage, hull   breaches and casualties. The CO will be busy fighting the ship and issuing fire control orders. Feel free to order damage control teams and medical teams to those locations. Ask for damage reports. Report information to the Captain as it comes through.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>The simple rules to follow in issuing orders as an XO can be best summed up using the adage of LADA (Look Assess Decide Act).</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>LOOK</term>
				<listitem><para>What is going on around you? What information does your character possess? Where are you? Is the Ship in Danger? Is the CO incapacitated? Can you see a problem that is about to develop?</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ASSESS</term>
				<listitem><para>What does the information tell you? What is the situation? What can you do about it? How can you influence the course of events?  Will the situation countermand your orders? Try to assess the consequences.</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>DECIDE</term>
				<listitem><para>Make your decision. You are the one in the position of authority because you earned it. Make your decision based on the information you have at hand. Making no decision or hedging your bets is dangerous. Don't countermand the CO!</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>ACT</term>
				<listitem><para>Give your orders. Give them with confidence. Remember if you don't believe in them, no one else will. So you might make a bad decision, but that is part of the job!</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>Finally, be respectful, be calm and be polite. Try not to scream and rant in character unless it is required character development.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-106">
		<title>Covering for a CO</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Harlan Cleveland</attribution>
			<para>"Leaders are problem solvers by talent and temperament, and by choice."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>Real life happens to us all. Some times we all need to take a LOA or a CO might go AWOL. What happens then?</para>
		<para>In a LOA situation you should be able to discuss that with your CO in advance. Discuss what their expectations are...what they want to achieve...and how they want their character handled in their absence. Make sure you are clear as to the limits of your own authority. The CO will have to ratify these decisions when they return. Keep in contact with your CO.</para>
		<para>In an AWOL situation you must report the CO to the Fleet Commander (FComm). It will be the FComm's decision on how to proceed from that point. Discuss the situation with them and their expectations. Once more, make sure that you are clear as to the limit of your authority. You may well be appointed acting CO. Be prepared for command!</para>
		<para>In all situations don't feel cast adrift! The Fleet Commander and the Assistant Fleet Commander (AFComm) are available to discuss any situations or problems. It is better to seek advice than commit to a situation you are not sure of. Follow the chain of command. It is there to protect you and help you.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-107">
		<title>Administration</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Dale Carnegie</attribution>
			<para>"Do the hard jobs first. The easy jobs will take care of themselves."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>This section deals with certain basic areas of the job of an XO in terms of OOC administration. This is broken down into several subsections that explain what they are and whether this is something that you are required to do, or whether this may be something delegated to you by your CO.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Fleet Reports (Mandatory)</title>
			<para>No getting away from these! Each fleet is required to submit a report each month on its' performance. Each ship has to produce a report that goes on to make up the Fleet Report. Reports are required from each CO, XO and GM.</para>
			<para>These are mandatory. If you are not going to be able to submit a report for that month you should notify your CO and your FComm. If you are not sure where to find the report forms, what to do with them or when they are due, ask!</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Message of the Day (MOTD) Updating (Required)</title>
			<para>Every role-playing environment in STF has a MOTD. The responsibility for the MOTD is down to the Commanding Officer of that environment. However, each one will have a section for updating your own comments. It is advisable to keep this up to date.</para>
			<para>When taking the role of XO, seek clarification from the CO as to the extent of updating they will tolerate on the MOTD. Some CO's prefer to update nearly everything themselves, others are happy to let the XO deal with it. Remember, you are merely using the MOTD, not owning it! Don't make any big changes without asking the CO first.</para>
			<para>Finally as a reminder, never ever ever, edit the MOTD of another ship without the express permission of the CO.</para>
			<para>The actual means of doing this is discussed in the Administration Menu Course in Star-fleet Academy.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Welcome Emails (Required)</title>
			<para>It is good practice to welcome everyone to a ship, regardless of whether they are experienced, new, or whether you helped to recruit them. You should be welcoming and friendly, introducing yourself and helping the new person to settle in. The best ships are the ones where you feel wanted. Make that person feel wanted too!</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Enforcing AWOL (May be delegated by the CO)</title>
			<para>As XO you must be aware of the AWOL policy for your ship and the fleet. These should be clearly displayed on the both the Fleet and the Ship MOTD. </para>
			<para>When you take the XO position you should ensure that you have discussed this with the CO. Some CO's will happily delegate AWOL responsibility to the XO, some will prefer to keep the AWOL task to themselves.</para>
			<para>If the CO delegates the responsibility to you then you should send an email to the role-player involved. Remember to be polite! Explain what the AWOL policy is and that they are outside of it. Enquire whether they are okay. Most AWOLs are due to illness so be understanding in your dealings with a fellow rper. Ask them to post by or reply to you by a specific date or that they will be removed from the roster. Allow them time to reply. Remember to copy the CO!</para>
			<para>If the time limit passes and the CO has agreed, remove the player from the roster. The details of how to do this are explained in more detail in the Star-fleet Academy Administration Course.</para>
			<para>Whatever the situation and regardless of whom has responsibility for AWOLs it is your duty to bring an AWOL player to the attention of your CO. If you see someone is AWOL then you should inform your CO. Don't just assume that someone else will notice.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>General Recruiting (May be delegated or shared by the CO)</title>
			<para>All ships need a healthy and active roster. People leave ships. Therefore recruiting is an important task for any ship to maintain a strong role-playing environment.</para>
			<para>The task of recruiting may be delegated or even shared by the CO. Equally the CO might prefer to keep all the recruitment duties. This is another area that you will have to discuss when you come to take an XO position. It is always best to know what the expectations are from the beginning.</para>
			<para>Even if you don't actively recruit for the ship there is nothing wrong with pointing out potential recruits to a CO. It shows interest and enthusiasm, and is a valuable skill to learn for when you take a command of your own.</para>
			<para>Where do you start looking for potential crew members? Start by looking on the other ships you are already on. If people impress you over a period of time then pass the name to your CO for their opinion. Regardless of whether you handle the recruitment or not always report to your CO before making an approach to any prospect. There may be information or history that you are not aware of. It is always better to be safe than create a potential problem.</para>
			<para>Look at other ships in your fleet. Read the other ships and identify the people that you think would be good for your ship. Another course of action would be to ask for recommendations from other role-players as to who might be best.</para>
			<para>The official Star-fleet IRC channel and other Instant Messenger programs are also excellent places to look for new people. Other places to look include the publish fleet reports in the Command Ship and see what players have been spotlighted for their performances. Always remember to do a bit of research on a player you are going to approach, if you can.</para>
			<para>Also remember that the Personnel Department (PDept) operates a vacancies list for each ship. You should work with your CO to ensure that the PDept has the right information to keep this up to date.</para>
			<para>Just as it is important to know where to recruit people from, you must know where you CANNOT recruit people. Under no circumstances can you approach a cadet in the academy about joining your ship until AFTER they have graduated and been placed in the main fleets. This is a clear rule of the club. If a cadet approaches you to join your ship while still a cadet you must decline them and refer the matter to the Academy Commandant.</para>
			<para>It is acceptable to contact the Academy Commandant about any potential graduates or recent graduates that they feel might be good for your ship. The Academy is here to help mainstream ships, not just the Academy Fleet.</para>
			<para>Recruiting someone should always be done on an individual basis with an email sent to the person you want to recruit and copied to your CO. Mass emailing is regarded as Spam in STF and is an offence.</para>
			<para>When you are looking for a potential candidate to join your ship you should look for several things. Look for the level of detail in their posts, since there is nothing worse on a ship than one liners. Look at the speed and frequency of their posting. Are they too slow for your ship? Will the sim and posting move on too quickly for them to keep up? Are they too fast for the speed of your ship? Will they lose interest and motivation? How well does the candidate interact with other people? Do they enjoy rping with everyone or only a select few 'friends'? Will they fit with the crew? Do they play off the wall or strange characters? Will these character types fit in on your ship?</para>
			<para>If you are recruiting for a particular position, say for a department head, look at the potential candidate with that requirement in mind. How do they give orders? Do they have leadership skills? Are they team motivated? Do they provide positive reinforcement? How do they act OOC? Do they keep busy? Think of the position you have. Do you need experience or would an inexperienced role-player be fine? Is there a player on your own ship you could promote up to DH?</para>
			<para>You might have to look at several ships and it is always worthwhile checking the player profile. Find out how many ships they are on. Will they have time to devote to one more ship? Will the amount of ships they are on detract from yours?</para>
			<para>At the end of the day the only way you can find out if a player is interested is to approach them (obviously decide this with the CO). Don't be surprised or offended if the player declines the offer. We all have real lives and some players set limits on the amount of ships they are on. Thank them for their consideration.</para>
			<para>Recruitment can be a thankless chore and rejection may happen several times before you get a suitable candidate, but never lose hope or sight of the fact you are doing this to improve your ship.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-108">
		<title>Conflict Management</title>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution>Arnold Glasgow</attribution>
			<para>"One of the tests of leadership is the ability to recognize a problem before it becomes an emergency."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>It is a topic that no one likes to think about but there are times when people don't get on and you might have to deal with complaints.</para>
		<para>This can happen for any number of reasons but you have to act to deal with a situation. Never sit on a problem or try to ignore it. The problems only get worse.</para>
		<para>How to deal with a problem or a complaint can be outlined in the following stages.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Acknowledge the complaint</emphasis> - Make sure you respond to the person sending the email saying that you have received the information and are looking into it. Always copy the CO in. Don't commit to the complaint or agree with it. You have to remain impartial. Agree to look into the matter further and, if possible, give a date when you will be back in touch with an update. Explain the situation if there is going to be a delay. Be polite, be clear and be understanding. Never agree with the problem until you have looked into the matter further. Remember to tell the person not to discuss this matter on the ship.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Assess the problem</emphasis> - Is this an issue you can really deal with yourself? Can you make a judgment or a decision? Is this something simple or is this complex? Is this just miscommunication? Take your time; don't run into a hasty decision. Discuss the problem with the CO and get their input. It is their ship after all. The CO may take the problem off your hands.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Investigate</emphasis> - With the permission of the CO you can contact the other participants in the problem, if required. Always be polite and be professional. Remember you could be dealing with hurt feelings or people who did not even know there was an issue. Try to get their side of the story and any supporting evidence. Be patient and be understanding. Remember what one person sees as an insult another might take as a compliment. Once more remind the participants that they should not discuss this matter on the ship.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Assess the evidence</emphasis> - Look at the evidence. Can you see what the cause of the problem is? Sometimes it can be something really small and simple that has hurt feelings. Never belittle the complaint. Discuss the evidence with the CO. Can you make a decision?</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Making a decision</emphasis> - With the help of the previous four points and discussions with your CO you should be in a position to understand the problem and its cause. With this information you must make the decision with your CO as to whether you can handle this problem yourself or the problem should be handed upwards for the CO to officially review. Remember to be calm, courteous, understanding and impartial. Your decision must be the best for the ship.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Your job is to maintain the ship to the best standards. Sometimes this means making a hard decision but in the end you must look after the interests of the ship first.</para>
		<para>Good luck!</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-conclusion">
		<title>Conclusion</title>
		<para>With thanks to Jack "Dippy" Dipper, Jen "Sloth" Herr, Sarah "Kat" Hemenway.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xo-exam">
		<title>Exam</title>
		<para>Submission Instructions</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Write out your answers to the questions below.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>E-mail them to the course grader: <ulink url="mailto:command-xo-tutor@star-fleet.com?subject=STF Command XO Exam">Symon Silvester</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Be sure to include your full name at the top of the e-mail!</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Send the original question followed by your answers.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> send your answers as an attachment.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> use "HTML-enriched" e-mail.  It makes it harder to grade.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>All answers must be original.  Do not simply copy and paste from the lessons.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<section>
			<title>Multiple Choice Questions</title>
			<para>1. What is the OOC chain of command on a ship/base?</para>
			<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
				<listitem><para>JO > DH > GM > XO > CO</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>JO > DH > XO > CO > FCOMM</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>CO only</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>FComm only</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>2. Who can you not recruit?</para>
			<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
				<listitem><para>An ensign from another fleet</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Someone on more than five ships</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Cadets from the Academy</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Someone at the rank of Captain and above.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>3. What does LADA mean?</para>
			<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
				<listitem><para>Look Assess Decide Act</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Look Agree Discuss Act</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Look Assess Delay Act</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Look Ask Discuss Act</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>4. Which of the following can an XO not do In Character?</para>
			<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
				<listitem><para>Take command of the ship if the CO is incapacitated</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Promote someone himself</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Organize a music festival</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Take command of an away team.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>5. Which of the following is a mandatory requirement of being an XO?</para>
			<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
				<listitem><para>Cleaning the roster</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>AWOLing players</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recruiting</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Completing Fleet Reports.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>6. How many XO positions may you have at one time (excluding the Academy)?</para>
			<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
				<listitem><para>One</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Two</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Three</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>As many as you want</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>7. According to FCOMM what is the primary duty of an XO in addition to role-playing duties?</para>
			<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
				<listitem><para>To have fun</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>To report to the FComm</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>To cover for the CO in the event of a LOA or AWOL</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>To monitor the OOC Comments on a ship</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Short Answer Section</title>
			<para>Answer the following in your own words. Do NOT cut and paste.</para>
			<para>8.	In your own words, describe what the position of an XO is on a ship.</para>
			<para>9.	In your own words, describe the relationship between a CO and an XO</para>
			<para>10.	In your own words, describe the In Character chain of command</para>
			<para>11.	In your own words, describe a situation where you would have to speak directly to the FComm about your ship?</para>
			<para>12.	In your own words, describe how you would handle a complaint from a junior officer about an OOC comment that another junior officer had made on the ship.</para>
			<para>13.	You have been asked to recruit a new CSO for your ship. In your own words, identify two places that you might look for a candidate and how you might select the right person for the role.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Short Essay Section</title>
			<para>14.	Write an AWOL email to Ensign X who is currently 10 days out on the ship. You have heard he might have had a family emergency.</para>
			<para>15.	Discuss the benefits and drawbacks to OOC Comments on a ship including how you would keep the number of comments to an acceptable level.</para>
			<para>16.	You are temporarily in charge of a ship while the CO and GM are on LOA between main sims. Give three basic side sim outlines of how to keep people busy. You may choose specific departments or the ship as a whole.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Essay Section</title>
			<para>17.	You are the XO of the USS Nelson, a Pendragon Class Battle Cruiser. While answering a distress call from a disabled freighter you were attacked by an unknown type of vessel. The first attack caught the ship by surprise and your shields were down at the time. The Captain was on the way to the bridge at the time, but you have lost contact with him in the attack. You do not know where he is or what his condition is. The Nelson is damaged and there is at least one hull breach, as well as reports of injured coming through. The freighter has two hundred people aboard and is completely defenseless. The COS, CNS and the CSO are on the bridge. The CMO is in sickbay and the CE is in engineering. You have communications to both CMO and CE. You are also on the bridge. Write an in character post building on this incident, give your orders to each department and set an example. At the end of the post do an OOC explanation of your rationale for your orders at the end.</para>
			<para>18.	Imagine you are the CO of a ship and are appointing a brand new Executive Officer, one who has no experience of being an XO on a ship before. Describe in your own words what you expect from your new XO both In Character and Out of Character and what advice you would give.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>
