<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="textbook-gamemaster">
	<title>Gamemaster</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Deanne</firstname>
				<surname>Ashton</surname>
				<email></email>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>19 September 2005</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Added to Library</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section id="gm-intro">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Welcome to the Academy's Gamemaster (GM) course, offered in cooperation with STF's GM Department (GMD). This course is designed with both the potential and veteran GM in mind. If you've got a story idea and you want to be a GM, this course will help you know what to expect when you get that first GM assignment. If you're a GM with one or one hundred sims under your belt, this course will give you ideas of how to be a better GM, and how to successfully make it through the rough patches that are bound to occur.</para>
		<para>The first and most important thing for you to know before you move past this page is that a GM's job is to entertain his assigned crew. Contrary to a very popular belief, being the GM doesn't make you a puppetmaster nor a god. The crew isn't there to do your bidding; you're there to show the crew a good time.</para>
		<para>Think of a GM as a cruise director. His job is to make sure all the passengers are happy and have things to do. He gives them a choice of activities from which to choose so they're not bored, even if it means everyone is doing something a little bit different. He also makes sure no one throws the deck chairs around. Just one passenger flinging a chaise lounge is liable to ruin the cruise for the others.</para>
		<para>Being a GM requires juggling talent, ego, and humility within a ring of common sense. You have to be tolerant without being a pushover; strong without being overbearing; flexible without being unfocused; and most of all, able to put the needs/wants of the crew above your own personal desires.</para>
		<para>Still think you have what it takes? Great! Let's proceed to the first lesson.
</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-101">
		<title>Finding Your Idea</title>
		<para>When you're a GM the first thing you need is a story. After all, it's hard to run a sim if you have no plot. There is no hard, fast rule on where to get story ideas. Inspiration is as unique as each GM, and can be found everywhere. Television, books, movies, magazines, even the news can provide story ideas. Look around, your next story could be hidden in the autumn leaves.</para>
		<para>For me, I find a lot of inspiration from the STF characters, themselves. For instance, if the CO of the ship is a Bajoran, what better antagonist can you find besides a Cardassian? Or maybe another character has lost one spouse to divorce, and another to death. What would happen if that character were forced to marry to save a Federation alliance?</para>
		<para>The plot is only limited by your imagination. However, there are a few guidelines to follow to make sure the crew loves the story as much as you do.</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Make sure the plot is big enough to keep everyone busy. If it's not, you may have to add a secondary storyline to involve those left out.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Avoid scenarios used to death in STF, as well as plots your ship has seen before. Check with the CO of the ship to which you're assigned. Ask him if he has preferences. Make sure that the battle sim you have planned isn't going to be the third one in a row the ship's been dealt.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Familiarize yourself with your ship's class. A wonderful sim exploring the exobiology of a newly-discovered planet won't work well on a Trafalgar or Kansas. Just as sending a McCoy into battle is suicide. Determine a ship's capabilities ahead of time, too, so you don't have a ship doing a saucer seperation that would normally only be possible if it were blown in two.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Make sure your plot is plausible. Sure, it'd be really cool if the ship crash-landed, but unless the ship is capable of sub-orbital flight, don't expect it to fly again. Likewise you can't do anything that contradicts canon.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Finally, avoid rehashing Trek episodes and overusing Trek characters and ships. STF has its own ships. Rely on them. Keep appearances by Trek characters to cameos.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>Okay, you were out for a bike ride the other day and a great story idea came to you. You've read the guidelines, have studied the ship's specs, and made sure no one has done a story about wheeled aliens. What's next?</para>
		<para>The next class. See you there.</para>
		<para>TIP FOR THIS LESSON:</para>
		<para>Your story idea cannot be so grandiose that it becomes a Trek version of the Neverending Story. If your story is one of sweeping proportions, you don't have to abandon it. Just break it down into individual sims, each one with an ending that segues into the next.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-102">
		<title>Turning the Idea into a Sim</title>
		<para>So you have your idea, now its time to turn that idea into a sim. For me, sitting down and planning a sim is one of the most enjoyable parts of being a GM. The creative process moves into full gear, and there is no limit to what a GM can imagine. The Planning Stage of a sim consists of creating the setting and the characters. GMs create the worlds that starship crews visit, ranging from an icy world at the edge of a solar system to a bustling spaceport filled with the slim of the galaxy. GMs also create the colorful cast of characters that will interact with the crew of the starship. Characters can include the dusty Starfleet admiral, the motherly diplomat, or the scheming villain. Whatever the GM ultimately conjures up at this point, there is one thing to keep in mind: The sky is the limit. Be creative. Be original. And above all, be daring.</para>
		<para>But what of the plot? The plot marks a common stumbling block for many GMs. One common mistake it trying to plan the entire sim in the Planning Stage. This is impossible. The GM interacts with many real live people in a role-playing environment. Each role-player enters the arena with their own unique backgrounds, cultures, and viewpoints. This diversity greatly affects the way a sim plays out. The players push the sim in directions the GM may not have anticipated, as well as often bring new ideas and thoughts to the sim. This often forces the GM to improvise and may even spark new ideas the GM had not previously considered. The bottom line is this: The GM and the players are on the journey together. It is a symbiotic relationship. The GM presents the story and guides the crew through plot points, and the players challenge the obstacles and bring new ideas to the story, which may ultimately make the story better.</para>
		<para>So how much plot do I need at the Planning Stage? Well, not a whole lot. The process of creating the plot for a sim is best likened to the making of Steven Spielberg's Jurassic Park III, which some of you may be familiar with.</para>
		<para>For the making of Jurassic Park III, Spielberg had a solid beginning. So should a GM. The GM should have a good idea of the characters, the setting, and the major plot points that will get the story rolling. This must accomplish getting the crew where they should be, having the crew meet the people they should meet, and putting them into the situation that they are playing out.</para>
		<para>For Jurassic Park III, Spielberg had a vague idea of how he wanted the movie to end. So should a GM. The conclusion, unlike the beginning, should not have major plot points. In all reality, a GM cannot predict the outcome of a sim. In my experience, a sim has never ended even close to how I thought it would. This is caused by the diversity of the players, which is normal. Therefore only a vague idea of where you are going should suffice for an ending.</para>
		<para>Jurassic Park III was unique from most movies, in that Spielberg had no real idea of what would happen in the middle of the movie when he started filming. Although this is a bad way to make a movie, it is a perfect way to plan a sim. A GM should have no real middle part to a sim. A few plot points may sit in the back of a GMs mind, put these should not be set in stone. Things change and new directions are taken. New GMs will often try to hit their middle plot points. This can be frustrating when the crew heads off in another direction. GMs are often discouraged at this point. Instead, the GM should adapt, and go with the flow, or risk being inflexible. Inflexible GMs can often find themselves butting heads with players or causing the crew to lose interest in their sims. Neither of which is desirable.</para>
		<para>The GM should enjoy seeing what direction the crew heads off in. One thing to keep in mind: Good sims keep the crew busy. A GM is required to constantly create new obstacles or challenges for the crew to encounter. Many ships and sims have suffered when players find there is 'nothing to do'. The GM must consider this when planning sims.</para>
		<para>Also as a side note, the stronger and more experience GMs develop the ability to run a sim without a sim outline, working off their story idea and making the rest up as they go. Although this can be a rewarding experience I would recommend newer GMs plan a sim outline to assist in giving them direction.</para>
		<para>TIP FOR THIS LESSON:</para>
		<para>Make sure your story will make a good sim. The best way to do that is to remember that it's the journey to the end that satisfies a roleplayer. The story has to be interesting enough that the players want to see how it ends, and are willing to work through the obstacles you throw in their paths. Make the players care and you've got them to the end.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-103">
		<title>Running the Sim</title>
		<para>Now that you have your idea, know more or less how your idea will play out in a sim, it is now time to review the methods you can use to present your sim. GMs have a couple of methods of giving information to the players and moving the sim along. They include Narrative posts, Interactive posts, and what I call Elsewhere Posts.</para>
		<para></para>
		<section>
			<title>Narrative Posts</title>
			<para>The Narrative Post most often comes across as an all-knowing voice. In other words, the post from the GM knows all. These types of posts are generally used to accomplish two types of tasks, all though I am sure this list is not all-inclusive. The first task is to set a chain of events in motion.</para>
			<example>
				<title>Narrative Posts - Style One</title>
				<para>Suddenly the rundown freighter the USS Anyname had been escorting exploded in a blinding flash of light, sending debris in all directions.</para>
			</example>
			<para>As you can see this post is meant to set the crew of the USS Anyname in motion. GMs often use this type of post to convey plot points of their sim.</para>
			<para>The second way the Narrative post can be used is to convey information as a result of a player's action. Think of this as sensor readouts, diagnostic results, or data from the ships library computer. These posts come in handy when players try to gather more information in the sim.</para>
			<example>
				<title>Narrative Posts - Style Two</title>
				<para>A player may post: Lt. Anywho activated the sensors and began to scan the debris. He desperately searched for any survivors from the explosion.</para>
				<para>A GM's response would be: Sensors showed several life signs in the largest section of debris.</para>
			</example>
			<para>As you can see this type of post will often be instrumental in giving players feedback on the results of the actions they take.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Interactive Posts</title>
			<para>The Interactive Post can often be the most fun to write. These posts are usually in response to the sim characters you created in lesson two interacting with the players. A GM can use sim characters to convey all types of information, ranging from explaining why the villain of the sim is trying to destroy a planet, or what background information the Intelligence Agent has on certain smugglers. I encourage every GM to make your characters as real and as deep as the characters the role-players have developed. This will enrich your story and get the role-players to invest themselves in your characters.</para>
			<example>
				<title>Interactive Posts</title>
				<para>A player may post: So did you notice anything unusual before you heard the explosion, "Lt Anywho asked as he interviewed the survivor.</para>
				<para>A GM's response would be: The injured man, an elderly Bajoran, nodded to the question, "I heard weapons fire. Lots of it... I stuck my head out of the cargo hold to see what I could and that's when I saw a Cardassian running my direction!"</para>
			</example>
			<para>Here the GM has used a character he developed to convey information that the crew can now dig deeper into. The one thing about the Interactive post is that it is not an all-knowing character. The character should only know and be able to convey information that the character would reasonably have. So in the example, the Bajoran wouldn't know if the Cardassians were from a group of radicals out to resurrect the Bajoran occupation. The more creative the characters are, the more fun you and the crew will have role-playing it out.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Elsewhere Posts</title>
			<para>This type of post should really be used sparingly. Often times I have seen it used in moderation in the start and end of a sim. Basically, this is a post where one or more of the GMs sim characters are interacting with each other, or with themselves.</para>
			<example>
				<title>Elsewhere Posts</title>
				<para>The Cardassian Commander shook his head as he saw the latest sensor readings. The Starfleet vessel had found survivors. This was not good. He slowly swiveled in his chair and turned to the helmsman. "Set an intercept course," he ordered, "Maximum warp."</para>
			</example>
			<para>As you can see this GM post takes place in an area where there cannot possibly be any of the role-players. Therefore, no players can respond or play off this post, since none of their characters would be aware of this. The benefit of using this post is to create suspense or a deeper understanding the players of what this sim is about. In the example, it now tells the player someone else is out there and could possibly come after the Starfleet crew. It creates anticipation, suspense, or can be used to close up a thread, or even a sim. Use this sparingly only because the sim is meant to get role-players involved. Just using Elsewhere posts basically means you are playing your sim to yourself. That can't be much fun!</para>
		</section>
		<para>A strong GM has mastered all these types of posts and is able to pull them together in perfect harmony to tell his sim and entertain the players.</para>
		<para>TIP OF THE LESSON:</para>
		<para>While I have yet to come across a quick sim in STF (most average five to sixth months), that doesn't mean you should let your sim meander along for years. Presenting a journey too long and arduous can make the players bored and/or frustrated long before they reach the end. And those obstacles I mentioned earlier, the ones you throw in the path of your crew to keep things interesting: Make sure they're surmountable. I remember a sim on a ship I commanded that resulted in the entire senior staff being locked in the holodeck. The engineers who remained free tried all kinds of things to break into the holodeck, but the GM never let them succeed. Rather than keep trying, the players went AWOL after two weeks of trying to solve the puzzle.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-104">
		<title>The Ways of the GM</title>
		<para>So you have your idea, turned it into a sim, know how to run your sim. That should be it right. Not quite. This lesson is designed to let you know the role of the GM on a starship. Most of the following rules and guidelines are simple common sense. All of them come from experience, a few are even laws. Pay attention. Abiding by them can make your GMing more pleasant; for you and your ship.</para>
		<para>Now make like Charlton Heston and accept these Ten Commandments:</para>
		<para><emphasis>Thou shalt not destroy thine assigned starship without prior approval of the CO and FComm.</emphasis> Very little can match the thrill of wreaking havoc to a starship. Many GMs I know delight in hull breaches, failed shields, and sparking bridge consoles. Before you lose matter/antimatter containment on that warp core, however, make sure you have the blessing of both the captain and fleet commander.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Thou shalt not covet thy captain's duties.</emphasis> Some people think of the GM as the god. To some extent that's true. The GM dictates the fate of the players and the ship. He controls what happens in their lives. However, a GM's deity status doesn't extend beyond the story. The GM cannot and does not interfere with the running of the ship. He doesn't write Captain's Logs, he doesn't AWOL players, he doesn't redesign the MOTD, he doesn't give players positions on the ship. That is the captain's job.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Honor thy players' wishes.</emphasis> I've said it before but I'll say it again. Your job is to entertain the crew. If the players are not enjoying your sim, makes changes. Ultimately, it doesn't matter if you think your sim is great unless the players agree.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Thou shalt not kill - until three Death Warnings are issued.</emphasis> Once upon a time, a player character could not be killed unless the player said so. Unfortunately, this begat a series of super-being players who would have their characters do death-defying and often very stupid things in a sim. After all, characters couldn't die. So who was to stop someone from taking on six heavily-armed Klingons by himself? This abuse by a handful of players led to the adoption of a Three Strike Rule. If someone does something really stupid - something that would probably end up with the person being killed, maimed, or otherwise incapcitated - the GM can issue a Death Warning. If the same player persists in this type of posting, the GM can continue to issue Death Warnings. Upon issuance of the third warning, the GM is allowed to kill that character. Death Warnings are serious stuff. Don't issue them without due cause.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Honor Star Trek canon and keep it holy.</emphasis> Always anchor your storyline with plausibility. It's true that the universe in which we play is one of science fiction, but that's no excuse to create things that don't mesh with Trek physics. If you're not sure about the plausibility of a plot point, research it. Here, ignorance is not bliss. By the same token, do not rewrite that which has been written. You cannot rewrite Trek history.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Follow thy chain of command.</emphasis> In a perfect world, everyone would get along. Each day would be filled with sunshine and your work would be applauded by the newest ensign all the way to the most venerated admiral. What a shame our world isn't perfect. In our world, chances are pretty good that you're going to have a problem with one of your GM assignments. Maybe a player keeps writing counteractive posts. Maybe the captain isn't holding up his end. Maybe there's a personality clash. Whatever the problem, always remember to follow the chain of command. Start with the CO. If the problem can't be rectified, you then go to the fleet commander. If you still can't get resolution, you can approach the GM Director for input. Only after you've trod upon each rung above you without success do you go to the president.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Thou shalt not be a GM before being a GMT.</emphasis> If you're not already a GM, you must participate in a GM Training program through the GM Department. It doesn't matter if you've mastered live action games and ran players through dozens of have-dice-will-travel dungeons. It doesn't matter if you're the best roleplayer in STF. Everyone must participate in the GMT program before being certified as a GM. If you are as good as you think you are, you'll be running people's lives in no time, anyway. A couple of months with a mentor looking over your shoulder isn't going to stop that from happening.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Know thine HTML and keep thy MOTD section current.</emphasis> Every ship's page (MOTD) I've ever seen has a section for the GM. You use this space to keep the crew updated on what's happening. You can also use it to foreshadow events and provide other minutiae, such as names, places, what-have-you. The ship's CO provides this place for you as a courtesy. Don't abuse it. Be sure to update your section as often as necessary. Don't make your section so long it makes up more than half the MOTD's contents. Also, don't change the way the section is coded. If the CO has it set up as a paragraph with blue text, don't make it a bulleted list in pink. If you're unfamiliar with HTML code take extra precaution that you don't rip the MOTD to shreds by accident. It's best to be at least somewhat familiar with the basic codes before you go about changing anything.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Remember thine posting requirements and keep active.</emphasis> With a ship's entire reality resting on the shoulders of the GM, it's vital that you post regularly. Never go AWOL. That means know the ship's posting requirements and stay well within them. Most require a post every three to four days. However, since your job is to entertain the crew, a more brisk posting regime may be necessary. Post as frequently as required to keep the story moving and remain within AWOL guidelines.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Thou shalt not antagonize thine enemies.</emphasis> It's bound to happen. You are the GM on a ship with someone you don't like. Being a GM does not give you the authority to make that player's life hell. Sure it would be great fun to lock up your sworn nemesis with a lovestruck moose. Yes, assimilation may do wonders for another foe's personality. The temptation - even the justification - can be strong. Do not give in to it. Doing so only serves to shorten your GM career.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-105">
		<title>Advice to Remember</title>
		<para>Before you go, take a moment and read what other GMs throughout the years have said. It will be on the exam!</para>
		<para>It was my first official sim. I planned the whole thing out, from beginning to end. I had every event worked out. I was very inflexible as the sim progressed, not having experience with running a sim. The result: The crew lost interest, and I had to narrate the end just to get the darn thing over with! That was my bad GM experience.</para>
		<para>A new GM was supposed to take over [after my sim was finished]. When that person AWOLed, I was put in the GM spot again. This time, I had nothing planned - I hadn't expected to be GMing! As it turned out, this was a good thing. My next sim was very spontaneous, and I had no trouble compensating for crew interest and keeping all departments active. The crew posted almost 100% daily by the end. It went great. Overall, I would advise new GMs to be flexible. Don't hold to your perfect mental image of what should happen - make sure the crew's having fun. Don't plan everything, just have a couple of good ideas.</para>
		<para>Be honest with the crew. If you make a mistake, admit it. Don't be afraid to be human. If a player posts something that you don't understand (a bit of physics you don't grasp or a hunk of engineering with which you're unfamiliar) ask the player to explain. Not only will you get the information you're lacking, you'll make the player feel good for being so creative.</para>
		<para>Develop a good rapport with the command staff of the ship. Communicate often with the CO (but I don't advise pestering him/her ), and make sure that the ship is running smoothly. If activity isn't what it should be, then it's important for the CO and GM to figure out a way to get more people involved in the sim.</para>
		<para>Make sure that your sim can involve every department on a ship. That's probably the most difficult aspect of developing a sim; something I've found rather annoying is that a sim will leave out a department entirely, leaving them to fend for themselves. Counselors, in particular, seem to get the shaft when a sim is being run; assignments will be divvied out, and then the counselor is stuck with crew evaluations or the like. Try to ensure that every department on the ship can be utilized.</para>
		<para>Ask questions if you're stuck. If there's a particular piece of technobabble that someone brings up in a sim that confounds you, then ask for advice from someone else; the GM Monitor (if applicable), the CO, someone from the Engineering Department.</para>
		<para>Never try to outline every movement that will take place within a sim. It is extremely important to allow the players to have some flexibility within the sim; people will undoubtedly come up with ideas that the GM would never think of, and it's important to keep that in mind as much as possible. By the same token, though, it's equally important to not let the players run away with the sim by grandstanding, et al. If one person tries to run away with the sim on his own by doing something that's next to impossible, then the GM needs to put the skids to that so that solving a sim can be a team effort.</para>
		<para>Regardless of skill, a GM needs to have a good rapport with the crew. Whether it's as an evil mastermind, a benevolent leader, a weenie, he has to be on very good terms with them.</para>
		<para>You should always give freedom of expression to the players on a ship. It tends to make things more pleasent for everyone, and it reminds you that you're not there for yourself but for the crew. Your main mission is to make sure that everyone on the ship has a chance to express themselves creatively and to contribute to the sim and interact with others.</para>
		<para>If you know you're taking a long LOA, don't accept a GM position. If you're already a GM and you have to go away, either leave enough to keep the crew busy while you're gone, or find someone to GM in your place.</para>
		<para>Creative roleplayers often have little side sims going in addition to their participation in the main sim. If you see a way to incorporate their story into yours, be sure to ask them before you take over.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-conclusion">
		<title>Conclusion</title>
		<para>You're now armed with all the GM theory you're going to need to get started as a GM, or improve upon your GMing skills. That doesn't mean there isn't anymore to learn. Even after years as a GM for STF, I'm still learning new things. Like life, GMing always changes.</para>
		<para>If you've paid attention to what was said in this course; if you thought about the advice the other GMs provided; you're building on a solid foundation. Enjoy the journey.</para>
		<para>Now it's time for the exam. Don't worry, it's not that hard. Not if you paid attention.</para>
		<para>I'd like to take this opportunity to give credit where credit is due. The following individuals assisted in one way or another over the lifespan of this course (idea to fruition). My apologies to anyone I accidentally neglected to mention: Chris Ashley, Steve Ashton, Mike Bourdaa, Stuart Coll, Jeremy Friedman, Larry Garfield, Brian Moss, Mackael Stockhausen, Owen Townes, and Moe Younis.</para>
		<para>Now go on, go. Take that exam. The sooner you take it, the sooner you'll be GMing. Good luck!</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-exam">
		<title>Exam</title>
		<para>Submission Instructions</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Write out your answers to the questions below.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>E-mail them to the course grader: <ulink url="mailto:goeagle15@gmail.com">Sarah Hemenway</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Be sure to include your full name at the top of the e-mail!</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> send the original question, just the answers.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> send your answers as an attachment.  Send them in the body of the e-mail.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> use "HTML-enriched" e-mail.  It makes it harder to grade.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>All answers must be original.  Do not simply copy and paste from the lessons.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<section>
			<title>GM 101</title>
			<para>List the five important guidelines to consider when picking out a story idea for your sim. (10 points)</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>GM 102</title>
			<para>When taking your story idea and planning it into a sim, explain how to develop your outline, in terms of how you should create the beginning, middle, and end. (10 points)</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>GM 103</title>
			<para>When running your sim, explain the three basic types of posts that are available to you and what they can accomplish. (10 points)</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>GM 104</title>
			<para>Discuss two of the GM Ten Commandments that you feel are the most important and why. (10 points)</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>GM 105</title>
			<para>Discuss three important pieces of advice the GMs in this lesson gave the reader. (10 points)</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>GM 106</title>
			<para>List three things in the Administrative Menu that are not to be used by Gamemasters. (10 points)</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Final Question</title>
			<para>As you can see, this section of the exam is worth the most and it can cause you to pass or fail the entire exam. Break out your best English skills, because they're going to count a bit toward those points. What? That's not fair? Well, how do you expect to GM well if you if you cant put forth your ideas in a clear, concise manner?</para>
			<para>Write down a brief sim idea that you would like to do. (5 points)</para>
			<para>Write down the outline for only the beginning of this sim. Describe one or two characters you would like to have the crew interact with. Also mention something about the setting and how you will get events set in motion. The more descriptive you are, the more points you will get. (35 points)</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>
