<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">-->
<article id="textbook-gamemaster">
	<title>Gamemaster</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>David</firstname>
				<surname>Wonderly</surname>
				<email>gamemaster-tutor@star-fleet.com</email>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
          <revision>
            <revnumber>1</revnumber>
            <date>19 September 2005</date>
            <revdescription>
              <para>Added to Library</para>
            </revdescription>
          </revision>
          <revision>
            <revnumber>2</revnumber>
            <date>13 October 2005</date>
            <revdescription>
              <para>Changed course proctor to Amanda Noon</para>
            </revdescription>
          </revision>
		  <revision>
		  	<revnumber>3</revnumber>
			<date>6 December 2005</date>
			<revdescription>
				<para>Course rewritten by Amanda Noon</para>
		  <revision>
            <revnumber>4</revnumber>
            <date>2nd January 2011</date>
            <revdescription>
              <para>Changed course proctor to David Wonderly</para> 
            </revdescription>
          </revision>
		  <revision>
            <revnumber>5</revnumber>
            <date>27th March 2011</date>
            <revdescription>
              <para>Course rewritten by Helen Hosick</para> 
            </revdescription>
          </revision>
			</revdescription>
		  </revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section id="introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
			<epigraph>
			<attribution>Voltaire</attribution>
			<para> "Each player must accept the cards life deals him or her. But once they are in hand, he or she alone must decide how to play the cards in order to win the game."</para>
		</epigraph>
		<para>Welcome to the Villain’s Guide to Evil... er, I mean, the Gamemaster (GM) course. This course is brought you by the letter 'E' for Evil by the STF's Department of Evil and Mischief (muhahaha)... I mean, STF's Gamemaster Department (GMD). This course will help you understand what it takes to be a Gamemaster and guide your story idea into a sim. It will provide insight to the world of 'Gamemastering', as well as beginner's tips that will help you succeed during your Gamemaster Training. If you already are a Gamemaster, this course may provide new tips, insight or simply a refresher to what you already know.</para>
		<para>In order for one to become part of the Dark Side, er, Gamemaster in STF you must have achieved the following:</para>
		<para>-Be an STF member for a minimum of six (6) months;</para>
		<para>-Hold a minimum rank of Full Lieutenant (somewhere in the club);</para>
		<para>-Pass this exam; and</para>
		<para>-Go through the Gamemaster Trainee (GMT) program.</para>
		<para>This is specified by the Omnibus GMD Revisions Edict (OGRE), which establishes the GMD and guidelines for GMs.</para>
		<para>It can be found <a href="http://www.star-fleet.com/library/bookshelf/charters/charter-gmd.html">Here</a></para>
		<para>Don't worry, we'll include a summary and overview for OGRE if you don't want to read through the fine details of red tape.</para>
		<para>Every GM must go through the GMT program, before being certified as GM. Sorry, we might be the department of evil, but bribery to skip your GMT training is against our departmental bylaws. Plus, it ensures that players like you, have excellent Gamemasters to play on our fine ships. Passing this exam is the first step to becoming a GM. Good luck on surviving this exam... muahahahaha.</para>
		<para>Throughout this course you will have some tasks(called "Homework") to do, these tasks are to be submitted with your exam at the end.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="what is a gamemaster">
		<title>What is a Gamemaster?</title>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution>Q from Spock Versus Q</attribution>
				<para>"It's swell! Being Q is just swell! It's clear than a bell, it's faster than pell mell, greater runs than hell, no need to under sell, it's swell!"</para>
			</epigraph>
		<para>A Gamemaster is the person who is in charge of entertaining his or her assigned crew. As the Gamemaster, it's not your duty to run the ship and it's not your duty to hound people for going AWOL. It is, however, your duty to be loyal to Star Trek Canon, our own club's canon and to have integrity to your sim.</para>
		<para>"Regardless of skill, a GM needs to have a good rapport with the crew. Whether it’s as an evil mastermind, a benevolent leader, a weenie, he has to be on very good terms with them." (Unknown GM)</para>
		<para>Think of it this way, the ship is a cruise liner, and you're the activities director... save that as activities director, you're really not on the ship, and you shape reality to the activities you had in mind. You give them all the activities from which to choose from so they aren't bored, even if it means everyone is doing something different. You also make certain that no one is being overly rowdy, attempting suicide (unless you feel really evil and letting them), or throwing deck chairs around. Just one passenger flinging a chaise lounge is liable to ruin the cruise for the others.</para>
		<para>"Be honest with the crew. If you make a mistake, admit it. Don't be afraid to be human. If a player posts something that you don't understand (a bit of physics you don't grasp or a hunk of engineering with which you're unfamiliar) ask the player to explain. Not only will you get the information you're lacking, you'll make the player feel good for being so creative." (Unknown GM)</para>
		<para>Being a GM requires juggling ego, talent and humility within a ring of common sense. You have to be tolerant without being a pushover; strong without being overbearing; flexible without being unfocused; and most of all, able to put the needs/wants of the crew above your own personal desires.</para>
		<para>A GM needs to be professional. One of the old GM commandments was "Thou shalt not antagonize thine enemies", this still stands. It’s bound to happen; you are the GM on a ship with someone you don’t like, being a GM does not give you the authority to make that player’s life hell. Sure it would be great fun to lock up your sworn nemesis with a love struck moose. Yes, assimilation may do wonders for another foe’s personality. The temptation - even the justification - can be strong; do NOT give in to it, doing so only serves to shorten your GM career.</para>
		<para>We might all have God complexes... well, most of us do anyway, but it doesn't give us the right to be jerks or like Doctor Gregory House. Being the GM is being God with a small twist... benevolent, humble but with a touch of chaos. As much power as we have over the crew, we're still subject to the will of the Captain, Fleet Captain, and anyone else above that. Just remember, the Captain has more power in Real Life than you do in game. He or she can fire you if they are dissatisfied with you. If you encounter an issue with a player, and you're uncertain how to deal with it, talk with the player and talk with the Captain and First Officer. We'll cover more about dealing with difficult situations and players later.</para>
		<para>"Ask questions if you're stuck. If there's a particular piece of technobabble that someone brings up in a sim that confounds you, then ask for advice from someone else; the GM Monitor (if applicable), the CO, someone from the Engineering Department." (Unknown GM)</para>
		<para>A GM also needs to accept that when they agree to GM a ship they are taking on a commitment to that crew and CO. He has a responsibility to post often, read all posts and work with the Command Staff to keep the ship a happy place. That means not accepting a GM spot when you know that you are going to have to go LOA for a long term within the next few weeks. Organizing with the CO as to how things will continue if you do have to go LOA and setting in place some sort of contingency plan should an emergency arise and you cannot post. We have all been grabbed by the real life monsters at times, be it illness or computer breakdown. There are ways to cope with this.</para>
		<para>Likewise, look at the posting speed on a ship. While the posting requirements may say every three to four days, as GM you will probably need to post more often. Be prepared to post as frequently as required to keep the story moving.</para>
		<para>Homework: Being a Gamemaster</para>
		<para>-What would your contingency plan be? </para>
		<para>-How important do you feel it is to be in contact with the CO and XO? </para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-rules">
		<title>Rules That GM's Need To Follow [Or how I got my OGRE tutorial in 3 easy steps]</title>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution>Albert Einstein</attribution>
				<para>"You have to learn the rules of the game. And then you have to play better than anyone else."</para>
			</epigraph>
		<para>As a Gamemaster, it is not all being power hungry and deciding the fate of the crew you are entertaining. Every month, just like the Captain and First Officer, you must make a monthly report on the status of your sim and your opinion on the health of the ship. You also need to file when you start a mission and when you end a mission, as well when there is a GM Change of the ship. Filing the start and end of a mission keeps a record of your status of a GM and allows you to move up in Gamemaster Rank.</para>
		<para>The important things you need to know about ORGE are:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>All prospective Gamemasters must be members of STF for a minimum of six (6) months;</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Have a minimum rank of full lieutenant;</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Pass the Gamemaster exam according to the standards set by the Gamemaster Department; and</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Provide to the Gamemaster Department three (3) recommendations from licensed Gamemasters with whom the prospective Gamemaster has served within the last three (3) months for a minimum of one (1) month.(A recommendation from a prospective Gamemaster's CO and/or XO may be substituted in situations where the prospective Gamemaster does not serve with three licensed Gamemasters.)</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>After you pass this exam, you will be assigned a Gamemaster Mentor (GMM) by the Gamemaster Department (GMD), in which you do have a say in whether you want the assigned GMM or a different one.</para>
		<para>At this stage, you become a GMT. Then you must find a willing victim... er, ship to train on. The ship must not be an Alternative Role Playing Area (such as the USS Ogawa, for example). If you are unable to find one, the GMD can assist you. Then you will run your sim on the ship until completion.</para>
		<para>After the first 90 days of your sim, preliminary reports will be given to you and the Gamemaster Director (GMDir) on improving your performance.</para>
		<para>Your GMM then may request 30 day extension for your training period for further observation. After one week of completing your sim, the powers at be (GMM, CO, GMDir) will decide if you have passed the training program. If you happen to fail from the training program, you can try again later in 2 weeks time.</para>
		<para>There are 4 ranks as a Gamemaster:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Junior Gamemaster (JGM)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Full Gamemaster (FGM/GM) - Also known as just Gamemaster</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Advanced Gamemaster (AGM)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Senior Gamemaster (SGM)</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		<para>You are recognized as a JGM after finishing your training program. The other ranks are conferred by the GMDir once applying for it in the GMD. 3 missions or 18 months later (whichever comes first), you'll be recognized as a FGM. After 10 missions or 36 months, you'll receive Advanced Gamemaster status. Senior Gamemaster status is achieved through 20 missions or 60 months.</para>
		<para>Disciplinary Action</para>
		<para>One thing that GMs have to do is always abide by the rules. IF the Gamemaster Director receives a complaint about a Gamemaster or has any reason to believe that a Gamemaster is abusing his authority, violating regulations or otherwise acting in an unprofessional manner; the Gamemaster Director is authorised to fully investigate the matter and, if need be, take disciplinary action.</para>
		<para>In this instance the Gamemaster Director should take the following actions:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Inform the Gamemaster in question of the potential problem. Should the Gamemaster be able to adequately explain the situation or amend their behaviour, the issue should be dropped. If the situation is irresolvable after the fact, the Gamemaster Director would take one of the following actions:</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Appoint a Gamemaster Observer (GMO) to the related Role Playing Area to monitor the situation and provide the Gamemaster Director with further details for a period of no longer than fourteen (14) days. The GMO may be any licensed Gamemaster of 		Full standing or higher. The Gamemaster Director may use information from the GMO to help determine what further action if any is necessary.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Issue a citation against the Gamemaster, with statement of explanation, which will be permanently recorded by the Gamemaster Department. Such a citation may be used against the Gamemaster in future consideration for Classification changes.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Impose a restriction against the Gamemaster for no longer than eight (8) months, with statement of explanation, restricting the Gamemaster from taking part in certain activities including, but not limited to, participating in Special Circumstances Missions, serving on more than a specified number of ships, or applying for a Classification change.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Revoke the Gamemaster's license. The Gamemaster Director must include a statement of explanation, and must also specify a Probation Period of no less than thirty (30) days and no more than six (6) months, during which time the Gamemaster in question may not reapply for their license.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		<para>Disciplinary action by the Gamemaster Director may be appealed to the President.</para>
		<para>Authority & Responsibility</para>
		<para>As a Gamemaster it is your job to provide an entertaining sim for the crew on the ship to be engaged in. However, there may be rare occasions where a character does something that has irreconcilable actions with the laws of STF, reason, or decency or with previously established RPG events. A Gamemaster may declare the posts in question to be null and void and must include a statement of explanation. Crew members are entitled to appeal any voided posts with the Gamemaster Director.</para>
		<para>As a Gamemaster you cannot go randomly killing off member’s characters, it really wouldn’t be fair.</para>
		<para>The only time you can kill off characters is as follows:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>AWOL. If the character has been declared AWOL, the Gamemaster may do whatever he likes with it, without restriction;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>The player gives consent to the Gamemaster, for whatever reason;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If the character has taken actions that, in the opinion of the Gamemaster, would result in a 90% or higher probability of death, a "Death Notice" may be served:</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>For the first Death Notice issued, the Gamemaster would publicly warn the player that their actions would kill the character, had it been real. Void the posts in question, modify the situation to reverse the extremely risky move, or shall otherwise modify the situation as to allow the character to continue to survive;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>For the second Death Notice, the results shall be the same as for the first notice; however, there shall also be an email sent by the Gamemaster to the ship's CO, XO, and to the owner of the character, warning that the character has received two death notices, and that a third will result in actual character death;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>For the third Death Notice, the Gamemaster shall rule the character has died as a result of his actions, and that character will be eliminated from the roster and their position. The CO of the ship shall have discretion as to whether to allow the person to create a new character on the same ship, and what position/rank that new character should hold on the ship;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>In the event that it is the CO who is receiving Death Notices, the Fleet Commander shall be notified. In the event that the Fleet Commander receives such notices, the President shall be informed.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>The Gamemaster may not intentionally place a player into a situation where any action (including lack of action) would result in a death situation. Unlike the real world, there must be at least one morally acceptable way to get out. Violation of this is the only acceptable grounds for overturning the Gamemaster's ruling of a "death notice".</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Any Death Notices may be appealed to the Gamemaster Director by the member receiving the Notice. If the Gamemaster is also the Gamemaster Director, it may be appealed to the Assistant Gamemaster Director</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		<para>You can bet that every Gamemaster dreams of blowing up a ship, but this causes reams of paperwork so STF has rules about this. Therefore, before blowing up any ship you must have consent from the CO and FComm.</para>
		<para>Disputes</para>
		<para>We all know that we wish we could live in a world full of roses and that there would be no upsets, but realistically we know this could never happen. Therefore, if a member isn’t happy with you as a Gamemaster, perhaps you have taken actions that they are not happy with,  then they should first come directly to you so you are given the opportunity to explain and resolve the matter. If the matter is not resolved then the chain of command is used.</para>
		<para>Gamemaster > Fleet Commander/Assistant Fleet Commander > Gamemaster Director > Assistant GM Director > President.</para>
		<para>Only the Gamemaster Director, Assistant Gamemaster Director, or President may forcibly overturn a decision of a Gamemaster and a decision of one of those parties shall be considered final.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-problems">
		<title>Common Problems That GM's Face</title>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution>Spock</attribution>
				<para>"Quite simply captain, I examined the problem from all angles, and it was plainly hopeless. Logic informed me that under the circumstances, the only logical action would have to be one of desperation. Logical decision logically arrived at."</para>
			</epigraph>	
		<para>Pace - The most common problem that trainees face is that the sim just won’t start. As a trainee you are on a deadline, you need to get the sim going so you can show what you can do. Sometimes the crew just won’t play along. The other problem with pace is if the sim grinds to a halt. Many things can cause this such as crew LOAs/AWOLs or maybe the command crew just isn’t pulling their weight and providing support.</para>
		<para>Missionless – Maybe you have a crew that isn’t participating in the sim, just spending more time side siming. This is when you need to sit back and evaluate your own posting and your sim idea. Maybe this is a time when you need to put something important at stake, something that the characters on the ship will care about and something the PLAYERS will care about. Can you fix your sim? Maybe this is one of those times where being flexible and following the players will pay off. Sometimes you may have a crew that wants you to point out every little detail and lead them fully by the hand, this can be time consuming and may lead to the crew not enjoying the sim, just as much as it can draw out the sim. Failing that, a private email to one of the crew giving them a big tip off is not frowned upon. Just don’t use this method too often.</para>
		<para>Nothing to do - Occasionally there are times when you will have crew who are just moaning that they have nothing to do, even though you are providing side plots for them. First off, look at the plots you have provided them, are there really tangible tasks for them to do? If you have provided the crew a reasonable task then you may want to have a quiet word with the CO or XO.</para>
		<para>Homework: Problem Time</para>
		<para>For each of the following explain how you would try to solve these problems:</para>
		<para>1. Slow Pace</para>
		<para>2. Crew Ignoring Sim</para>
		<para>3. Side Plots Being Ignored</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-ideas">
		<title>Ideas For Your Sim</title>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution>Ashleigh Brilliant</attribution>
				<para>"Good ideas are common - what's uncommon are people who'll work hard enough to bring them about"</para>
			</epigraph>	
		<para>Ideas can spring from anywhere your imagination takes you. Only you can limit your ideas. One thing that all Gamemaster’s must do is abide by Star Trek Canon, you cannot go rewriting history. It is a big No No!</para>
		<para>As a Gamemaster you can find a lot of inspiration from the STF characters themselves. For instance, if the CO of the ship is a Bajoran, what better antagonist can you find besides a Cardassian? Or maybe another character has lost one spouse to divorce and another to death. What would happen if that character were forced to marry to save a Federation alliance?</para>
		<para>Things that you must do when you come up with your ideas are as follows:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Keep all crew busy within the sim;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Try to avoid 're-runs' or a sims of similar nature; check with the CO, you don’t want to be doing the umpteenth battle sim in a row;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Learn about the ship’s class, you need to make sure the ship you are GMing on is suitable for the kind of sim you are planning. There is no point planning a battle sim on a small explorer. So just make sure you know the ship’s limitations;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Make sure the plot is plausible; you don’t want to plan something that simply couldn’t happen;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Finally, try not to over use Trek episodes and characters. We have our own ships and characters, try to utilise them, there are only so many times that tribbles multiplying can be funny, so try to avoid it.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		<para>The main things that your idea needs to accomplish are:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Provide a problem for the crew to overcome, whether it is a mystery, drama or action idea;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Make sure that the crew can be invested in the idea;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Ensure you provide the crew with some form of accomplishment at the end of the sim.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		<para>Homework: Sim Idea</para>
		<para>Take a few minutes to come up with a story idea suitable for a sim. Identify how you will involve the various departments. You may need to just point out that a certain department is going to need a side sim.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-planning">
		<title>How To Plan Your Sim</title>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution>Unknown</attribution>
				<para>"bad planning on your part does not constitute an emergency on my part"</para>
			</epigraph>
		<para>There is no point going into a sim without a plan, even the best role-players will get lost if their Gamemaster doesn't have a plan.</para>
		<para>Think of it as planning a journey, you need to know where you are going, what you might encounter along the way and how you are going to get there. By knowing these things, you are able to evaluate exactly how things are progressing and you will be able to see where you might need to give the crew a nudge in the right direction.</para>
		<para>When writing out a sim plan, it is usually best to split it into acts. You can see where you want to get to along the way and provide yourself break areas so you don’t go crazy trying to achieve the whole sim in one sitting. That way, you can reassess where you are at each act break. If there are crew members or staff sections that are running behind the rest around the time of an act break, you should give them a push in the right direction. It gives you points where you can clearly figure out how closely you are to the plan, and take some time to re-evaluate the plan. Remember, there's anywhere from 12-20 crew members on the ship and there's only one of you. The only tool in your box you have to deal with that -- other than brute force -- is the ability to plan ahead. Crews do NOT enjoy the brute force approach. You want to be at least two steps ahead of the crew.</para>
		<para>Homework: Break It Up</para>
		<para>Using your sim idea from the last chapter, write a plan and for this plan show where you might break it down into acts. Explain what key points you would want to be achieved by the end of each act.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-stylesinteraction">
		<title>Styles and Interaction</title>
		<para>You are probably wondering what the best ways to GM actually are, well there are a couple that we shall discuss here.</para>
		<para>Trailblazing - This is like playing Hansel and Gretel in the forest. The GM has a plot and leads the crew with 'breadcrumbs' or clues to get to the end result. Should this style be chosen, then the GM has to make sure that the crew do not get too fixated on the path as they may not go in the direction that you wish. There is no point continually forcing a crew to do something that they are not already doing. With this method it is best to keep in mind that you have to be flexible with the crew. This would be the best method to use when first starting off as a Gamemaster.</para>
		<para>Free Form - Quite often a Gamemaster’s favorite choice, however, it can be extremely difficult. To be successful at free form, you have to completely understand the ship and its crew to see the possibilities in every post they write and you have to have a willingness to not have complete control. To free form, you have to have a minimal sim plot to start with. You might not have decided on the end result, but you will allow the crew to guide the story to each phase.</para>
		<para>Homework: Clues and diversions</para>
		<para>Using your sim idea, explain the series of clues you might use to get the crew from the beginning to the end of the sim. Point out places where you feel the crew might branch off from your plan.</para>
		<para>Right, you have got an idea, you know how you want your sim to play out. Now its time to look at how you present your ideas to the crew, there are three main types of posts.</para>
		<para>First we shall look at Narrative; this is the most common type of post used to provide information to crew and to set chains of events in motion.</para>
		<para>For example, another way that a narrative might be used is to convey results.</para>
		<para>The next style of post is interactive.</para>
		<para>Homework: Narrative</para>
		<para>Using the sim idea you came up with in the last lesson, write out the sim’s first post using the Narrative style.</para>
		<para>Interactive - We also have Interactive posts; this style seems to be growing in popularity as more strong role-players find their way into the GM ranks. Interactive posts can be the most fun to write, they are usually in response to the sim characters the GM has created. Sim characters can be used in many ways to convey various information, such as why a villain is planning to destroy a planet, or what background information intelligence can get from smugglers. Sometimes contact with a GM character might be limited, other times a whole sim could be created around a GM character. When you write these characters they need to be as real as any other character on the ship. Treat it like you would any other character, even write up a bio about them, this will provide dimension to your story.</para>
		<para>Homework: Interactive</para>
		<para>Now write a post introducing a GM character for your sim idea to the crew, using the Interactive style. Leave spaces for replies... do not play the other character.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Examples and Experiences From Gamemasters</title>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution>Douglas Adams</attribution>
				<para>"Human beings, who are almost unique in having the ability to learn from the experience of others, are also remarkable for their apparent disinclination to do so."</para>
			</epigraph>
		<para>“I remember a sim on a ship I commanded that resulted in the entire senior staff being locked in the holodeck. The engineers who remained free tried all kinds of things to break into the holodeck, but the GM never let them succeed. Rather than keep trying, the players went AWOL after two weeks of trying to solve the puzzle." (Unknown GM)</para>
		<para>"Never try to outline every movement that will take place within a sim. It is extremely important to allow the players to have some flexibility within the sim; people will undoubtedly come up with ideas that the GM would never think of, and it's important to keep that in mind as much as possible. By the same token, though, it's equally important to not let the players run away with the sim by grandstanding, et al. If one person tries to run away with the sim on his own by doing something that's next to impossible, then the GM needs to put the skids to that so that solving a sim can be a team effort." (Unknown GM)</para>
		<para>"It was my first official sim. I planned the whole thing out, from beginning to end. I had every event worked out. I was very inflexible as the sim progressed, not having experience with running a sim. The result: The crew lost interest, and I had to narrate the end just to get the darn thing over with! That was my bad GM experience."</para>
		<para>"A new GM was supposed to take over [after my sim was finished]. When that person AWOLed, I was put in the GM spot again. This time, I had nothing planned - I hadn't expected to be GMing! As it turned out, this was a good thing. My next sim was very spontaneous, and I had no trouble compensating for crew interest and keeping all departments active. The crew posted almost 100% daily by the end. It went great. Overall, I would advise new GMs to be flexible. Don't hold to your perfect mental image of what should happen - make sure the crew's having fun. Don't plan everything, just have a couple of good ideas." (Unknown GM)</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Tools You Might Need</title>
		<para>STF has many resources available to you. Here are the ones that have not been mentioned already in the course.</para>
		<para>Gamemaster Department - This is your home department, there are a few resources to be found here. You can also ask questions and will receive advice from other GMs. So if you have a question, don’t be afraid to ask!</para>
		<para>The Reference Manual is a home grown encyclopedia for STF. It has entries on planets, people, etc. GMs are allowed to write entries for this Manual, but you'll need to check the GM Dept for the latest submission requirements. This is a useful place to find information for a sim.</para>
		<para>Mission Records form the new GM Archive. The GM Department has been building up a record of all sims and there are two good reasons for this. One, it helps our GMs keep track of where they have GMed and how many sims they have run. Two, it provides a useful database for GMs planning sims. Eventually the archive will be the place to go and see if the ship you are about to GM has been doing back to back battle sims. Or check that they haven’t done a sim very similar to the one you’re planning.</para>
		<para>The interactive map provides you a visual aid so you can see exactly where in the universe each fleet lies and so you can establish better ideas, you don’t want to have a Klingon issue happening in the alpha quadrant.</para>
		<para>The Player's Handbook - In the academy you can find a link to The Player's Handbook. You need to be familiar with this document.</para>
		<para>Personnel Dept - The Personnel Dept is the place to go to find out about the ships in STF. Their ship profile page contains lots of information and is a good starting point. You could also ask the Personnel staff for information that they may have regarding ships. This is all good starting research, but don't forget to actually go read possible ships and see if you like the feel of it. Chat with the Command staff, find out what they expect of the GM and see if it matches with your ideas. A good match now will make for a much easier sim, be it a training one or later on when you’ve got some experience.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gm-exam">
		<title>It's Crunch Time: Exam</title>
		<para>Here is the exam for the course; you will need a score of 70% to be accepted into the GM Training Program. It is recommended that you completely read through the entire exam first before writing anything down. The primary aims of this exam are to check that you have absorbed the material of this course, emphasize the important points and evaluate you on your ability to communicate effectively through your writing. Total Marks: 103 marks.</para>
		<para>Submission Instructions</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Write out your answers to the questions below.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>E-mail them to the course grader: <ulink url="mailto:gamemaster-tutor@star-fleet.com?subject=STF Gamemaster Exam">David Wonderly</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Be sure to include your full name at the top of the e-mail!</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do not use "HTML-enriched" e-mail. It makes it harder to grade. </para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Word or a Rich Text Format attachment is most acceptable.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Please request a receipt for this email.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<section>
			<title>Section A: Facts and Mechanics</title>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>1. a. Cut and paste homework: Being a Gamemaster<emphasis>2 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>1. b. Using homework Problem Time, cut and paste two of the problems you addressed <emphasis>4 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>2. a. Who is responsible for completing mission records for the GM archive <emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>2. b. When should they be completed?<emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>3. Why do we keep these records?<emphasis>2 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>4. Show the chaing of command for a GM in STF.<emphasis>2 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>5. When can you kill a players character?<emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>6. When can you destroy a ship?<emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>7. a. Who can void posts and why? <emphasis>2 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>7. b. How would you void a post whilst minimising any disruption to the ship? <emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>8. a. Who can issue a death notice? <emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>8. b. What criteria need to be met? <emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>8. c. Explain how you might try to avoid issuing a death notice <emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>9. Suppose you are a GM on the USS Master and there is a player named Sally Cheatum and Sally continually disrupts your sim by constantly contradicting you. Sally usually does this with an OOC note stating that your recent post regarding the warp engine nearly breaching could not possibly happen because she is a theoretical physicist and there is no way a warp engine could ever do that! Brainstorm possible ways you might address this issue.<emphasis>6 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>10. What qualities/characteristics do you think make up a good and reliable GM? <emphasis>4 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>11. What is the best way to provide constructive criticism to another player through a post on the ship and why might it be a good idea to do so rather than simply e-mailing the player? <emphasis>2 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>12. a. How can you use multiple timelines to your advantage? <emphasis>2 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>12. b. When might they be a disadvantage? <emphasis>2 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>13. a. Why is it important to be able to tell the difference between canon and non-canon? <emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>13. b. When should you use canon material? When should you use non-canon material? <emphasis>1 mark</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>13. c. Where can you find what is considered canon to STF? <emphasis>2 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>Total 40 marks for Section A</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Section B: Show Me the Money</title>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>1. a. Cut and paste homework Sim Idea. Look it over to make sure you included every department (Hint: Do you have work for swing departments like CNS or CTO?). <emphasis>5 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>1. b. Cut and paste homework Narrative <emphasis>5 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>1. c. Cut and paste homework Interactive. Did you leave spaces for a reply by another character?  <emphasis>4 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>1. d. Using your idea from homework Sim Idea, create a sim plan broken down into acts. Be sure to explain what should be accomplished at the end of each act.  <emphasis>10 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>2. Where did you get the inspiration for your story idea? Why will your story idea make a good sim? <emphasis>4 marks</emphasis></para></listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>3. A GM has to be able to invent new worlds, new characters and new technology. Pick TWO of the options below and show that you are capable of doing so. Each answer should be at least two paragraphs. At least one should be related to your sim idea <emphasis>10 marks</emphasis></para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>A New World</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>A New Character</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>A New Technology</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>4. Sometimes a Gamemaster may need to really sell his or her sim to a prospective Captain. Looking over the ship profiles, write an email to the Captain of the ship you think your sim would most suit and explain why. <emphasis>5 marks</emphasis>!</para></listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>5. Sometimes a GM is called to help out on a ship. Whatever the reason, this means that sometimes you find yourself having to come up with a sim idea on the spot. Pick ONE of the following ships and come up with a sim <emphasis>10 marks</emphasis></para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>Starbase 202</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Outpost 45</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>USS Ogawa</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>USS Genesis</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>USS Constellation</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>N.B. There are <emphasis>10 marks</emphasis> for good spelling, punctuation and grammar.</para>
			<para>Total Marks - 63 for Section B</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>
