<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="textbook-security">
	<title>Security</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Matt</firstname>
				<surname>Bernardin</surname>
				<email></email>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
          <revision>
            <revnumber>1</revnumber>
            <date>19 September 2005</date>
            <revdescription>
              <para>Added to Library</para>
            </revdescription>
          </revision>
          <revision>
            <revnumber>2</revnumber>
            <date>19 October 2005</date>
            <revdescription>
              <para>Changed course proctor to Andrew Robinson</para>
            </revdescription>
          </revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section id="sec-intro">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>So, you've considered a career in security. You wish to journey to Far and distant worlds, meet new and ancient civilisations. And then kill them. Well if so you've come to the WRONG place. Check the Klingon Empire recruiting poster three doors down in the Halls of the Spanish Inquisition.</para>
		<para><quote>NOBODY expects a Spanish Inquisition</quote></para>
		<para>So, leave that Phaser in your spare Duty Uniform. Don't worry you ARE going to get to use it. But first a word from our sponsors. The Spanish Inquisition.</para>
		<para><quote>NOBODY expects a Commercial Break</quote></para>
		<para>Okay, now lets get this straight right from the start. Security Officers if they are lucky, get to fight a drunken Klingon in the mess every once in a while. They do Away teams, they are more of a police force then anything else, and on the very odd occasion they get to repel the boarders the evil Game Master sends to remove the entirety of stuff you never thought was important. This means that shipboard combat is a rare and treasured thing for a Security Ensign, the quintessential arse kickers of the fleet. However Star-fleet expects every member wearing a Security Uniform and carrying a Phaser Rifle to be experts in the martial arts, and MIT's. No it's not a College near Cambridge. It's actually a term you’re going to want to be familiar with. But that's for a page coming soon.</para>
		<para>If you're still sure that security is still you, head for the next page; Sec 101.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec-101">
		<title>The Jack of all Trades and all around can do guy</title>
		<para>Alright, welcome to Boot Camp, for the next 6 or so pages your going to be instructed in what it means to be a security Officer, what a Sec Officer is supposed to do, and given some ideas on how to get it done. Phasers will automatically be surrendered to the Quartermaster upon entry. You're not on the Firing range, nor on the Stalker course. That said, enjoy........</para>
		<para>The Security Officer, is first and fore most, a peace maker. In Tsan Zsu's the Art of War, it states that the warrior must at all times strive towards a state of perfection. A capable capacity for death. So that he does not have to deal it. This is the core principle and fundamental value at heart of being a Security Officer. Strive for perfection in your ability to impose your will by force of arms, so that you never have to do so. In other words, the training is designed to give you one thing, a choice. Security is all about choices remember, know and live this. You will be responsible for the safety and the lives of everyone onboard ship. This is not a responsibility to be taken lightly, or for granted. So you are going to be taught Situational Awareness, and Response skills. For example arming all the security department with Type IV concussion rifles, Anastazine grenades and shaped anti-Matter charges, as well as Tritanium composite riot shields to hunt down one truant child avoiding school, would be a over reaction, to say the least. Although it might be fun, it would be a complete waste of department resources, and manpower.</para>
		<para>Your role aboard ship is simple. Easy to learn, yet even harder to master. You are inter-personal diplomats, a police force, Marines, Counselors. Intelligence operatives, Tactical staff, Counter-Terrorist soldiers, emergency doctors, field engineers. The Security Officer is therefore called the Jack of All Trades, and Master of None. (Note: this doesn’t give you a broad license to do whatever you like in any department.) It would be impossible for one course to cover this broad instructional field. The Ship's small arms Phasers are kept in the locked box, only for use on the firing range or training. So please always remember, unless there's an order given specifically for Phaser's, combat is going to confined to practise, training missions or drills. And me and the Sergeant-Major here, we love to train. Two bonus points to anyone who can tell me where that came from.</para>
		<para><quote>NOBODY expects an obscure quote.</quote></para>
		<para>The defining quality however of a Security Officer is his ability to achieve objectives. Whether small like the capture of one ignoble mouse, or large, repelling Borg once they've established a habitat. The Security Officer must at any point in time be able to instantly size up a room, identify threats, sleepers and get to the heart of the matter within moments. Otherwise the probabilities are quiet high that he'll wind up dead, or incapacitated, and capture is also a thing to be kept in mind. These skills are developed for protecting the crew, not to mention keeping you alive. Hopefully this will put you on the right track to developing those skills. The Security Officer must have an approachable, conciliatory YES attitude.</para>
		<para>Alright now, Quartermaster, escort the staff to the Holodeck and issue them all training Phasers. (Didn't think I was going to give you something big straight up did you)</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec-102">
		<title>The Means or the Ends. An Abject lesson on Options</title>
		<para>Alrighty recruits, gather round. Within this section of the course, you’re going to be shown situational examples, and then debriefed on the course of action taken. Before I begin, I want you to consider one thing for me. The age old question, the means or the ends. Ultimately the decision is up to you, but I'll want an answer on your exam. So start thinking about it now.</para>
		<para>Let’s start with a base example of Situational Awareness, and means to an end. A Security Officer walks into Ten Forward, the lights are low, and there is no-one there. Rather strange considering we're at Green Alert general quarters haven't been called, there is no known emergency, plus it’s almost 1800 hrs. He calls for lights and the computer is unable to respond. What currently are his options, they are as follows. Call it into security, report it as odd and proceed anyway. Draw his Phaser and proceed, or back out the door, and call for another Sec member in to investigate. Which one would you have chosen?</para>
		<para>Well because you can't know for this situation, here's what was going on. It was the Officer's birthday, and a few friends had arranged for Ten Forward to be vacated so when he was getting off his duty shift at 1730 hrs he would be able to walk into a surprise party.</para>
		<para>Results of actions, 1 Security logs the call and they send a team into investigate within 15 minutes should he not report back, the Officer walks into his surprise party. He is thoroughly surprised and logs it with security, with a few chuckles shared all round. 2 He draws his Phaser he walks in and when someone jumps up he fires at them, it ruins the surprise by having someone sent to sickbay, and the Officer has his Phaser privileges revoked for a few weeks. 3 A security member comes and as they investigate Ten Forward, the surprise occurs and scares the hell out of them. They laugh it off and enjoy the party. In this case the wrong action most certainly was drawing his Phaser and approaching the dimly lit area. However if there had been insurgents inside that room instead of friends, number one would have gotten him killed, and the Security team walking into an ambush. Number two would have seen him kill a few before dying, and number three would have most likely seen him survive and report their presence so a team could come running, only this time knowing what they where walking into.</para>
		<para>Note: Very few people ever survive an ambush.</para>
		<para>Next the Stalker Course.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec-103">
		<title>Staying Alive, A haha ha Staying alive, Staying Alive</title>
		<para><quote>NOBODY expects an outbreak of Saturday Night Fever, even me.</quote></para>
		<para>Alright it's that time of day, Quarter Master, break out the Type III Phaser Rifles, it's time to send them off to the Stalker Course</para>
		<para>Note: This part of the training Course is a area in a dry river, it's filled with poles driven into the ground and car tires placed on them to obstruct a straight view, targets then pop up and you have a weapon to stalk and kill them.</para>
		<para>Now, eventually you're going to come into a place and time when combat IS required, as a matter of fact, training is probably the thing you’re going to be doing the most. So let’s give you the info that you’re going to need for the martial arts component of your simming.</para>
		<para>The system that is used is a variant of TB, and stands for Turn Based, this means players take a turn and post a set of movements within the forms allowed for by the rules. Generally a Block Move Strike set, then the other player gets his turn and so on and so forth. A hit occurs when a player can't block or avoid a movement, according to the laws of physics. You must be descriptive down to your stance exactly and post how you’re moving exactly. Combat then becomes an elegant dance of moves rather then I say I hit you, you say I didn't, but you hit me in return, to which I say you didn't. *Sigh*, yes it happens only too often, regardless, the introduction of full TB, will allow a form for which players can fight other players without arguments. Or accusations of modeing. (Modeing is the term used to imply that you have done something not humanly possible simply because you *felt* like it, or didn’t want your character hit/hurt/damaged)</para>
		<para>Congratulations, you've successfully reached the half way point. The next sections deal with Tactics. Don't worry; there are no Security Restrictions on them. This is designed to give you an idea of how a Professional soldier thinks, and acts, within an operational environment.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec-104">
		<title>MIT for the follower</title>
		<para>Now for that elusive acronym you've all been wondering after. MIT stands for Minor Infantry Tactics, it deals with the Tactics used by individual soldiers, and provides advice and reminder points for a Section Leader. This section is devoted for the individual; the next section will be for the leader of a group. Should you ever be put in charge of something or wind up in the unenviable position of DH then your most likely going to want some advice on how to lead your men into battle. Or perhaps what to do when you conduct a group training exercise?</para>
		<para>Alrighty; now where to begin? Ahh yes this should do.</para>
		<para>TEAM. It stands for Together Everyone Achieves More. This means that in a hostile situation the Team will either accomplish the objective, or the team will fail to meet there objective. There isn’t a single case of One Security Ensign actually accomplishing a mission without dying or other people to aid him (TOS +VOY) There is no I in TEAM. Up to a thirty percent casualty rate is termed by Star-Fleet as acceptable losses, Worf himself made mention that in a war up to fifty percent was acceptable, however for the Security team, one casualty is completely un-acceptable. Therefore your movements should reflect this fact.</para>
		<para>A team was also invented because it gave the enemy someone else to shoot at :)</para>
		<para>Combat itself has three key components. Contact. Engagement. Withdrawal.</para>
		<para>Contact is the part of battle where two opposing forces meet, exchange a volley or two. And a couple of casualties are generally sustained on both sides. During the contact phase, most likely for a planned engagement, lines are being established, arcs of fire and kill zones are being put in place.</para>
		<para>Note : If two sides exchange small amounts of fire then retreat after contact, it is majoritively termed as a firefight.</para>
		<para>Engagement</para>
		<para>Two sides go through the motions of killing each other, this is where the metal meets the meat for lack of better words. This is where tactics, troop placements and such come into play. This section can last for several hours, days or even months. It all depends on you and the enemy. Withdrawal</para>
		<para>The Battle having been decided will resolve into one side either retreating, or the other side having crushed the opposition. And if crushing is the order of the day, will rotate fresher troop to push through the breaches created if available.</para>
		<para>Now when one engages an enemy, if you employ a contact drill, then the chances of being hit in the initial contact lessen significantly. Contact Drill is as follows, drop to the ground on your chest, and, if this removes you from there sight you roll over twice look up to find a target to sight in on. Then roll back one and pop up and fire.</para>
		<para>In shipboard combat, contact drill because of the lack of available cover becomes redundant. However you can modify it to match ship’s conditions. Therefore one might use the following procedures.</para>
		<para>In a Clearing action a team of three clear critical areas, one drops to the floor, the other launches a grenade of some variety, then hits a knee while the third supports from the standing position behind whatever cover is available. This is due to the fact that federation vessels where designed with long coverless decks, because the advent of below decks combat, are supposed to be an infrequent thing. As opposed to the TOS and ENT eras, in which all the decks are designed with plenty of cover for security forces to fight from. As boarding actions happen frequently. Covering fire is also another consideration to be made, moving only while a team mate covers you will save you from being put up like a pigeon on a wire. This is true in reverse, covering a team mate while he is moving is a very good thing.</para>
		<para>The last thing we need to discuss is communications, now star-fleet has encrypted transmitters supposedly making it impossible for an enemy to listen to your comms. However, this is not the only consideration. Alerting an enemy to the fact that you are there at all is not a good thing. Conversely if you run a scan on RF and other communications waves, you might just get lucky. Remember what we discussed about learning how to fight so you don't have to. If you can sneak up on an enemy unseen or unheard, you can take prisoners. Gain info and access to some otherwise previously unreachable places.</para>
		<para>To counter this, remember the more technology you take with you the easier you will be to track. So take weapons your comm. Badge, perhaps some personal Armour and that's it. Now these things take a while for them to become ingrained into how you think, so don't worry if you don't quiet understand.</para>
		<para>To go in or not to go in, this is the question that plagues everyone.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec-105">
		<title>I'm going in</title>
		<para>Alright remember how I talked about MIT's for the leader last section. Here they are in all there glory detail.</para>
		<para>If in doubt hold and set up a defensive line. (Wait for stuff to shoot) If in doubt after that, clear it out (Clearing Action). If still in doubt..........CHARGE. (Blow it up)</para>
		<para>Simply put the leader needs to know how his troopies move, and be able to give them orders to where they can give the most fire while taking the least return fire. You must find a way of inflicting damage while staying clear of it yourselves. Cover is one thing to consider in this manner, covering fire and employing these tactics to aid in the moving of your troops.</para>
		<para>Suppressive fire, this means basically put enough rounds into the general area of a hostile to force him to seek cover. The aim of suppressive fire is to limit a hostiles options, so that you can lead him into an area of highest possible kill with minimal casualties in return</para>
		<para>Covering Fire, similar to supressive fire, however you are covering the movements of troops, this is simply designed so that you can safely move troops to where they can provide supressive fire and inflict damage.</para>
		<para>Employing all your weapons, supressive fire while employing a grenade will often either incapacitate an enemy, or kill him outright. Deploying two men with Phaser Rifles while three men with type 2 phasers to lead them into an ambush. Remember, these tactics are learnt by experience, practice is required to refine them. So keep up the good work.</para>
		<para>Old Saying: Don't draw fire, it irritates everyone around you.</para>
		<para>Remember Battle is unless you have a Gun hoe GM a rare thing, but with this as a guide. It may give you a few ideas as to how to solve a situation that stumped you before.</para>
		<para>Bonjourno.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec-exam">
		<title>Exam</title>
		<para>Submission Instructions</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Write out your answers to the questions below.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>E-mail them to the course grader: <ulink url="mailto:andrewrobinson257@msn.com">Andrew Robinson</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Be sure to include your full name at the top of the e-mail!</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> send the original question, just the answers.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> send your answers as an attachment.  Send them in the body of the e-mail.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> use "HTML-enriched" e-mail.  It makes it harder to grade.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>All answers must be original.  Do not simply copy and paste from the lessons.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<section>
			<title>Section One</title>
			<para>Short Response          Worth total 10 Marks.           On Roles and Achieving results.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>A Security Officer is defined as a what?</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>What Core Philosophy should guide your footsteps when training for your role?</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>How do you see your primary role aboard ship?</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>How would you define Sleeper, and Threat?</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>What type of environment do you think is the appropriate one to foster
aboard ship?</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Section Two</title>
			<para>Post            Worth total of 30 Marks         Options</para>
			<para>Catch 20, The Jacobs Situation.</para>
			<para>Alright, we're going to take the previous scenario, a security officer walks into ten forward and discovers the lights are out, he proceeds to investigate and finds out he's walked into a hostage situation. Some rogue Romulan agents have snuck aboard ship during the stopover at the last star base. They're demanding a shuttle and the access codes to deactivate the surveillance systems on a certain remote area of Federation space. They will kill the hostages if they're demands are not met within 3 hours. One includes the first officer, who was due to show up for duty within the next hour, plus a Klingon Ambassador that's being transported to a conference due to exchange some classified technology. There is a Jeffries tube access point somewhere in the rear of where the insurgents are. They've rearranged the tables to provide cover, and one of them looks to be holding an explosive device of some type. Identify your options, and then proceed with your plan In Character.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Section Three</title>
			<para>Essay                   Worth Total of 15 Points                Means and Ends</para>
			<para>In the Above situation there are about four or five possible ends. However there is up to 30 means of accomplishing all the ends. So there is about five ways to accomplish each individual end. Write me an essay on why you chose that particular end. As oppossed to the means used to accomplish them. Was your means justified to accomplish that end, and why? Was it ethically right, morally right? If not then why did the End outweigh the means?</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Bonus Questions</title>
			<para>Invent a Scenario for training purposes. Put the Security Officer in a difficult situation which challenges his ethics and his current training. (Worth 12)</para>
			<para>Name the film that the quote: Me and the Sergeant-Major here, we love it. Came from (Worth 2)</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</article>
