<article class="whitepaper" id="reference-entrytypes">
	<title>Types of Reference Manual Entries</title>
	<section>
		<title>Canon</title>
		<para>Canon entries are those entries that cover a topic defined by official Star Trek.  These are planets, species, and powers that are defined by the producers of Star Trek and seen in the TV shows and movies, and possibly elaborated upon by official producer-authored texts such as the Chronology or Encyclopedia.  Examples include the Klingons, the Cardsassian Empire, Risa, and so forth.</para>
		<para>Canon entries are, strictly speaking, "owned" by Paramount, and the STF Reference Manual is just documenting them.  The TV shows and movies are the definitive source for these entries, not the submitter.  Therefore, Canon entries should stick to canon information only and not embellish with material from non-canon or custom sources.</para>
		<para>A canon entry may be updated with new information by anyone, subject to approval by the Librarian, not just the original submitter.  Credit will be retained on the entry for all authors of all submissions, unless a particular submitter asks to be removed.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Non-Canon</title>
		<para>Non-Canon entries are those entries that cover a topic defined by non-canon Star Trek, that is, The Animated Series and novels.  These often show up in STF, so they are useful to have clearly referenced.  Examples include the Brikar, Caitians, Hermats, and so forth.</para>
		<para>Non-Canon entries are, strictly speaking, "owned" by their respective authors (authors of various novels, for instance), and the STF Reference Manual is just documenting them.  The novels in which they appear are the definitive definitive source for these entries, not the submitter.  Therefore, Non-Canon entries should stick to non-canon information only and not embellish with material from custom sources.</para>
		<para>A non-canon entry may be updated with new information by anyone, subject to approval by the Librarian, not just the original submitter.  Credit will be retained on the entry for all authors of all submissions, unless a particular submitter asks to be removed.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Custom</title>
		<para>Custom entries are those entries that cover a topic created by one or more STFers.  They are an original Trek-inspired part of the STF universe that do not appear in canon Trek or in a Trek novel.  These often show up in STF, so they are useful to have clearly referenced.  Examples include the Crag, Flarn, New Bajor, and so forth.</para>
		<para>Custom entries are, strictly speaking, "owned" by the STF member who developed them.  The STF Reference Manual is hosting them for reference by the rest of STF so that others know what "Trek+" settings they may run into.  The definitive source for a Custom entry is the original author(s) and the approved entry.  Custom entries should be restricted to Custom information only, and not be an "extension" on any particular canon or non-canon subject.</para>
		<para>A Custom entry may be updated only by the original author/submitter, or the original author/submitter and someone else he chooses to bring on board.  The author/submitter may bestow ownership of the entry on another member, removing himself, by explicitly notifying the GMDir and Librarian by email and posting in the GMD ship to that effect.</para>
	</section>
</article>
