<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"> -->
<article id="charter-403rd">
  <title>403rd Platoon</title>
  <subtitle>Fleet Four</subtitle>
  <articleinfo>
    <author role="President">
      <honorific>President</honorific>
      <firstname>Andrew</firstname>
      <surname>Robinson</surname>
    </author>
    <author role="Fleet Commander">
      <honorific>Fleet Commander</honorific>
      <firstname>Krystelle</firstname>
      <surname>Bromilow</surname>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>11 March 2009</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/robinson/#e54">Robinson #54</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <para>An alternative roleplaying environment is hereby established in Fleet 4 named 403rd Platoon.</para>
  <para>403rd Platoon is a Marine RPG. It is a primarily Marine based Roleplaying Area whereby a Specialized Marine contingent is required to complete certain missions as a platoon where ever they are dropped. It will consist of a Commanding Officers and Enlisted Personnel.</para>
  <para>403rd Platoon will remain an active Roleplaying Area, provided that it meets the following criteria:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>403rd Platoon must maintain a healthy roleplaying environment with a cast of reliable players who remain on the whole within the outlined AWOL guidelines.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>403rd Platoon must continue its function solely as a Marine based environment successfully.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>If 403rd Platoon should deviate from the criteria set in this charter at any time, it shall be decommissioned.</para>
  <para>403rd Platoon shall have a similar command structure to a Starfleet vessel however it shall utilize Marine Ranks, both officer and Enlisted. The commanding officer shall be a Marine Lieutenant; executive officer shall be a Staff Sergeant as is consistent with a standard with a regular marine platoon. These members shall hold Member ranks of there ship side counterparts (captain and commander respectively) and shall count towards the CO/XO limit of the member however the characters rank must reflect realistically the command structure of a Marine Platoon. The bulk of the Platoons force shall be enlisted personnel performing a variety of tasks. The Departments shall include, but are not limited to, the following:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>Field Medics</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Assault</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Recon</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Technicians</para></listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>Each of these shall be commanded by either a SNCO and staffed by enlisted personnel primarily.</para>
  <para>The platoon shall be split into 4 separate squads. The first shall contain the Lieutenant, Staff Sergeant, Medic and Technician. The other three shall be headed by a Sergeant and will consist of a force of Privates and corporals. The CO may decide to reinforce certain squads with other personnel or reorder the squads and their compliment depending on the mission. Any changes made to the Platoon structure must be reasonable and are done at the Captains discretion. Ranks specified in this charter are only a guidline and the CO may decide to promote personel if they have done an exceptional Job, as would be the same on a regular ship.</para>
  <para>The premise for each mission shall be the platoon being dropped on a Planet or Base with a particular mission to accomplish. They then proceed under the GM.s direction to complete their assigned objective. It should be noted that the Platoon does not operate on a ship environment so transport to and from each mission is via an NPC ship that shall not be utilized within the mission itself.</para>
</article>
