<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="charter-code">
	<title>The Coder</title>
	<subtitle>"CODE"</subtitle>
	<articleinfo>
		<author role="President">
			<honorific>President</honorific>
			<firstname>Sarah</firstname>
			<surname>Hemenway</surname>
		</author>
		<author role="Internet Director">
			<honorific>Internet Director</honorific>
			<firstname>Jack</firstname>
			<surname>Dipper</surname>
		</author>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>1 April 2007</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://star-fleet.com/prez/hemenway.php#e26">Hemenway #26</ulink></para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Establishment of the Coder</title>
		<para>An Executive Assistant position is hereby created known as Coder.</para>
		<para>The Coder is charged with the maintenance and development of STF's core software and related software components by means of the authority in this and subsequent edicts.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Appointment of the Coder</title>
		<para>The Coder shall be appointed by Presidential Edict with the prior consent of the Internet Director. The Coder may not be removed or replaced except with the joint-consent of the President and Internet Director.</para>
		<para>As an Executive Assistant position, the Coder is automatically retained at the start of each Presidential Term. As an Executive Assistant position, the Coder's direct superior is the President, not the Internet Director.</para>
		<para>Neither the President nor Internet Director may be appointed Coder without the consent of the Vice President or Assistant Internet Director, respectively. Should the Coder also be either the President or Internet Director, the consent of the Vice President or Assistant Internet Director, respectively, will be required for removal.</para>
		<para>Should the author of the software be available and willing to accept the position, he will be given preference in appointment. Other candidates must be able to demonstrate an appropriate level of technical proficiency with the software and programming languages involved, as well as due regard for security and accessibility concerns.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Authority of the Coder</title>
		<para>The Coder shall:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Maintain, debug, and support STF's core software and related software components.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Develop and implement new features and upgrades to STF's core software as required, as needed, and as is found feasible in coordination with the Internet Department.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Make significant architectural changes to STF's core software, including replacement of the core software, with the prior consent of the President and Internet Director.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Ensure that the system is adequately documented for standard usage, administration, and maintenance.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The Internet Department must grant the Coder sufficient server access to carry out his maintenance and development duties.</para>
		<para>Should the Coder also be either President or Internet Director, the consultation and approval of the Vice President or Assistant Internet Director, respectively, shall be required.</para>
	</section>
</article>
