<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">-->
<article id="charter-constellation">
  <title>USS Constellation</title>
  <subtitle>Fleet Two</subtitle>
  <articleinfo>
    <author role="President">
      <honorific>President</honorific>
      <firstname>Jen</firstname>
      <surname>Herr</surname>
    </author>
    <author role="Fleet Commander">
      <honorific>Fleet Commander</honorific>
      <firstname>Katherine</firstname>
      <surname>Dedul</surname>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>31 January 2006</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/herr/#e7">Herr #7</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <para>The USS Constellation NCC-1017-H is hereby recommissioned as an alternative role playing area in Fleet 2. It is to be solely a comedy sim ship. Because of its lack of adherence to canon, and its completely unserious characteristics, it is to be a second character only environment.</para>
  <para>The Constellation is allowed to change her class without being decommissioned as an Alt RPG. She is currently in service and is herby confirmed to be successful under the classification of a comedy sim ship and by the following criteria:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>The Constellation currently has a healthy roleplaying environment with a cast of reliable players who remain on the whole within the outlined AWOL guidelines.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The Constellation has managed to function as a comedy ship successfully.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>The Constellation will remain a permanent addition to Fleet 2, but if at any time she deviates from the criteria set in this edict, she must be decommissioned.</para>
  <para>As a comedy ship, the Constellation is not bound by established Star Trek canon. Players may select characters, abilities, and technology from non-canon and custom sources, with the approval of the CO. However, these freedoms must be treated responsibly, and are allowed for the sole reason of having fun. God characters, cast members from Star Trek canon, and other such restricted character types are still forbidden. While a sim may be silly and fun in any respect, it must be realistic enough to be playable.</para>
  <para>The Constellation shall have a similar command structure to other Starfleet vessels, including all standard departments, rank structure, and chain of command. As such, RPG Ranks on the Constellation will count toward Member Rank the same as on Standard Ships, and CO and XO positions on the Constellation will count fully towards any limits in place.</para>
  <para>Additional swing positions may be added under the CO's discretion, without being limited to demands of canon positions. Examples might include: </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>Chief Sanitation Officer</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Chief of Jello Investigations</para></listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>The current CO and crew of the USS Constellation are retained in their current positions aboard the ship. The CO may be removed at some later date in accordance with the rules of the site without penalty to the Constellation herself.</para>

</article>
