<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="charter-id">
	<title>The Internet Department</title>
	<subtitle>"SCSI"</subtitle>
	<articleinfo>
		<author role="President">
			<honorific>President</honorific>
			<firstname>Jack</firstname>
			<surname>Dipper</surname>
		</author>
		<author role="IDir">
			<honorific>Internet Director</honorific>
			<firstname>Larry</firstname>
			<surname>Garfield</surname>
		</author>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>30 November 2005</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/dipper/#e31">Dipper #31</ulink></para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
    <section>
      <title>Supercedence of previous edicts</title>
      <para>Edicts Hughes #30-B, Hughes #30-C, Hughes #30-D, Hughes #30-E, Hughes #30-F, Hughes #30-G, Hughes #30-H, and Hughes #30-I are hereby rescinded and superceded by this Edict.</para>
      <para>Edict Garfield #21 is hereby rescinded and superceded by this Edict.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Establishment of the Internet Department</title>
      <para>An Executive Department is hereby established under the name "Internet Department".</para>
      <para>The Internet Department shall be responsible for managing and maintaining STF's real-world technology infrastructure, including but not limited to any servers, application code, web sites, etc. It is empowered to set and maintain policy relating to the acquisition, development, and use of such resources in order to maintain the security and stability of STF's technological infrastructure.</para>
      <para>The daily activity of the Internet Department shall be overseen by the Internet Director, who shall be appointed by the President. The Internet Director is a cabinet position, and is equal in power to other departmental directors and Fleet Commanders.</para>
      <para>The Assistant Internet Director shall be appointed by the Internet Director. The Assistant Internet Director answers directly to the Internet Director, and is responsible for departmental decisions in the event the Internet Director is not available. Additional responsibilities are at the discretion of the Internet Director.</para>
      <para>The Internet Director may delegate any of his duties enumerated in this Edict or any other responsibilities incumbent upon him as a result of another Edict to another named member of the Internet Department.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Web Resources</title>
      <para>The Internet Department is responsible for maintaining STF's web site and other web-based resources. Web resources shall include any and all web pages, web-based applications, and any supporting resource files (images, stylesheets, etc.). Any web resource not under the explicit jurisdiction of another Department, Fleet, Ship, or Executive Office shall be considered under the jurisdiction of the Internet Department.</para>
      <para>The Internet Department may establish a common template for use on Internet Department-controlled pages.</para>
      <para>The Internet Department shall make available web space and an MOTD (collectively "Section") to the head of each Department, Fleet, registered RPG Area, and Executive Office (collectively "Maintainers") for their use. The Internet Department may establish publicly documented reasonable standards for such Sections in order to maintain accuracy, site integrity and organization, security, and community standards as defined by the STF Terms of Service or other Edicts. Any changes to such standards must be publicly announced and a grace period given of no less than thirty (30) days.</para>
      <para>Maintainers may opt for one of three options for their Section.</para>
      <orderedlist>
	      <listitem><para>Full Control. The Maintainer is fully responsible for all content and design for the Section, and for any and all routine maintenance that is required.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Content Control. The Maintainer is responsible for providing the content for the Section, but the Internet Department is responsible for the layout and presentation, and is not required to use a format other than the common template. Maintainers wishing an alternate design should request Full Control.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Departmental Control. The Internet Department is responsible for both the content and presentation of the Section. The Internet Department will use the current departmental template for such Sections, and is not required to provide more than a general informational page. Maintainers wishing expanded content or an alternate design should request Content Control or Full Control.</para></listitem>
       </orderedlist>
       <para>The Internet Department may assume Departmental Control of any Section whose content is more than sixty (60) days out of date and whose Maintainer has been given at least fourteen (14) days notice. This rule applies only to pages whose contents have been inaccurate for sixty days, regardless of when the page was last updated.</para>
       <para>A Maintainer may request a change of status from the Internet Department in writing. Such requests may only be denied if the Internet Department can show just cause why such a change would be detrimental to STF.</para>
       <para>Maintainers are under no obligation to provide content or layout of pages in their Sections personally, but will be held responsible for them by the Internet Department regardless of the original author.</para>
       <para>All content and resources required by a Section or the associated MOTD -- including but not limited to HTML files, images, stylesheets, PHP scripts, etc. -- must be hosted on the STF server. References to off-site resources are forbidden in order to maintain the technical stability of the site and to prevent the loss of information or resources should off-site hosts become unavailable or inaccessible.</para>
       <para>The Internet Department may remove content that is in violation of standing policy, but must immediately notify the related Maintainer and provide the Maintainer with a copy of the removed content. That includes links to off-site resources not permitted under the preceeding paragraph.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Exempted Sections</title>
      <para>Content on the site of specific historical value or that has special circumstances requiring it to be exempted from the Internet Department-established structure and organization may be declared Exempted. Such exemptions may only be granted by the dual consent of the Internet Director and President, and only if subjecting the content to Internet Department regulation would violate copyright, significantly reduce the value of the content in question, or otherwise be detrimental to STF.</para>
      <para>The Internet Department shall have no authority over such content, except where necessary to avoid violations of STF, US, or international law.</para>
      <para>Revocation of Exempted status may only be made with the dual consent of the Internet Director and President and with no less than ninety (90) days notice to the recognized Maintainer of the content in question.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Application Software</title>
      <para>Maintainers may implement auxiliary web applications to use in their Sections if they so choose, or to implement dynamic web pages using a server-side technology such as PHP or Perl. Such applications may be custom written by an STF member or a 3rd party application. However, auxiliary web applications are subject to the following additional restrictions:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para>The Internet Department reserves the right to audit any executable code intended for installation on the STF server, and to modify or reject it order to protect the security and integrity of the system.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>If a 3rd party application, the application must be under an open source license that permits the Internet Department to audit and modify the code if needed.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>If a custom application, the author grants STF a non-exclusive, perpetual, non-revokable license to use or alter the application in any way whatsoever as needed. The original author will, however, retain any related copyright, and STF is not given the authority to redistribute the application to 3rd parties unless otherwise specified.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Although the Internet Department is authorized to modify any application code on the server for security reasons, it must inform the related Maintainer that it has done so and may not modify the application for other reasons.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Dynamic web pages or any web pages that include executable code, such as PHP or Perl, are considered a web application, even if the code is being used only for easier, centralized page formatting.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Real-Time Chat</title>
      <para>The Internet Department may establish official real-time chat venues, such as IRC channels. The Internet Department shall have exclusive authority over such venues, including regulation of assistant adminstrators such as IRC "Ops". Such venues are considered public and open to all STF members who have not been banned for specific rules violations, however, any and all STF Terms of Service shall apply in addition to any additional rules published by the Internet Department.</para>
      <para>The Internet Department has no authority over chat venues created by other STF members.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>E-mail Addresses</title>
      <para>The Internet Department shall maintain e-mail forwarders for key government officials, directing to the personal address of the member's choosing. "Key government officials" includes the President, Vice President, Cabinet Officers and Executive Assistants, and their immediate successors. Forwarders for internal departmental positions may be created as well at the request of the Department Director.</para>
      <para>Fully functional e-mail accounts will only be created if it can be shown that a forwarding account is insufficient for the intended use.</para>
      <para>The Internet Department reserves the right to rename or remove an address upon thirty (30) days notice to the related member or department, or immediately should the related position cease to exist.</para>
     </section>
     <section>
      <title>Security</title>
      <para>All administrative passwords to official STF resources, including but not limited to the STF server, any official chat venues, and the core web application software, must be held at all times by the Internet Director, President, and at least one other individual selected by the Internet Director. That individual need not be the same person for all passwords. At least the Internet Director and one other holder of a given password must agree in order to change the password, and it must then be provided immediately to all other authorized individuals.</para>
      <para>Other government officers may request administrative access to various STF resources if they can show that it is necessary for the performance of their duties. The Internet Director is the final authority on who may or may not have administrative access, and no one but the Internet Director may authorize additional individuals to hold administrative access for any reason. A recommendation from the President to consider a given government officer should be given due consideration.</para>
      <para>The Internet Director may require access to other web applications installed on the server for security purposes.</para>
      <para>An exception to the above rules is made during Election Season. For the duration of Election Season, the Election Coordinator will be granted access to any resources necessary for his position and server access will be restricted to the Election Coordinator, Internet Director, and President. Should in the opinion of the Election Coordinator any member, including the President or Internet Director, be too involved in any campaign they will be barred from administrative access for the duration of Election Season and replaced by another member agreed upon by the Election Coordinator and Internet Director. Preference will be given to other non-Election-involved members of the Internet Department.</para>
      <para>At no point may the password for any official resource be held by fewer than three people, but should at all times be kept to a reasonable minimum.</para>
     </section>
    <section>
      <title>Disputes</title>
      <para>Unless otherwise specified, any disputes regarding access to or control of club resources will be moderated by the Internet Director, unless the Internet Director is a party to the dispute in which case the dispute will be moderated by the President. The decision of either moderator will be considered final, however, deference should be given to security considerations except in extreme circumstances.</para>
    </section>     
</article>
