<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="charter-library">
	<title>The STF Librarian</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<author role="President">
			<honorific>President</honorific>
			<firstname>Jack</firstname>
			<surname>Dipper</surname>
		</author>
		<author role="Librarian">
			<honorific>STF Librarian</honorific>
			<firstname>Larry</firstname>
			<surname>Garfield</surname>
		</author>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>23 June 2005</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://star-fleet.com/prez/dipper.php#e8">Dipper #8</ulink></para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Establishment of the Librarian</title>
		<para>An Executive Assistant position is hereby created known as Librarian (or STF Librarian).</para>
		<para>The Assistant Librarian shall be appointed by the Librarian. The Assistant Librarian answers directly to the Librarian, and the position serves primarily as a "training" role. Additional responsibilities are at the discression of the Librarian.</para>
		<para>The Librarian shall maintain a publicly accessible archive of reference, legal, and historical material for STF by means of the authority granted in this and subsequent edicts.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Authority of the Librarian</title>
		<para>The Librarian shall have the authority to:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Collect and archive references and documents deemed of referential, legal, or historical interest, with the consent of the original author. Posting of the material on STF shall be considered acceptable consent, as per the STF Terms of Service.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Establish and maintain a standard format, style, and layout for archived information, as well as for the submission of new content. However, all file formats used must be based on open, non-proprietary standards and not require a financial outlay on the part of any member to participate.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Annotate and provide a framing for collected works, provided that such meta-information is distinct from the actual content.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Make non-substantive changes to archived content in order to maintain said format, including, but not limited to, correcting spelling, punctuation, grammar, links, and pagination. The Librarian is not permitted to make substantive changes to the content of archived worked without the consent of the original author.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Services rendered by the Librarian</title>
		<para>Executive Departments, Fleets, and the Office of the President (collectively "Departments") may request that the Librarian archive certain documents for which they are responsible on their behalf. Such documents may include complete works or collections of works. For the purposes of the Librarian, the submitting Department shall be considered the original author.</para>
		<para>The Librarian may accept or decline such a request based on the document's usefulness to STF at large, its compatibility with the rest of the Library, conformance to established standards for formatting, style, and layout, and the Librarian's current workload. A declined document may be resubmitted later should the reasons it was declined be addressed.</para>
		<para>Once a work has been accepted into the Library, the submitting Department may submit additions and modifications as necessary, which the Librarian may only decline on the grounds of improper format for such a submission or excessive stylistic errors (spelling, punctuation, etc.).</para>
		<para>A document may be removed from the Library only upon the request of the original author, demonstration that its presence as part of the Library causes some harm to the Library, STF, or the author, and with Presidential permission. If the original author is the President, the permission of the Vice-President will be required.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Exempted documents</title>
		<para>A Department submitting a document to the Library may request that the document be treated as an Exempted Document. The Librarian is not permitted to make any changes whatsoever to Exempted Documents without the consent of the author, except those absolutely necessary for archival.</para>
		<para>An Exempted Document will only be considered if the submitter can show just cause for it to be considered Exempt, and with the consent of both the Librarian and President. A desire for artistic purity is generally insufficient cause for a document to be considered Exempt. If accepted, the Librarian may require a stricter format for change requests in order to facilitate changes without violating the document's Exempt status.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Disputes</title>
		<para>Any dispute regarding the content of or modification to the Library, including a document's Exempt status, shall be moderated by the President. The decision of the President will be considered final.</para>
	</section>
</article>
