<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">-->
<article id="charter-mac">
  <title>Marketing and Advertising</title>
  <subtitle>"MAC"</subtitle>
  <articleinfo>
    <author role="President">
      <honorific>President</honorific>
      <firstname>Sarah</firstname>
      <surname>Hemenway</surname>
    </author>
    <author role="MAC">
      <honorific>Marketing and Advertising Coordinator</honorific>
      <firstname>Jim</firstname>
      <surname>Hosick</surname>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0</revnumber>
        <date>05 May 2007</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/hemenway/#e43">Hemenway #43</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE MARKETING AND ADVERTISING COORDINATOR</title>
    <para>An Executive Assistant position is hereby created known as Marketing and Advertising Coordinator (or "MAC").</para>
    <para>The Assistant Marketing and Advertising Coordinator shall be appointed by the Marketing and Advertising Coordinator. The Assistant Marketing and Advertising Coordinator answers directly to the Marketing and Advertising Coordinator, and the position serves primarily as a "training" roll. Additional responsibilities are at the discretion of the Marketing and Advertising Coordinator.</para>
    <para>The Marketing and Advertising Coordinator is responsible for establishing and maintaining STF's online presences in order to ensure the club's continued health in the online role-playing community. He functions as the President's representative in external matters relating to the status of the club within the role-playing community.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>THE RESPONSIBILITIES OF THE MARKETING AND ADVERTISING COORDINATOR</title>
    <para>The Marketing and Advertising Coordinator shall be tasked with such duties as, but not limited to:</para>
    <para>- Monitoring and improving STF's position on search engines.</para>
    <para>- Analyzing the online role-playing community that STF is a part of.</para>
    <para>- Researching, approaching appropriate clubs for, and maintaining banner exchanges and joint advertising endeavors</para>
    <para>- Maintaining a list of contacts within the online role-playing community.</para>
    <para>- Establishing a point of contact for those seeking information about the club.</para>
    <para>- Creating and maintaining a set of introductory reference materials about the club to be provided to interested parties. These materials will contain brief information regarding the club and provide a guide to other, more detailed information.</para>
    <para>- Investigating ways to continually improve STF's presence.</para>
    <para>- Providing monthly reports regarding STF's status and the MAC's activities.</para>
    <para>Any formal agreement with another club or organization must be entered into Edict by the President, in coordination with the Marketing and Advertising Coordinator. This power may not be delegated to any individual for any reason. The Marketing and Advertising Coordinator may require the services of any other Executive Department or Executive Assistant in order to accomplish his responsibilities. The President may delegate any additional duties or projects to the Marketing and Advertising Coordinator, but only as required for the advancement and maintenance of the club's position in the role-playing community.</para>
  </section>
</article>