<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="charter-moo">
  <title>Member Order and Organization</title>
  <subtitle>"MOO"</subtitle>
  <articleinfo>
    <author role="President">
      <honorific>President</honorific>
      <firstname>Andrew</firstname>
      <surname>Robinson</surname>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>3</revnumber>
        <date>31st May 2009</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/robinson/#e64">Robinson #64</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>2</revnumber>
        <date>29th February 2009</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/robinson/#e49">Robinson #49</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>1 April 2007</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/hemenway/#e34">Hemenway #34</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>Supersession Of Previous Edicts</title>
  	<para>Edicts Hemenway #34 and Robinson #49 are hereby rescinded and superseded by this Edict.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Membership</title>
    <para>A Member of STF is defined as an individual who has at least one active role-playing or Gamemaster position within the club.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Club rank structure</title>
    <para>The club rank structure (for out of character usage) of STF is defined as, from junior to senior: Cadet/Ensign, Lieutenant junior grade, Lieutenant, Lieutenant Commander, Commander, Captain, Fleet Captain, Commodore, Rear Admiral, Vice Admiral and Admiral. Cadet and Ensign are equivalent for the purposes of club rank.</para>
    <para>A Member's club rank, below the rank of Captain, is defined as the highest role-playing rank that a Member has achieved since he joined STF. Club rank at and above the rank of Captain is determined by the most recent Presidential Edict. A Member at or above the rank of Captain may be recognized for exemplary role-playing and service to the club by promotion by the President in an Edict to the next highest club rank.</para>
    <para>Character rank is defined as the rank that a Member's individual role-playing character has attained. The rank structure for character rank is, from junior to senior:</para>    
      <simplelist role="Member Rank List">
      <member>Civilian</member>
      <member>Crewman</member>
      <member>Cadet</member>
      <member>Ensign</member>
      <member>Lieutenant Junior Grade</member>
      <member>Lieutenant</member>
      <member>Lieutenant Commander</member>
      <member>Commander</member>
      <member>Captain</member>
      <member>Fleet Captain</member>
      <member>Commodore</member>
      <member>Rear Admiral</member>
      <member>Vice Admiral</member>
      <member>Admiral</member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>Alternate Role-playing Areas may have a different character rank system. No Member shall have a character with a character rank higher than the Member's club rank.</para>
    <para>A Marine rank structure exists within STF and follows that of the United States Marine Corp as follows, junior to senior</para>
    <para>Enlisted:</para>
    <simplelist role="Marine Rank List">
      <member>Private First Class</member>
      <member>Lance Corporal</member>
      <member>Corporal</member>
      <member>Sergeant</member>
      <member>Staff Sergeant</member>
      <member>Gunnery Sergeant</member>
      <member>Master Sergeant</member>
      <member>Sergeant Major</member>
      <member>Warrant Officer</member>
      <member>Chief Warrant Officer</member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>Officer:</para>
    <simplelist role="Marine Officer Rank List">
      <member>Second Lieutenant</member>
      <member>First Lieutenant</member>
      <member>Captain</member>
      <member>Major</member>
      <member>Lieutenant Colonel</member>
      <member>Colonel</member>
      <member>Brigadier General</member>
      <member>Major General</member>
      <member>Lieutenant General</member>
      <member>General</member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>Each marine officer rank has an equivalent within the regular fleet. No member may hold a marine character with a rank higher than their club member rank.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Absence from the club</title>
    <para>A Member is determined to be Absent without Leave (AWOL) if he is not within the defined AWOL limits for his club position. A Member who has a club rank of Captain or above may be subject to a club rank penalty for AWOL; each case will be considered individually by the President.</para>
    <para>A Member is entitled to take a Leave of Absence (LOA) if they are unable to post within the defined AWOL limits for his club positions. A Leave of Absence is defined as any period of declared leave from club posting duties that is less than thirty days. Any LOA for a period of less than 30 days will have no effect on an individual's positions; however, multiple LOAs within a short time scale by a Commanding Officer or an Executive Officer may result in the removal of an individual with the approval of the Fleet Commander and the President. The individual's removal from department head and junior officer positions is at the discretion of the appropriate ship's Commanding Officer.</para>
    <para>Any leave of absence of 30 days and beyond is considered to be an Extended Leave of Absence (eLOA). Any leave of absence with an unspecified end date is considered to be an Indefinite Leave of Absence (iLOA). Any individual taking an eLOA or an iLOA understands that no position they hold is guaranteed to remain open for when they return to the club. This covers any position including that of a Commanding Officer (CO) and government positions. This ruling is not absolute and will not cover any individual arrangements that may be subject to approval by either the Fleet Commander or President.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Promotions Guidelines</title>
    <para>For exceptional service to the club at large a member may be promoted beyond the rank of Captain by Presidential Edict. Promotions beyond the rank of Captain should be considered using the following guidelines as a benchmark:</para>
    <para>Fleet Captain (Flt Capt): For exceptional service to the club, the President can promote members beyond the rank of Captain. Fleet Captain is a mark of commitment or contribution to the club above and beyond the usual requirements.</para>
    <para>Commodore (Cdre): Somewhat Rare, Commodore is a promotion usually given to those who have not only made exceptional commitments to the club above and beyond that which is required, but have done so consistently over a number of years. This is considered the first of the 'Flag Ranks'</para>
    <para>Rear Admiral (RAdm): Rare. Rear Admiral is a promotion given to those who have not only made exceptional commitments to the club above and beyond that which is required for a number of years, but have also had a permanent and lasting impact in developing the club through government work in Fleets or Departments.</para>
    <para>Vice Admiral (VAdm): Very Rare. Vice Admiral is a promotion given to those who have made exceptional, lasting and long term impacts on the way in which the club operates and functions. Usually given to those members who have served as President at least once and have a long history of government work developing new procedures and working tirelessly to develop the best procedures and policies for any Department or Fleet that they turn their hand to.</para>
    <para>Admiral (Adm): Ultra Rare. The highest member rank achievable in the club, Admiral is given by the President to those rare few members who have given their all for many years and have had a significant lasting impact on the club in terms of its development through government and technology as well as a profound impact on how we function and operate through the implementation of long lasting changes that revolutionise the Government, the platform on which we operate or the Presidency.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Promotions Limits</title>
	<para>Beyond the rank of Captain, no member may be promoted more than once in any eight month period. Members may only be promoted in this manner to the next highest rank as outlined in the Chain Of Command.</para>
  </section>
</article>