<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="charter-merrimack">
	<title>USS Merrimack</title>
	<subtitle>Fleet Six</subtitle>
	<articleinfo>
		<author role="President">
			<honorific>President</honorific>
			<firstname>Larry</firstname>
			<surname>Garfield</surname>
		</author>
		<author role="Fleet Commander">
			<honorific>Fleet Commander</honorific>
			<firstname>Stuart</firstname>
			<surname>Coll</surname>
		</author>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>23 June 2005</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://star-fleet.com/prez/garfield.php3#e17">Garfield #17</ulink></para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>

	<para>MOVIE ERA SHIP CHARTER</para>
	<para>A new Alternate RPG Area is hereby commissioned in Fleet Six, a TOS Movie Era RPG Ship.</para>
	<para>The USS Merrimack, Mariner-class, NCC-2346 is hereby commissioned in Fleet Six as the TOS Movie Era RPG Ship. If for any reason the Merrimack should change its class, it must be decommissioned.</para>
	<para>The USS Merrimack will be structured the same as a Standard Ship, and be commanded by a CO and XO who are appointed the same way as on a Standard Ship and a GM who is appointed in the same way as on a Standard Ship. However, the Merrimack will be set 293 years from today rather than in the standard STF time frame. That places it shortly after the end of the events depicted in "Star Trek VI: The Undiscovered Country." The Merrimack's time frame must honored with respect to technology that is permissible, known species, species present in Starfleet at the time, etc.</para>
	<para>CO and XO positions on the Merrimack will count fully towards any limits in place. The Merrimack will not accept new members to STF. It is a Second Character Only Ship.</para>
	<para>The Merrimack will officially begin service on or about 1 July. It will be reviewed in 90 days on or about 1 October by the President, Fleet Commander, and CO to determine if the Merrimack has been successful in its mission. The President shall have final ruling in this matter. The Merrimack will be reviewed based on the following criteria:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>Has the Ship established an active and healthy Role-Playing environment?</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Has the Ship established itself as a 23rd century ship, with all the anthropological and technological idiosyncrasies of the era.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>If the Merrimack is found to be successful in its mission, it will be considered permanent. It may be decommissioned at a later date should it be found to be irreparably in violation of any of the points of its mission. If the Merrimack is found to have failed in its mission, it will be decommissioned. If the Merrimack is found to have failed in its mission before its scheduled review date, it may be decommissioned prior to its review date. Should the Merrimack be decommissioned at any point, all characters and positions pertaining to it will be eliminated. Promotions given on the Merrimack will remain in effect.</para>

</article>
