<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="charter-moo">
	<title>Member Order and Organization</title>
	<subtitle>"MOO"</subtitle>
	<articleinfo>
		<author role="President">
			<honorific>President</honorific>
			<firstname>Sarah</firstname>
			<surname>Hemenway</surname>
		</author>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>1 April 2007</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://star-fleet.com/prez/hemenway.php#e34">Hemenway #34</ulink></para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Membership</title>
		<para>A Member of STF is defined as an individual who has at least one active role-playing or Gamemaster position within the club.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Club rank structure</title>
		<para>The club rank structure (for out of character usage) of STF is defined as, from junior to senior: Cadet/Ensign, Lieutenant junior grade, Lieutenant, Lieutenant Commander, Commander, Captain, Fleet Captain, Commodore, and Admiral. Cadet and Ensign are equivalent for the purposes of club rank.</para>
		<para>A Member's club rank, below the rank of Captain, is defined as the highest role-playing rank that a Member has achieved since he joined STF. Club rank at and above the rank of Captain is determined by the most recent Presidential Edict. A Member at or above the rank of Captain may be recognized for exemplary role-playing and service to the club by promotion by the President in an Edict to the next highest club rank.</para>
		<para>Character rank is defined as the rank that a Member's individual role-playing character has attained. The rank structure for character rank is, from junior to senior: Civilian, Crewman, Cadet, Ensign, Lieutenant junior grade, Lieutenant, Lieutenant Commander, Commander, Captain, Fleet Captain, Commodore, and Admiral. Alternate Role-playing Areas may have a different character rank system. In the case of the ranks Captain, Fleet Captain, Commodore, and Admiral, no Member shall have a character with a character rank higher than the Member's club rank.</para>		
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Absence from the club</title>
		<para>A Member is determined to be Absent without Leave (AWOL) if he is not within the defined AWOL limits for his club position. A Member who has a club rank of Captain or above may be subject to a club rank penalty for AWOL; each case will be considered individually by the President.</para>
		<para>A Member is entitled to take a Leave of Absence (LOA) if they are unable to post within the defined AWOL limits for his club positions. A Leave of Absence is defined as any period of declared leave from club posting duties that is less than thirty days. Any LOA for a period of less than 30 days will have no effect on an individual's positions; however, multiple LOAs within a short time scale by a Commanding Officer or an Executive Officer may result in the removal of an individual with the approval of the Fleet Commander and the President. The individual's removal from department head and junior officer positions is at the discretion of the appropriate ship's Commanding Officer.</para>
		<para>Any leave of absence of 30 days and beyond is considered to be an Extended Leave of Absence (eLOA). Any leave of absence with an unspecified end date is considered to be an Indefinite Leave of Absence (iLOA). Any individual taking an eLOA or an iLOA understands that no position they hold is guaranteed to remain open for when they return to the club. This covers any position including that of a Commanding Officer (CO) and government positions. This ruling is not absolute and will not cover any individual arrangements that may be subject to approval by either the Fleet Commander or President.</para>
	</section>
</article>