<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">-->
<article id="charter-oed_v">
  <title>Oed V</title>
  <subtitle>Fleet Six</subtitle>
  <articleinfo>
    <author role="President">
      <honorific>President</honorific>
      <firstname>Sarah</firstname>
      <surname>Hemenway</surname>
    </author>
    <author role="Fleet Commander">
      <honorific>Fleet Commander</honorific>
      <firstname>Symon</firstname>
      <surname>Silvester</surname>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>2</revnumber>
        <date>1 August 2006</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/hemenway/#e2">Hemenway #2</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>23 June 2005</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/garfield/#e24">Garfield #24</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>Supercedence of Previous Edicts</title>
    <para>This edict supercedes Garfield #24.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>A new Alternative Roleplaying Area is hereby established in Fleet Six, named Oed V.</para>
    <para>Oed V is a planet-based RPG, set on the planet Oed V, near the Vren Border. It is a joint Starfleet-civilian colony consisting of both Starfleet personnel and civilians.</para>
    <para>Oed V will remain an active Roleplaying Area, provided that it means the following criteria:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Oed V currenly has a healthy roleplaying environment with a cast of reliable players who remain on the whole within the outlined AWOL guidelines.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Oed V has managed to continue its function as a planet-based environment successfully.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>If Oed V should deviate from the criteria set in this edict at any time, she will be decommissioned.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Crew Structure</title>
    <para>The Leader of Oed V both In Character and Out of Character is entitled Governor and may be a Starfleet officer or civilian. The Governor of Oed V will be appointed in the same fashion as a normal CO and counts as a CO position toward any limits in place. The Governor has similar powers and responsibilites to a CO. There will also be a Lieutenant Governor of Oed V will be appointed in the same fashion as a normal XO and counts as a XO position toward any limits in place. Oed V is a second-character-only Roleplaying Environment.</para>
    <para>Oed V includes the standard STF departments for Starfleet characters. Possible swing positions may be added under the Governor's discretion. They may include, but not be limited to the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Head of Police</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Chief Customs Officer</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Head of Construction Services</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Resources</title>
    <para>The Governor of Oed or his appointed authority is required to maintain a resource page regarding the colony. This page may include, but not be limited to the following information:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Geography of Oed V</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>In Character History of Oed V</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Ships Assigned to Oed V</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Oed V Facilities</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This information must be as historically accurate as possible and remain consistent.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Implementation</title>
    <para>The current Governor is retained in his position on the colony.</para>
  </section>
</article>
