<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">-->
<article id="charter-ogawa">
  <title>USS Ogawa</title>
  <subtitle>Fleet One</subtitle>
  <articleinfo>
    <author role="President">
      <honorific>President</honorific>
      <firstname>Jen</firstname>
      <surname>Herr</surname>
    </author>
    <author role="Fleet Commander">
      <honorific>Fleet Commander</honorific>
      <firstname>Symon</firstname>
      <surname>Silvester</surname>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>21 January 2006</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Based on Edict <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/prez/edicts/herr/#e6">Herr #6</ulink></para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <para>The USS Ogawa NCC-64284 is hereby recommissioned as an alternative role playing area in Fleet 1. It is to be solely a medical/hospital ship, McCoy-class medical frigate. Its missions are expected to be predominantly medical in nature and biased toward medical issues and plotlines, and its crew staffing is expected to be biased toward the Medical department. </para>
  <para>If for any reason it should change her class from a medical frigate, it must be decommissioned.</para>
  <para>The USS Ogawa is already in active service and is hereby confirmed to be successful as a medical frigate. It will continue to be judged by the following criteria:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>The Ogawa must maintain an active and healthy roleplaying environment.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The Ogawa must continue to function as a medical frigate.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>As the Ogawa is already an established RPG Area, it will not be required to pass a trial period. It will therefore remain a permanent addition to Fleet 1, but if at any time it deviates from the criteria set in this edict, it must be decommissioned.</para>
  <para>The Ogawa shall have a similar command structure to other Starfleet vessels, including all standard departments, rank structure, and chain of command. As such, RPG Ranks on the Ogawa will count toward Member Rank the same as on Standard Ships, and CO and XO positions on the Ogawa will count fully towards any limits in place.</para>
  <para>Additional Swing personnel will be possible at the CO's discretion, including but not limited to the following:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>Nurse</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Medic</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Forensic Pathologist</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Medical Examiner</para></listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>The current CO and crew of the USS Ogawa are retained in their current positions aboard the ship. The CO may be removed at some later date in accordance with the rules of the site, without penalty to the Ogawa herself.</para>

</article>
