<article class="whitepaper" id="species-bajoran">
	<title>Bajoran</title>
	<subtitle>RACE_SCI_NAME</subtitle>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<!-- For non-custom, this would be the person who wrote/copied the article for STF -->
				<firstname>Mike</firstname>
				<surname>Rouse-Deane</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<keywordset role="stats">
			<keyword role="Homeworld">Bajor</keyword>
			<keyword role="Height (Average)">5' 0"</keyword>
			<keyword role="Weight (Average)">Unknown</keyword>
			<keyword role="Lifespan">Unknown</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<keywordset role="classification">
			<keyword role="type">Canon</keyword>
			<keyword role="source">TNG, DS9</keyword>
			<keyword role="starfleet">Occational</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>25 March 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Unknown</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Abstract</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Homeworld</term>
				<listitem><para>Denev IV</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Height (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>6' 2"</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Weight (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>170 lbs</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Lifespan</term>
				<listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Entry Type</term>
				<listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Source</term>
				<listitem><para>"Encounter at Farpoint" (TNG)</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Found in Starfleet</term>
				<listitem><para>Unlikely</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<sect1>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>An ancient race of humanoids from Bajor III. The Bajorans had a thriving primitive culture in the arts and sciences 25,000 years ago. They slowly developed space travel and colonized their system and several nearby star systems. Almost identical to Terrans except for distintive nose ridges and minor differences in the female reproductive system. The Bajoran race was conquered by the Cardassian Empire in 2328 and formally annexed 2339. Bajoran freedom fighters repulsed the Cardassians in early 2369. Soon afterwards the Bajoran wormhole was discovered in the Denorious Belt. With the enormous economic boon of the only known stable wormhole, the rebuiliding of Bajor has been accellerated.</para>
		<para>Bajoran culture flourished a half-million years ago, when humans on Earth were not yet standing erect. The Bajoran people are deeply spiritual, but their history also recorded many great architects, artists, builders, and philosophers. Bajoran culture declined seriously during decades of Cardassian occupation in the 24th century, during which most Bajorans were driven from their homeworld. Bajorans traveled in space at least eight centuries ago, using Bajoran solar-sail vessels to explore their star system. Some ancient Bajoran space travelers even made it all the way to Cardassia.</para>
		<para>As recently as the 22nd century, Bajoran society was strictly divided into D'jarras, or castes. A family's D'jarra determined its status in society, as well as what occupation its workers could hold. Under Bajoran custom, a person's family name is first, followed by the given name. Most Bajorans wear an ornamental earring, a symbol of their spiritual devotion. Bajoran women carry their children for less than five months. Because they have a relatively short gestation period, they vascularize very quickly. Mother and child form a complex interconnecting network of blood vessels. Bajoran women often have fits of uncontrollable sneezing while pregnant. In Bajoran childbirth, relaxation of the mother is essential. Participants at the birthing ceremony play rhythmic instruments to help her reach a fully relaxed state. When the child arrives, all present verbally welcome the child into the world.</para>
		<para>Bajorans can usually be seen wearing an earing on one of their ears. This wearing of silver earrings is a direct link to the belief in the Pagh, or life force, that can be sensed by the Monks through the ear. Many scientists have taken to not wearing an earring in a break from traditions, they have developed doubts in the Pagh belief even though its predictions are very accurate most of the time. Every Bajoran wearing an earring has a unique design that can link it to the person. Often a characteristic effect or insignia is carried down through the generations of a family. Bajorans are a deeply religious people and somewhat hardened by their experience with the Cardassians. They appear human except for a few ridges on the bridge of their nose.</para>
		<para>Nearly a century ago, in 2328, the aggressive militaristic race of the Cardassians arrived, saying they wanted to help the native populace. There followed years of Military Occupation and slavery for the Bajorans, in which well over 10 Million Bajorans were killed. The religion became their saviour, uniting them against their enemy. Very quickly, small cells of resistance fighters appeared to strike back at the oppressors. Eventually the Cardassians withdrew but most of Bajor's mineral wealth had already been depleted.</para>
		<para>Very soon after the Cardassians left, polluting the wells and destroying homes and even the sacred temples in the process, the Bajoran factionalised and started to squabble over who would lead the free Bajor. The Provisional Government was formed from the chaos and asked the United Federation of Planets to send assistance, giving them the old Cardassian Mining Station in orbit as a base. The base, called Terok Nor by the Cardassians, was named Deep Space Nine by the Federation and Cmdr. Benjamin Sisko sent to command it.</para>
		<para>As the prophesied Emissary, he was instrumental in the discovery of the Wormhole, or more properly referred to as the Celestial Temple of the Prophets. The role of Cmdr Sisko was to protect Bajor and the wormhole from the continuing actions of the Cardassians, and also prepare Bajor for fully joining the UFP.</para>
		<para>A deeply religious people, Bajorans look to their spiritual leader, the Kai, for leadership and guidance. The Bajoran religious faith was a powerful force in their society, and helped give the Bajoran people the spiritual strength to survive the brutal Cardassian oppression. The Bajoran religion believes that ships are safely guided through the wormhole by the Prophets and that the Celestial Temple dwells within the passage. Some conservative Bajoran religious leaders, notably Winn, tried to suppress scientific theories of the wormhole's creation, believing that the teaching of science lessened the religious leaders' political power.</para>
		<para>Traditional Bajoran childbirth requires the mother to achieve a completely relaxed state through breathing exercises, ritual music and incense. This usually takes about an hour and any men in attendance wear knotted neck scarves. The child is born into the world with the following greeting: "Awake child, we await you with love and welcome you into the world."</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Religion</title>
			<para>The Kai's are the highest ranking religious figure on Bajor, selected from the Vedek Assembly from its members on the death of the previous holder. Such is Kai Winn, who was elected such a figure after First Minister Kalem Opren died. However, in 2375, she turned to the side of the Pah-wraith's, trying to release them from the fire caves, as her hatred of the Emissary being a non-Bajoran grew inside. However, Kai Winn died in the fire caves, along with Benjamin Sisko and Gul Dukat. Only 112 Vedeks exist at any one point in time, these positions are also selected by the Vedek Assembly.</para>
			<para>The Prophets are the central figures of the Bajoran faith, transcendent entities who exist in a non-linear time frame. Bajoran faith believes the Prophets to be the embodiment of truth, who reveals their wisdom through visions given by the Orbs. The Prophets are also the ones who replenish the life force of Bajorans, the pagh that allows existence. Bajorans believe that the pagh is a spiritual force inherent to all sentient beings and that the Prophets replenish the pagh of the living from the Celestial Temple.</para>
			<para>With every good side, there is always an evil side, and in the Bajoran religion they are called the Pah-wraiths. The Pah-wraith's once resided in the Celestrial Temple, until they were exposed as false prophets and were banished to the fire caves, though some remain in ornaments and tablets, such as the tablet smashed by Benjamin Sisko on Deep Space Nine, which released both a Prophet and a Pah-wraith. The ceremony was classed as the Reckoning, in which the Prophet and Pah-wraith would battle each other. However, the ceremony was stopped by Kai Winn, before it was resolved and so the Prophet's stated that a terrible event would occur. The Pah-wraith's vision was to take the celestrial temple from the Prophet's, unfortunately, during the final battle in the fire caves, in which Kai Winn and Gul Dukat, who was possessed by a Pah-wraith, battled with Benjamin Sisko, who himself was a prophet, they both dove into the fires and stopped the Pah-wraith's entry into the celestrial temple and allowed Bajor to live peacefully again.</para>
			<para>The Orbs (Tears of the Prophets) are approximately 10,000 years old. The first Orb, with eight others to follow, appeared in the skies of Bajor. Taken as a gift from the Prophets to endow their followers with wisdom and insight, the Orbs were traditionally housed in sacred shrines at temples and monasteries around Bajor. Each Orb has a different function. After the Occupation, only one from the original nine Orbs remained. Through the years, three have been recovered and are currently in the hands of the Bajoran people. A fifth, unknown, orb was discovered by Captain Benjamin Sisko in 2375.</para>
			<para>The Emissary is the title given to the person who would discover the Celestial Temple and speak with the Prophets, then unify the Bajoran people. Commander Benjamin Sisko was announced as the Emissary by Kai Opaka when he had just arrived at the Station. Akorem Laan briefly succeeded Sisko as the Emissary in 2372 when Laan was transported two centuries after his times into the 24nd century by the Prophets. After reinstating the unpopular D'jarra caste system, Sisko challenged Akorem for the title of Emissary, and was ultimately vindicated by the Prophets themselves. Captain Sisko would firmly establish himself as the Emissary of Bajor after the Laan incident.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>History</title>
		<para>500 millennia ago Bajor was already a flourishing civilization, culturally rich and technologically advanced. Their faith gave the people the peace and harmony of life while fostering the philosophers, architects, and builders that are the pride of Bajoran culture.</para>
		<para>10,000 years ago, the first of nine Orbs fell from the sky, and the present Bajoran faith was founded on the wisdom imparted from Orb-generated visions. In between these ancient times and the 22nd century, Bajoran explorers would travel through near-space with their tachyon accelerated space vessels, coming in contact with nearby Cardassia, whose people were then as peaceful and religious as themselves.</para>
		<para>Thousands of years passed. Cardassia Prime became a starved planet that was beset by problems caused by its lack of natural resources. When the military, sickened by the weakness of its civilian government, seized control of the state, they believed that only expansion will allow Cardassians to survive. Ruthless conquest of nearby systems followed, and the Empire lost no time in plotting to annex neighboring Bajor.</para>
		<para>The Bajoran faith could not have prepare them for the superior military forces of Cardassia, and the planet fell to Cardassian forces in 2328. During the years of Cardassian Occupation, which spanned from its formal annexation in 2339 to the withdrawal in 2369, 10 million Bajorans were killed and many times more forced into slave labor in mines and labor camps by the Cardassian occupational government. In 2351 the Cardassians built the mining station Terok Nor in the orbit of Bajor to process minerals from the surface and prepare them for transport.</para>
		<para>Throughout the 30 years of the Occupation, the underground resistance relentlessly bombed and sabotaged Cardassia's organized government, knowing full well the Cardassians would retaliate with three times the ferocity. Resistance cells such as the Shakaar, the Higa Metar, the Khon-Ma and the Ornathia cells engaged the Cardassians in guerrilla warfare in the mountains of Bajor, and despite their vastly inferior numbers, somehow always managed to escape Cardassian pursuit. Though millions died during the Occupation, the violent opposition to Cardassian rule finally made the decision-makers back on Cardassia Prime change their stance on Bajor.</para>
		<para>In 2369, the Bajor-Cardassia Armistice was signed, and Cardassian Supreme Directive 26/45 issued, which provided for the full retreat of Cardassian presence from Bajor. After some initial chaos and anarchy, the newly erected Bajoran Provisional Government signed the Ilvian Proclamation that exiled all and any person who had collaborated with the Occupation's Cardassian forces.</para>
		<para>Though free at last from the authoritarian rule of Cardassia, the world of Bajor was left shattered. Defenseless and struggling to recover from the decades of war and deprivation, the Bajoran provisional government requested the Federation to administer to the operations of Terok Nor, abandoned after the hasty withdrawal. Designated as space station Deep Space Nine by Starfleet, Commander Benjamin Sisko arrived on board with his senior officers to help oversee the rebuilding of Bajor and restore the station to working order. Cardassian policy dictates that anything of value which cannot be taken must be sabotaged or rendered useless and Terok Nor was accordingly trashed by the Cardassians before they left it to the Bajorans.</para>
		<para>Shortly after Sisko's arrival on Deep Space Nine, Kai Opaka announced that he was the long-awaited Emissary. Though quietly skeptical of the whole idea about being a religious icon, Sisko consequently did go on to discover the wormhole and later spoke with the alien entities Bajorans believe to be their Prophets. On a visit to the Gamma Quadrant, Kai Opaka was trapped, and when no trace of her was found, presumed dead. The ensuing race for the position of Kai divided the Bajoran people, with Vedek Winn eventually winning when Vedek Bareil withdrew from the race.</para>
		<para>Civil unrest escalated in 2370, instigated by The Alliance for Global Unity, otherwise known as the Circle. Their activities climaxed when they besieged the Provisional Government and Deep Space Nine. However, it was the highly popular Minister Jarro Essa who had engineered the coup, using the Circle as a front for his designs to eliminate the weak Provisional Government and build a new, stronger Bajor. Jarro had been an outspoken opponent of the Cardassians during the Occupation and equally opposed to the Federation presence on Deep Space Nine. He convinced more than a few Bajoran militia officials to support his cause and lend their military power in the uprising. When Jarro's connection with the Cardassian government was exposed, however, his plans were thwarted and he went into hiding from shame and public outrage over his hypocrisy. Li Nalas, who was liberated from a Cardassian POW camp on Cardassia IV not long before the failed coup, died in the crossfire protecting Commander Sisko during phaser fire on Deep Space Nine.</para>
		<para>Towards the middle of 2370, several million Skreens from the Gamma Quadrant applied for asylum on Bajor, believing it to be their promised land. The Provisional Government decided against having to support so many refugees when the planet was still recovering from the Occupation. The Federation facilitated the Skreen exodus by transporting them to a suitable M Class planet to begin colonization.</para>
		<para>Bajoran colonists on New Bajor fell victim to Dominion forces at the end of the year, their lives and presence eliminated from the colony they had only recently populated. The Dominion clearly showed their intolerance of an incursion into their territory, and as a show of force, easily destroyed the U.S.S. Odyssey, which was on a mission to the Gamma Quadrant to retrieve Cmdr. Sisko, Jake, Quark, and Nog.</para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		<para></para>






The Dominion threat prompted Starfleet to deploy the warship U.S.S. Defiant to Deep Space Nine the following year, serving to protect the station as well as Bajor from seemingly imminent invasions. Bajor and Cardassia formally signed a peace treaty in 2371, ending years of hostility and opening a new chapter in bilateral relations. Exchange of Ambassadors, return of the stolen Orbs and war reparations to Bajor for damages were included in the provisions. Kai Winn would be credited for the treaty signed with Legate Turrel, though it was Vedek Bareil who died closing the talks he had initiated and brought about the treaty.

The year also saw the return of the Orb of Wisdom, courtesy of Grand Nagus Zek, who was paid a small price for his troubles.

Shortly after, First Minister Kalem Opren died, leaving the highest political chair empty. Kai Winn secured the position and became both spiritual leader and political ruler, leaving certain Bajorans skeptical about her monopoly on power. After Kai Winn reacted rashly to the refusal of Shaakar to return a few soil reclamators, Shaakar led his past fellow resistance cell members, Major Kira among them, to a renegade life in the mountains in protest. Winn cracked down by sending in her militia, an action which provoked widespread public disapproval on Bajor. After some running and hiding from the militia, Shaakar convinced its leader, who was also a former resistance fighter, to put down his weapons and seek other options. In the end, Shaakar ran for First Minister and won by an overwhelming victory.

The tension between the Dominion and the Alpha Quadrant powers rose increasingly the following years. The Klingon invasion of Cardassia served to set off a chain of events that eventually escalated into war with the Federation and the dissolving of the Khitomer Accords.

Meanwhile, Bajor was still working towards membership into the United Federation of Planets. During a conference on Deep Space Nine, the Cardassian extremists The True Way made an attempt on First Minister Shaakar's life which was exposed by Lt. Commander Worf.

Later, the title of Emissary was challenged by Akorem, saved from death by the Prophets and sent two centuries forward into 24th century Bajor. Though he assumed the title briefly, the unpopularity of his archaic reforms soon pressed Captain Sisko to reassert himself and resume the title of Emissary. The Prophets were testing their Emissary, and later placed Akorem back into his own time.

The year 2372 marked the beginning of conflict for the Alpha Quadrant, Klingon forces engaged the Federation in warfare, and even on Bajor, the fabled Pah-Wraiths were freed from the fire caves and soon wreaked havoc, loosing no time to attempt the elimination of the Prophets within the Celestial Temple.

In 2373 the Federation Council voted to allow admission of Bajor into the Federation in accord with an agreement reached the year before with First Minister Shakaar. At the ceremony on DS9, Captain Sisko as the Emissary warned against admission at this time and the Council of Ministers voted to delay acceptance.

With Cardassia freed from the iron grip of the Central Command after a successful coup, the new civilian government returned the Orb of Time to Bajor as a gesture of friendship. It was also at about this time that Emissary Captain Sisko experienced a pagh'tem'far and located the lost city B'Hala, from which he realized the urgency of postponing Bajor's entrance into the Federation. Membership into the Federation was postponed by the Bajoran Council of Ministers as a result of the Emissary's warnings.

It was not three months before the civilian government was deposed by Gul Dukat, who promptly joined the Dominion and became the head of the new Cardassian government. By now awareness of the Founder's infiltration has made the Alpha Quadrant apprehensive. Yet, the skilled impostors still almost managed to destroy Bajor and Deep Space Nine by attempting to make the Bajoran sun go nova.

With the Dominion steadily breaking through the Federation/Klingon fleet and gaining ground in its conquest of the Alpha Quadrant, Bajorans became increasingly alarmed by the prospects of a Dominion victory. Kai Winn consulted the Emissary on what course to take, since the Dominion offered a nonaggression pact which would secure the safety of Bajor as long as it remained neutral in the war. Sisko could not make any guarantees about Bajor's security, and advised Winn to stall for time. But eventually, when the Federation pulled out of Deep Space Nine, he told Winn bluntly that he could not make any guarantees for the safety of Bajor and asked her to sign the pact.

While the Dominion and its Cardassian allies occupied Deep Space Nine, again renamed to Terok Nor, the Bajorans were compelled to cooperate. Major Kira remained liaison officer, but the relationship is now Dominion/Bajor, and she came to see that she had in effect become the Collaborator she loathed in her terrorist days.

The Federation retook the station when the Wormhole aliens intervened and prevented Jem'Hadar reinforcements from reaching the Alpha Quadrant, but the war was nowhere near over. With Deep Space Nine as the front line of defense against the Dominion, the Bajoran System was more important than ever.

The wormhole inverted itself and the Prophets seemingly abandoned Bajor when Dukat, possessed by a Pah-Wraith turn the orbs black and destroyed the Celestrial Temple. The turn of events shook Bajor's confidence in its Emissary, but Sisko later recovered the Orb of the Emissary and restored the wormhole.

Towards the end of 2375, Kai Winn saw a vision from the prophets for the first time. She was given the task of the "Restoration of Bajor", and there would be a guide, a "man of the land", who would help her walk the path laid down by them. Ecstatic that the prophets have finally spoken to her, she quickly agreed to do anything for the Prophets. Anjohl, a "simple farmer" visited her at around the same time and she immediately believed him to be the guide. He soon shared her bed and her favors, but in one horrible vision, the "Prophets" turned out to be none other than the Pah-Wraiths. Though frightened at first, Kai Winn tired of the silence of the Prophets and of remaining in the shadow of Sisko, and decided to take the path the Pah-Wraiths laid out for her.

At around the same time, Colonel Kira was sent to Cardassia to help Damar's resistance cell. They who once oppressed Bajor and created people like Kira had become the oppressed themselves, and to add to the irony, Kira would be key in their rebellion against the Dominion. From the once deep hatred of any Cardassian, Kira had learned to not let generalization influence her judgment and though she had no love for Cardassians, she helped the resistance as much as she could. The role she played in the freeing of Cardassia will in the future pave the way for bilateral ties and a repaired relationship between the once enemies.

Kai Winn returned to Bajor after Sisko went against the will of the prophets and married Kassidy Yates, where she began to use her position to access the forbidden Kosst Amojan books. Considered by all Bajorans to be the Book of Evil, it details how to release the Pah-Wraiths from the fire caves, where they were trapped eons ago by the Prophets who now reside in the Celestial Temple. Prodded along by Anjohl, Winn spent many months on her project without success. She could not decipher the book, which consisted of empty pages. When Sobor found out that Anjohl was none other than Dukat surgically altered to appear Bajoran, Winn was shocked beyond reason, and in a dizzied state accidentally stabbed her faithful servant. Frightened at what she'd done, she vowed to destroy the evil book, but the bloody knife in her hand set the book ablaze, and lo, there were Bajoran ideograms on the once empty pages. Dukat she banned from her bed and cast into the streets when he blinded himself by trying to read the Kosst Amojan himself.

Winn eventually read through the book and she took along Dukat, who had been retrieved from the streets, to the fire caves, where she freed the Pah-Wraiths by sacrificing Dukat and reading chants from the book. The Pah-wraiths, however, passed over Winn and favored Dukat, who was again inhabited by a Pah-wraiths. He incinerated Winn and tried to overpower Sisko, who'd come down to confront him. They both tumbled into the depths of the fire cave, and with the book destroyed as well as Dukat, the Emissary's work was finished, and he joined the Prophets in the Celestial Temple. The Emissary had forever sealed away the Pah-Wraiths, and they would no longer harm anyone again, but news of Kai Winn's betrayal will surely have lasting effects on Bajoran religion and politics. The new cooperative spirit between the Cardassians and Bajorans promises a new future where the old archenemies can coexist peacefully, and Bajor's sorrows as an occupied land will be but a faded memory.

	</sect1>
</article>
