<article class="whitepaper" id="species-benzite">
	<title>Benzite</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<!-- For non-custom, this would be the person who wrote/copied the article for STF -->
				<firstname>Jason</firstname>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>25 March 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Unknown</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Abstract</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Homeworld</term>
				<listitem><para>Benzar (Gamma Xertia III, Phedadon)</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Height (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>5' 9"</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Weight (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>150 lbs</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Lifespan</term>
				<listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Entry Type</term>
				<listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Source</term>
				<listitem><para>(TNG)</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Found in Starfleet</term>
				<listitem><para>Unlikely</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>Benzites are a humanoid race whose members require a special breathing apparatus for oxygen atmospheres. This apparatus is worn on their chest with an extension reaching up to just in front of the mouth and nose slit. The slit is wider than the mouth with four whisker-like extensions, much like the Terran catfish. Benzites do not have facial hair, and they have blue-gray skin. They have large, short-pointed ears and in addition, they strongly resemble each other. Benzites are very sincere eager people, however, their eagerness is sometimes perceived as superiority. Benzites tend to be perfectionists, and as part of their eager and perfectionist nature, Benzites will offer advice in improving efficiency. This is one of the reasons that Benzites appear to be acting superior. </para>
		<para>Benzites are not members of the Federation, but carry treaty relations and officer exchanges. Benzites can apply for Starfleet Academy, and many Benzites do. Benzites have an extreme pursuit for knowledge and they tend to excel in Science and Engineering. It is also interesting to note that Benzite space service calls for an officer to withhold unusual findings until an extensive analysis can be run and a resolution is offered. Benzites tend to get depressed if they do something which they perceive as a failure. By 2372 the Benzites had made such medical advances that they were no longer required to use the respiration device in Class-M atmospheres.</para>
		<para></para>
	</section>
</article>
