<article class="whitepaper" id="species-chairosan">
  <title>Chairosan</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <!-- For non-custom, this would be the person who wrote/copied the article for STF -->
        <firstname>Barret</firstname>
        <surname>Vogtman</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>4 August 2001</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Unknown</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
<!--  <indexterm>
    <seealso>
      <link linkend="location-chairosiv">Chairos IV</link>
    </seealso>
  </indexterm>-->
  <section>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Homeworld</term>
        <listitem><para>Chiaros IV</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Height (Average)</term>
        <listitem><para>2 meters</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Weight (Average)</term>
        <listitem><para>98 kg</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Lifespan</term>
        <listitem><para>60 years</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Entry Type</term>
        <listitem><para>Non-Canon</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source</term>
        <listitem><para>"Section 31: Rogue" by Andy Mangels and Michael A Martin</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Found in Starfleet</term>
        <listitem><para>Unlikely</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The Chiarosans are a warrior race and have a very strict honor system, very similar to that of the Klingons. They are very hierarchical and protocol-conscious and can easily be offended. Physically, the race is very strong due to the harsh environments of their home planet, Chiaros IV. Their bodies are covered with a coarse fur in the same areas that a human male has hair. Their bodies are very well defined granting them a physically strong appearance. They are bipedals and all joints appear to be triple jointed granting them an extraordinary range of motion, making them extremely graceful. As with most predators, their teeth are razor sharp, attributing an unnerving quality to even a friendly smile.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    z
    <title>History</title>
    <para>The Chiarosans have not had warp capability for more than a decade, but have become the key race in the Geminus Gulf, which lies just outside the boundaries of both the Federation and Romulan star Empire. Under recently negotiated agreements, neither the Federation nor the Romulans could establish a permanent presence in the Gulf until invited to do so by a space-faring civilization native to the Gulf. As the only warp-capable culture yet known in the Gulf, the Chiarosans have thus become the key to the entire region.</para>
  </section>
</article>
