<article class="whitepaper" id="species-cytherian">
  <title>Cytherian</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <!-- For non-custom, this would be the person who wrote/copied the article for STF -->
        <firstname>Jason</firstname>
        <surname>Lee</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>19 April 2002</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Unknown</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Homeworld</term>
        <listitem><para>A planet near the center of the Galaxy</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Height (Average)</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Weight (Average)</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Lifespan</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Entry Type</term>
        <listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source</term>
        <listitem><para>"The Nth Degree" (TNG)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Found in Starfleet</term>
        <listitem><para>Never</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The Cytherians are curious beings who are explorers. However, they are not ordinary explorers. The Cytherians prefer to stay home and send out probes of advanced technology. These highly advanced probes can reprogram computers and even living beings. In addition, these probes use a propulsion method unknown to Starfleet that does not create any subspace distortions or field emissions. The purpose of these probes are to give information in order to bring other races to them. In this way, the Cytherians explore the galaxy by bringing the galaxy to them. The Cytherian that appeared on the USS Enterprise only showed his head. It appears that it was some type of holographic image or some type of technology beyond the Federation's understanding. This particular Cytherian looked human like, and was very elderly. By the looks of the Cytherians, they appear to have a blue patch in the middle of their foreheads as well as ridges similar to Klingon foreheads. The difference between this particular Cytherian forehead and a Klingon's forehead was that It was wider, flat, and curved in opposite direction from the bottom to the top, which allowed a flat area where the blue patch would be. This Cytherian also had a large flat nose; the ridges on the forehead seems to start where the top of the nose becomes part of the forehead. This Cytherian had white hair and seem to wear his hair with thick strands of hair running down past his face. These strands of hair only extended 1 to 2 inches past the face. Lastly, this Cytherian also had a white beard.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>History</title>
    <para>On Stardate 44704.2, the USS Enterprise-D went to investigate a problem with the Argus Array, on the edge of Federation space. The USS Enterprise-D found an alien probe near the array. When the Enterprise sent out a shuttle, the probe attempted to reprogram the shuttle but failed. However, the probe managed to reprogram Lt. Barclay instead. It was discovered that the probe was unable to reprogram the Argus Array or the shuttlecraft's computers, but it managed to reprogram Lt. Barclay. The probe was able to increase Lt. Barclay's intelligence, creativity and everything else in his brain. In order to save the Argus Array, Lt. Barclay had to connect to the computer using a neural interface on Holodeck 3. Apparently, the probe caused something to change Lt. Barclay where his intelligence would increase bit by bit. So when Lt. Barclay connected to the computer of the USS Enteprise-D, he became the computer. Since his higher level brain functions were in the computer, he was not able to return to his body and unable to disconnect from the computer. When Lt. Barclay connected to the computer of the USS Enterprise-D, he was able to use the graviton emissions from the USS Enterprise's warp nacelles to create a large subspace distortion. This subspace distortion allowed the USS Enterprise to travel to the Cytherians for first contact. The Cytherians did not pose no threat and only wanted an information exchange. Only one Cytherian appeared on the Bridge of the USS Enterprise-D. He did not physically appeared, but only the image of his head was shown. They seem to be peaceful and did not mean any harm. They were able to return Lt. Barclay to normal, however it seems Lt. Barclay has retained some of the intelligence and confidence that he picked up from this experiance. Lt. Barclay, once he was normal again, was able to explain to Captain Picard about the Cytherians. The information exchanged from the Cytherians will take decades for Federation sciencists to analyse. The USS Enterprise-D had spent 10 days in the company of the Cytherians before returning to Federation space.</para>
  </section>
</article>