<article class="whitepaper" id="species-elven">
	<title>Elven</title>
	<subtitle>Hunteris Hubonis</subtitle>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<!-- For non-custom, this would be the person who wrote/copied the article for STF -->
				<firstname>Matt</firstname>
				<surname>Evans</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>23 July 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Unknown</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Abstract</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Homeworld</term>
				<listitem><para>Creslin V</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Height (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>5' 5"</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Weight (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>130 lbs</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Lifespan</term>
				<listitem><para>260 years</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Entry Type</term>
				<listitem><para>Custom</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Found in Starfleet</term>
				<listitem><para>Never</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>An independent mining corporation first discovered the Elven race after an expedition was sent to their home world. The Elven name was actually chosen for them by some of the miners who compared them to legend and myth. The name has stuck ever since. They have a mastery of language skills and quickly picked up English from the miners. Their native language consists of an almost bird-like whistling quality. An Elf is short and relatively small in size, but is very athletic and graceful. They are the best at hunting, tracking, running, and a variety of other physical sports. They have very keen senses and are much better than humans in reflexes and agility. They do not have a great amount of strength, though, but make up for it in other areas. It is not very likely to see very many Elves outside of their planet because their society is a very close knit community. However, a few of the more prestigious families can afford to send their sons and daughters off to train elsewhere.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>History</title>
		<para>Their social structure evolved to what it is today after several bloody civil wars. Cooperation became the main goal in their society. It could be compared to Communism on Earth except for the fact that it actually works. Their economy was based upon a barter system as opposed to currency. A fair system of administration was established by having representatives from each family unit attend the regional unit council meetings. A lot of focus was spent on achieving mastery of agriculture and environmental study. The race has a proverbial 'green thumb', but took several decades to achieve this. Not much else is known of their history prior to First Contact.</para>
		<para>As far as the recorded history goes, the Elven society was remarkably peaceful. Most of the family units cooperated with each other to make the region units. Each region units was self-sufficient, but quite a bit of trading and commerce happened between each region. After being discovered by the miners a massive change technology wise occurred. In exchange for the rights to mine the planet and the knowledge of the surrounding area, the mining corporation invested considerable resources to improve the quality of life on the planet. Spaceports, factories, and processing plants were all constructed and quite a few jobs were opened to the population. However, there was a stipulation that the mining and refining of the material not harm the environment. Schools were built, but until present only the most fortunate received any real education.</para>
	</section>
</article>
