<article class="whitepaper" id="species-flarn">
	<title>Flarn</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<!-- For non-custom, this would be the person who wrote/copied the article for STF -->
				<firstname>Larry</firstname>
				<surname>Garfield</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>12 April 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Unknown</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<!--<indexterm>
		<seealso>
			<link linkend="power-flarn">Flarn Regime</link>
		</seealso>
	</indexterm>-->
	<section>
		<title>Abstract</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Homeworld</term>
				<listitem><para>Flick (Iota Zeta II)</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Height (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>1.8 meters</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Weight (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>78.4 kg</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Lifespan</term>
				<listitem><para>84 years</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Entry Type</term>
				<listitem><para>Custom</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Found in Starfleet</term>
				<listitem><para>Never</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>The Flarn are basically humanoid, with skin that is a pale mint green. Their only other identifying feature is a brow ridge that runs from their left ear up to their forehead and across the forehead, to descent symmetrically on the other side to their right ear. All males have chocolate brown hair, while all females have white hair.</para>
		<para>Male Flarn are stronger and more muscular than their female counterparts, and as such make up the bulk of their armed forces. However, the 26% of the military that is female is quite feared, even by their male comrades. It is possible that the maternal instinct is part of the increased aggressiveness of the Flarn female over the male of the species. A female Flarn is more likely to shoot first and ask questions later.</para>
		<para>A typical Flarn is stronger than their human counterpart, roughly on par with an angry Vulcan. However, there is no such concept as "honor" or a "fair fight" in Flarn culture, so they have no qualms about foregoing their physical advantage to shoot someone in the back with a disruptor. Flarn are decidedly self-interested, aggressive, and ambitious. Every Flarn's lifelong dream is to be supreme despot of the universe, simply for the power trip involved. However, pragmatism typically keeps them loyal to their chosen military, making bribery difficult in most cases.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>History</title>
		<para>The Flarn are a warrior race that spent most of their history at war with themselves. As such, they devoted most of their scientific endeavors to machines of war. They apparently developed photon torpedoes before they developed space ships to put them on. The entire planet was unified only in 2343, when one faction developed basic space travel. They used their new power to oppress the rest of the factions, and have since formed a single, cohesive, militaristic oligarchy.</para>
		<para>As they are new to space travel, their fastest ships are capable of only warp 3.2 sustained, and 3.6 max for 2 hours. However, due to their violent history and lengthy arms race, their weapons and shielding are superior to Starfleet's.</para>
		<para>The Flarn are the sole species in the small Flarn Regime.</para>
	</section>
</article>
