<article class="whitepaper" id="species-tholian">
  <title>Tholian</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <!-- For non-custom, this would be the person who wrote/copied the article for STF -->
        <firstname>Mike</firstname>
        <surname>Rouse-Deane</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>27 January 2002</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Approved by Unknown</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Homeworld</term>
        <listitem><para>Tholia</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Height (Average)</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Weight (Average)</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Lifespan</term>
        <listitem><para>Unknown</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Entry Type</term>
        <listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source</term>
        <listitem><para>"The Tholian Web" (TOS), "Life Support" (DS9)</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Found in Starfleet</term>
        <listitem><para>Never</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>A Beta quadrant species, the Tholians are one of the relatively few major non-Humanoid races in our section of the galaxy. In appearance they are multifaceted solids, apparently existing at a very high temperature. Tholians tend to be aggressive, territorial and extremely punctual beings who do not welcome intrusions into their space. A silk, known as Tholian silk, is highly prized as it is virtually frictionless and is known to be made within their homeworld, Tholia.</para>
    <para>They are highly advanced sentient beings, apparently crystalline species, non-humanoid in appearance and extremely territorial in disposition. They hail from a hot planet by Human standards, probably not Class-M. Together, two Tholian ships can literally spin a web of energy in space in order to trap an enemy vessel, after which the web is then drawn together, constricting and finally destroying the vessel inside.</para>
    <para>On stardate 5693.2, the U.S.S. Enterprise NCC-1701 made first contact with this species. Tholians are a hive-mind and known for their punctuality. One of the independent border races that could have been dragged into a Klingon civil war, due to their proximity. During a period of renewed conflict with the United Federation of Planets in 2253, they attacked a starbase and killed the entire complement, except civilian advisor Kyle Riker, who refused to give up survival. In a battle simulation during his Academy days, Riker figured out the sensory blind spot of a Tholian ship and hid there. However, tensions have eased enough for the Tholians to send an ambassador to space station Deep Space Nine, in talks with the Federation for hopefully peace with the species.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>History</title>
    <para>The USS Enterprise encountered the Tholians in 2267 while investigating the loss of the USS Defiant in an interphase region. The Tholians demanded an explanation for the Starship's presence, and initially agreed to allow the Enterprise to remain in the area. When the ship was unable to provide proof of the Defiant's presence in the area the Tholians attacked the ship. The Enterprise proved militarily superior to the Tholian vessels, but was almost trapped within one of the forcefield webs, a system designed to enclose a vessel within a network virtually unbreakable strands.</para>
    <para>In 2353 the Tholians attacked and nearly destroyed a Federation starbase, killing all but one of its complement. As recently as 2355 tensions remained high enough that Starfleet routinely trained against Tholian warships in simulations. Tensions remained sufficiently high that it was feared that they might become involved in the Klingon civil war, but eventually relations with the Federation were established and in 2371 a Tholian Ambassador visited Deep Space Nine. A Tholian observer was present at the ill fated Antwerp conference on Earth in 2372 when a bomb destroyed the conference hall.</para>
  </section>
</article>
