<article class="whitepaper" id="species-trill">
	<title>Trill</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<!-- For non-custom, this would be the person who wrote/copied the article for STF -->
				<firstname>Philip</firstname>
				<surname>Stonness</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>25 March 2002</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Unknown</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Abstract</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Homeworld</term>
				<listitem><para>Trill</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Height (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>5' 6"</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Weight (Average)</term>
				<listitem><para>157 lbs</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Lifespan</term>
				<listitem><para>115 years</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Entry Type</term>
				<listitem><para>Canon</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Found in Starfleet</term>
				<listitem><para>Common</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>A unique "joined race" whose humanoid members have provided host bodies for small soft-bodied entities in a symbiotic relationship. Trills have spotted skin areas beside the vertical hairline that follow down the Trill body.</para>
		<para>The symbiont body is a foot-long purplish lump of cranial and exoskeletal tissue, some are susceptible to damage by transporter beam. In emergencies, a symbiont can survive in stasis for only a matter of two hours maximum. In extreme cases, a human body can serve as a temporary host for no more then a few days.</para>
		<para>Since the symbiont integrates each new host's personality with its own after joining, Trill relationships are often hard for single-unit species to deal with and sometimes don't survive the change and thus a relationship that existed with a previous host is discouraged for a host. Trills are usually very responsible and moderate or reserved in personality; the symbionts don't seek romance and try to adhere to a "higher plane," feeling it a nuisance and a weakness of the young - although the host body occasionally indulges. The symbiont does carry memories of time shared with each of its hosts, except this does not mean a joined Trill carries the responsibilites and obligations a previous host did, and each new combination - aside from gender, height and weight - carries a different blood type, metabolism, nervous system, and brain wave pattern. The complex brain carries two cerebral nuclei - one in each being, linked together - whose brain wave patterns can each be scanned separately as well as together. The two are biologically interdependent; at 93 hours after their joining, neither can survive without the other. A Trill host's hands feel cold-blooded to the touch; their more overtly developed senses include identifying a known individual only by the audible rhythm of footsteps.</para>
		<para>The humanoid host species' unruly children are not above throwing rocks at windows, just like their Human and Bajoran counterparts, at least. To other races, Trill may seem arrogant side. Only one Trill in ten is chosen to be joined to the "thousands" of symbionts, but those not joined still lead normal, productive lives. The brains of hosts produce endorphins as in the human brain. Thousands of symbionts live on Trill. Joined Trills are allergic to insect bites, since the biochemical connections of the symbiont and host can't tolerate the toxins. They are more resistant to a noxious paralyzing volcanic gas found on planet LS VI than other humanoids such as Bajorans. Among outworlders, they have been in contact with Klingons at least since 2289.</para>
		<para>A Trill's lineal or family name follows the given name, as is done on Earth, but a host drops his lineal name in favor of the symbiont's. People at the Symbiosis Commission worry that the symbionts would be bartered as commodities if the truth were known that half the population could be hosts, rather than the 1-in-1,000 ratio officially quoted and the reason behind the rigorous selection and training program. Social role equality seems apparent among the population, at least in medicine, with doctors and nurses of both genders.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>History</title>
		<para>On the Enterprise NCC-1701-D it was first discovered by the Federation that some Trills were joined. This happened when Odan was involved in an attack while in a shuttle, and was severly inhured. Doctor Beverly Crusher found the symbiont while examining Odan, and soon they had ask assistence by the Trill government to save the Odan symbiont. </para>
	</section>
</article>
