<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="areasofinterest">
	<title>Areas of interest</title>
	<para>There is more to STF than government and roleplaying. It's hard to believe, but it's true. Following is a list of areas you may want to explore:</para>
	<sect1 id="oocarea">
		<title>WeBB OOC</title>
		<para>Accessible from every fleet's ship menu, the WeBB OOC area is a place for STF members to just cut up and be silly. The topics of conversation range from last week's Enterprise episode to the supremacy of Coke over Pepsi to favorite flavors of Jello (sic).</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="command">
		<title>Command Area</title>
		<para>Are you interested in what's going on behind the scenes of STF? Do you have an idea you want to share? Or maybe a problem you need resolving? Then check out Starfleet Command. Located within the Command fleet, this is the public arena in which the government operates. Topics are restricted to official STF matters.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="irc">
		<title>Internet Relay Chat</title>
		<para>Feel like chatting live with the personalities of STF? Then point your browser to <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/id/irc/">Internet Relay Chat</ulink>.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="archives">
		<title>Archives</title>
		<para>STF has been around a long time. It started as a message board section on Prodigy back in around 1991. In the late 90s, with the growing popularity of the World Wide Web, Mike Bourdaa wrote a program (effWebb) that would enable STF to have an Internet presence. He called this Web-based bulletin board system WeBB, and it went online August 1, 1997, with STF's Third Fleet (Fleets One and Two remained on Prodigy until late 1998).</para>
		<para>Every post made on the WeBB from that first day is archived. If you want to check out the evolution of STF, what a ship was like way back when, or find a post you wrote a month ago, head to the <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/archives/">Archives</ulink>. Here you'll find all posts zipped and categorized by fleet and ship.</para>
		<para>Typically, posts are archived monthly. Of note: Any ship's topics that are empty at the time of archiving are deleted unless their mortality is changed. Toggling topic immortality is at CO's discretion.</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
