<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="government">
	<title>The government</title>
	<para>STF is best described as an elected dictatorship. Every eight months, the membership is welcome to participate in a presidential election. After a month of campaigns and primaries, the membership elects the ticket it wants as president/vice president of STF.</para>
	<para>Once in office, the president can do whatever he wants to the club. There is no regulation in place obligating the president to act in a certain manner. Nor is there any official way to remove a president who is failing in his duties. Short of disappearing, there is nothing established that a president can do to guarantee removal from office.</para>
	<para>The first thing a president typically does is name his cabinet. This is made up of directors of various departments and the fleet commander for each of the seven fleets. A Fleet Commander must be a current or previous captain within the fleet he's appointed to run. His primary job is making sure the fleet runs smoothly. He's responsible for selecting captains for the ships within his fleet (which the president appoints), and he's also responsible for coordinating the GMs.</para>
	<para>Currently, the cabinet is made up of seven Fleet Commanders, and the Academy Commandant, Engineering Director, Gamemaster Director, Internet Director, and Personnel Director.</para>
	<para>The Academy Commandant (ACmdt) is in charge of both STF's <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/acad/">Academy Courses</ulink> and the Academy training ships. A person who passes an Academy course has all his characters within that discipline promoted to Lieutenant j.g.</para>
	<para>The Engineering Director (EDir) is in charge of ship and technology designs used in our roleplaying arena. In order to keep ourselves away from possible copyright infringment issues with Paramount, STF does not use any of the ships or characters in the Star Trek franchise. All ships are designed by STF members. If you're interested in ship design, be sure to check out the <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/ed/">Engineering Department</ulink>. For discussion on current projects, go to the Engineering ship within the Command Area.</para>
	<para>Once upon a time, the Gamemaster Director (GMDir) was in charge of placing GMs on all the ships of STF. As the club grew, that burden became too much. Now the system is run on the fleet level, with FComms handling GM assignment. Today's GMDir is in charge of the GM Training program, maintaining the IC Database, and providing help and guidance to those who want to run sims. If you're interested in being a GM, the GMDir is the man to see. The GM department is accessible from the Command section of the fleet menu.</para>
	<para>The Internet Director (IDir) heads the <ulink url="http://www.star-fleet.com/id/">Internet Department</ulink> and is in charge of how the site looks. His job is to keep the pages updated, or see to it those who write them keep them updated. He also handles server administration.</para>
	<para>The Personnel Director (PDir) is responsible for getting new members assigned to ships. He also helps replace lost passwords. In some cases, he also assists players looking to add additional characters to other ships. Typically, however, if you want to either transfer your character to a different ship or add a second character to your repetoire, you email the CO of the ship in which you're interested. The Personnel Department has several resources helpful to old and new members alike. It's accessible within each fleet's dropdown.</para>
</chapter>
