<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="trainingships">
	<title>The training ships</title>
	<sect1 id="program">
		<title>The Program</title>
		<para>The Academy-run training ship program offers new members an opportunity to learn the ins and outs of STF roleplaying within a nurturing environment. Players are taught using an immersion, hands-on technique where they roleplay as a member of the crew from Day One, with encouragement and instruction from the ship's senior staff.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="who">
		<title>Who's it for?</title>
		<para>The training program is for new members who want to learn the ropes before participating on a mainstream ship, base, or planet.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="how">
		<title>How does it work?</title>
		<para>New members who request the training ship option on their join form are attached to one of the two training ships, provided there is room. To maintain the nurturing atmosphere of the ships, a maximum of three junior officers per department is permitted. Sometimes new members must either accept a position within their second-choice department or wait for an opening on one of the ships.</para>
		<para>Once aboard, the player is a cadet and under the direct supervision of both his DH and the ship's CNS. He begins roleplaying upon arrival, receiving help and encouragement from other members of the senior staff as the sim progresses.</para>
		<para>The chain of command on the training ships is different from other RP arenas within STF. The XO is the defacto captain of the ship. He handles all administrative duties, including reports to the Academy Commandant, AWOLs, complaints, etc. The ship's CNS is the Dean of Students, as it were, and is responsible for the cadets.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graduation">
		<title>Graduation</title>
		<para>Each sim runs for about three months. At the end of each sim, all cadets are evaluated by the senior staff. Cadets who have been on board for over a month and who have demonstrated an understanding of how roleplaying is done in STF graduate from the program and are promoted to Ensign.</para>
		<para>The top cadet in each department, or in the case of equally talented players, the most senior cadet remains aboard the training ship as a DH. All others are transferred to mainstream ships. The Academy Commandant is responsible for finding posts for all training ship graduates.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="co">
		<title>Captain in training</title>
		<para>In addition to training new members, the training ships also provide mainstream XOs with a chance to captain a ship. The Academy Commandant selects a sitting XO for the CO position.</para>
		<para>Trainee COs are the captain of the vessel IC, but OOC administrative duties are handled by the permanent training ship XO.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="rules">
		<title>Rules</title>
		<para>Because of the on going demand for training positions, cadets are forbidden from roleplaying on any other ship until they graduate. Cadets who join other ships before graduating from the training vessels are expelled from the training program.</para>
		<para>The high demand also requires a judicious handling of AWOLs. Cadets must post once every seven days. Cadets who fail to post within this time frame are contacted by a member of the senior staff and given a chance to return to active duty. If the player fails to return, and offers no explanation for the absence, he is removed from the roster. Except for special cases, no cadet should remain on the roster after 14 days of inactivity.</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
