<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="techmanual.xslt"?>
<article class="specification" id="cutlass">
	<title>Cutlass-class</title>
	<articleinfo>
		<authorgroup role="Maintainer">
			<author>
				<firstname>Brandon</firstname>
				<surname>Irvine</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Primary">
			<author>
				<firstname>Brandon</firstname>
				<surname>Irvine</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<authorgroup role="Original">
			<author>
				<firstname>Brandon</firstname>
				<surname>Irvine</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword role="service">NPC</keyword>
			<keyword role="category">Fighter</keyword>
			<keyword role="variant">Medium</keyword>
			<keyword role="mark">I</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1</revnumber>
				<date>28 November 2003</date>
				<revdescription>
					<para>Approved by Engineering Director Barry Vogtman</para>
				</revdescription>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
	</articleinfo>
	<sect1>
		<title>History and Mission Overview</title>
		<para>With many Starfleet fightercraft beginning to lose their effectiveness in combat, Starfleet R&amp;D decided to look for a new craft that could achieve most of the same objectives and at the same time be smaller and more effective.  AST Shipyards submitted this design that was approved by Starfleet R&amp;D on Stardate 03101.0.  The Cutlass-class medium fightercraft has the following mission objectives.</para>
		<simplelist>
			<member>Interception of enemy fighters.</member>
			<member>Support of capital ships.</member>
			<member>Reconniasince duty.</member>
			<member>Escort of friendly ships.</member>
			<member>Standard Patrol duty.</member>
		</simplelist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Structure and Construction</title>
		<para>The Cutlass-class features a duranium/tritanium hull.  The designers at AST decided on a design that featured a cigar shaped body, round at the nose and flat at the back.  Wings extend from the body, and they have dimensions of 4m by 6m by 1 m.  The dimensions of the ship are 9.5m by 8.5m by 6m.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Science and Remote Sensing Systems</title>
		<para>The Cutlass uses a computer core similar to the Type-X shuttlecraft.  The unit is made up of 5 polled processor segments.  In case of failure of this system, the pilot is a) in trouble, and b) should immediately eject from the craft.  The fighter?s sensors are taken from Type-X shuttlecraft.  Cutlass-class craft are unable to detect cloaked vessels without the aid of the mothership?s sensors.  Sensors are located in the forward section, aft of the phasers.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Impulse Propulsion Systems</title>
		<para>Since the Cutlass is incapable of faster than light travel, it relies on warp capable carriers for transport to new engagements.  Microfusion generators power the engines of the Cutlass.  The fighter takes the Reaction Control System packages from type-IX shuttlecraft for manueverability, allowing it to outmanuever many fighters currently used by the major powers in the galaxy.</para>
		<para>The maximum speed for the Cutlass is .30c, where c is the speed of light.  It can attain this speed from a dead stop in 10 seconds, but it takes 13 seconds to slow to a dead stop from .30c.  This is considered very good speed, to cover the entire spedometer, as it is, twice in 23 seconds.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Tactical Systems</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Defensive Shields</title>
			<para>The Cutlasses basic defensive systems, shields and signal jamming devices, are the same as those in most shuttlecraft.  The shields? Maximum Graviton Load (continuous) is 30 MegaWatts.  Their Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate is 845 killowatts.  The Cutlass includes 1.5-cm thick ablative armor over the engines and the torpedo bay, and 1 cm thick over the cockpit, wings and computer core.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Phaser Systems</title>
			<para>The phaser armament consists of two Type V pulse emitters housed in the nose of the craft.  A small Type IV emitter covers the ships backside.  It is located directly beneath the microtorpedo bay.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Torpedo Systems</title>
			<para>The weaponry systems on the Cutlass are significant.  Each wing has one microtorpedo launcer, slung beneath it.  The microtorpedo bay holds 50 microtorpedoes, enough for 25 per launcher.  The fighter can fire 2 torpedoes every 15 seconds, but only does so in a very intense fight.  In normal situations, such as convincing a renegade freighter to power down, the pilot of the craft should only need to use up to five (5) torpedoes. </para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Command and Support Systems</title>
		<para>The cockpit is located directly behind the sensors.  Inside the cockpit there are three consoles.  The one on the pilot?s left gives sensor readouts.  The console directly in front of the pilot contains tactical readouts.  The console on the right contains system status readouts.  Also included is a viewscreen.  This viewscreen has a standard mode and a tactical mode, which transmits sensor blips onto a grid.  The pilot uses a joystick, similar to ones used in 20th and 21st century jet fighters, to pilot the ship and fire the weapons.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Utility Systems</title>
		<para>When drawing up the plans for the craft, it was decided to eject the lifeboat by means of explosive charges placed around the rocket, a safe distance away from the air tanks on the bottom of the pod.  Once the pilot has ejected, there can be no immediate attachment.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Crew Support Systems</title>
		<para>Cutlass class fighters use subspace communication equipment that includes encoded channel systems that allow for safe communication between pilots trying to co-ordiante assaults.</para>
		<para>Atmospheric Recycling Systems located behind the cockpit provide air to the pilots.  Additional air is stored in tanks beneath the cockpit, enough for one hour.  This air is used only when the cockpit lifeboat is ejected. Since not all pilots are human, alternative environment survival equipment is shipped with the fighters.</para>
		<para>Like most fighters, Cutlass class ships have a cockpit that is designed to separate and act as a lifeboat in case of immenent fighter destruction.  Propulsion for this lifeboat is achieved through use of a small ion rocket.  A small emergency distress beacon is attached to the cockpit.  Survival rations for 2 days are located beneath the pilot?s seat, incase of landing on a moon or other celestial body with any sort of atmosphere.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Technical Specifications</title>

		<sect2>
			<title>Dimensions and Structure</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Length"> 9.5 meters</member>
				<member role="Beam (Width)"> 8.5 meters</member>
				<member role="Height">6 meters</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Crew Complement</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Pilot">1</member>
    			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Computer Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Core">Isolinear data core</member>
				<member role="Chipset">250 isolinear chips</member>
				<member role="Operating System">Starfleet Library Computer Access and Retrieval System (LCARS)</member>
				<member role="User Interface">MAJEL</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Impulse Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Full Impulse">0.30c</member>
				<member role="Accellerate">10 seconds</member>
				<member role="Decellerate">13 seconds</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Defensive Systems</title>
			<simplelist>
				<member role="Shield Maximum Graviton Load (Continuous)">X30 MegaWatts</member>
				<member role="Shield Maximum Energy Dissipation Rate">845 kilowatts</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Offensive Systems</title>
			<simplelist role="Micro-Torpedoes">
				<member role="Torpedo Tubes">2</member>
				<member role="Standard Payload (total)">50 micro-torpedoes</member>
			</simplelist>
			<simplelist role="Phasers">
				<member>2 Type-V Pulse Phaser Cannons</member>
				<member>1 Type-IV Pulse Phaser Cannon</member>
			</simplelist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Conclusion</title>
		<para>AST has put the Cutlass-class medium fightercraft into mass production.  The fighter will serve as an assault ship against enemy targets, perform reconnieters, escort ships and enact patrols.  With its high defensive AND offensive capabilities, this well-rounded ship will become a Starfleet dynasty in the coming years.</para>
	</sect1>
</article>
